<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Erik Ramsgaard Wognsen]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/"/>
  <updated>2022-12-15T21:30:13+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.erw.dk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Ramsgaard Wognsen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Avatar: The Way of Water]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2022/12/15/avatar-the-way-of-water/"/>
    <updated>2022-12-15T21:23:34+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2022/12/15/avatar-the-way-of-water</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/avatar2.jpg" title="Picture shows a scene from &#34;Avatar: The Way of Water&#34; with Na'vi people and creatures on a beach" alt="Picture shows a scene from &#34;Avatar: The Way of Water&#34; with Na'vi people and creatures on a beach"></p>

<p>Back in December 2009, I saw the premiere of the movie Avatar, and was
completely enraptured by this beautiful fictional blue world. I went to the
cinema to watch it multiple times. I studied <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Na%CA%BCvi_language">Na&#8217;vi</a>, the language
constructed for the movie (which has a real grammar behind its pleasant alien
sound). I ordered the movie for pickup at Blockbuster at the midnight DVD
release (yes, a physical Blockbuster store!) I just absolutely adored the
movie. Fast-forward to the present, and we finally got to watch the sequel,
Avatar: The Way of Water.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This post is not a review, or at least not a very comprehensive one. It is just
a short praise of a movie that managed to transport me 13 years back, back to a
time before I was a dull grown-up with a mortgage. Back to when a good movie
meant a movie <em>I</em> enjoyed, rather than one that critics enjoyed.</p>

<p>Did the movie have flaws? Yes.</p>

<p>Did I love it? Yes.</p>

<p>Did I shed a tear? Yes.</p>

<p>Am I going to watch it again? Yes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ioniq Efficiency]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2022/11/29/ioniq-efficiency/"/>
    <updated>2022-11-29T08:18:04+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2022/11/29/ioniq-efficiency</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/hyundai_ioniq_electric_2020_leaves.jpg" title="Picture shows the Hyundai Ioniq Electric's aerodynamic profile in front of some autumn leaves" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve driven the <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2021/05/02/hyundai-ioniq-electric/">Hyundai Ioniq Electric</a> for two years now, and it&rsquo;s
time for some more stats. While the car model is not for sale anymore, it will
exist on the used car market for many years to come, and I&rsquo;m going to continue
documenting my experiences with it here. Despite being discontinued, the car
remains one of the most energy efficient mass market vehicles on the roads
today.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The Ioniq Electric reports energy use per distance (e.g., kWh/100km) or
distance traveled per energy amount (e.g., km/kWh), depending on your
preference. The car has three counters: A trip with automatic reset (after four
hours of parking), a trip with manual reset, and a long-term counter with
manual reset. I reset the long-term counter a couple of times, so I do not have
the car&rsquo;s own efficiency value for the past two years. But I do have a log of
all the times I charged the car, so I know how much energy I put into the
battery and how far I drove. This gives me an overall vehicle efficiency of
6.46&nbsp;km/kWh.</p>

<p>This value includes all the energy spent under all of the real-world conditions
of the shifting Danish weather, HVAC use (heating, ventilation, and air
conditioning), tires (AllSeasonContact), driving styles and speeds, etc. The
figure is the vehicle efficiency and so does not include charging losses. It
does however include the energy used by the car while it is parked, which I
estimate to be around 50&nbsp;kWh/year. (I didn&rsquo;t get the Bluelink option to
make the Ioniq internet-connected. An app-enabled online car could use (much)
more energy while parked.) By correcting for the assumed 50&nbsp;kWh/year
drain, I get a driving-only efficiency of 6.83&nbsp;km/kWh (still including
HVAC and everything else while driving). In the table below, I compare my
performance with the WLTP results and the <a href="https://ev-database.org/car/1165/Hyundai-IONIQ-Electric">Electric Vehicle Database</a>&rsquo;s
Real Range (also driving only) numbers:</p>

<div class="next-table-sidescroll next-table-striped"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:left;">                     </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Vehicle&nbsp;efficiency</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Vehicle&nbsp;consumption</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Average&nbsp;range</strong> </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:left;"> <strong>WLTP</strong>            </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 8.13 km/kWh </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">               12.3 kWh/100km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 311 km </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:left;"> <strong>My&nbsp;driving</strong> </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 6.83 km/kWh </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">               14.6 kWh/100km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 262 km </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:left;"> <strong>EVDB</strong>            </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 6.54 km/kWh </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">               15.3 kWh/100km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 250 km </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><br />
The table also shows the range which is calculated as the efficiency multiplied
by the usable battery size which is 38.3&nbsp;kWh. (If the range seems too low
for you, Hyundai are on their way to fix it with the upcoming
<a href="https://ev-database.org/car/1718/Hyundai-IONIQ-6-Long-Range-2WD">Ioniq&nbsp;6</a> sedan which is expected to keep the efficiency of the
Ioniq Electric while almost doubling its range.) I do not report my car&rsquo;s own
range estimation as it is not representative of the long-term. It depends only
on recent driving conditions, as well as HVAC considered either as turned off
or with its instantaneous power draw, neither of which are long-term
representative.</p>

<p>The results give me a lot of confidence in EVDB to not overestimate efficiency
and range, like the WLTP often does. My results being better than EVDB might be
down to the fact that I drive slightly less on motorways/highways than an
average driver, or that the Danish weather is slightly warmer than in the EVDB
model. Speaking of the weather, let&rsquo;s look at how efficiency changes with the
seasons.</p>

<a name="Efficiency.over.time"></a>
<h2>Efficiency over time</h2>

<p>The following diagram shows the driving efficiency average for each two-month
period (Nov-Dec, Jan-Feb, etc.) for the past two years, ranging from 4.7 to
8.4&nbsp;km/kWh.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/ioniq_efficiency_1.png" title="Graph shows efficiency is lowest in winter and highest in summer" ></p>

<p>In the next diagram I add the daytime air temperature in my region of
Nordjylland, Denmark. (<a href="https://www.dmi.dk/vejrarkiv/manedens-sasonens-og-arets-vejr/tabeller-maned/">Data source</a>. I calculate/approximate daytime
temperature as the average between (1) the average daily peak temperature in
the period and (2) the overall average temperature of the period.)</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/ioniq_efficiency_2.png" title="Graph shows efficiency approximately follows daytime air temperature" ></p>

<p>The efficiency correlates fairly well with the temperature within the
0&ndash;20&deg;C range, but the efficiency actually rises faster than the
temperature in the spring. This could be caused by the spring sunshine:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/ioniq_efficiency_3.png" title="Graph shows sunshine is high in both spring and summer" ></p>

<p>It might be that the sun dries wet roads faster and slightly increases the road
and tire temperature compared with the air, improving efficiency. Either way,
here&rsquo;s the same diagram with the efficiency turned into range, from 179 to
323&nbsp;km:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/ioniq_efficiency_4.png" title="Graph same as previous, with range instead of efficiency on vertical axis" ></p>

<p>The efficiency at a given time of year is still just an average of different
driving styles and speeds. Here&rsquo;s how speed affects efficiency.</p>

<a name="Efficiency.and.speed"></a>
<h2>Efficiency and speed</h2>

<p>I tested the efficiency of my car at different speeds. On a calm and sunny
Sunday at the end of May, I drove a motorway round trip three times at
different speeds. I started at 50% state of charge, then drove the 46.6&nbsp;km
loop and charged back up to 50%, then repeated two more times.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/ioniq_efficiency_E45.jpg" title="Picture shows my motorway round trip route on a satellite image map" ></p>

<p>The Danish Meteorological Institute reported 21°C (in the shade), while my car
(in the sun) said 24°C. Without using the air conditioning, I drove on the E45
motorway from the Clever charger at exit 33 Haverslev to exit 36 Onsild and
back. Of the 46.6&nbsp;km round trip, 43.4&nbsp;km (93%) were motorway, while
3.2&nbsp;km (7%) were on/off ramps and other roads. On the motorway I set the
cruise control to 95, 115, and 135&nbsp;km/h which in true speed should be
around 90, 110, and 130&nbsp;km/h.</p>

<p>This resulted in the following efficiency values reported by the car, for the
full round trip. From the vehicle efficiency I derive the vehicle consumption
and the resulting range.</p>

<div class="next-table-sidescroll next-table-striped"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Cruise&nbsp;speed</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Vehicle&nbsp;efficiency</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Vehicle&nbsp;consumption</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;">   <strong>Range</strong> </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;">           <strong>90 km/h</strong> </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                  9.1 km/kWh </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">               11.0 kWh/100km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 349&nbsp;km </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;">          <strong>110 km/h</strong> </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                  6.9 km/kWh </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">               14.5 kWh/100km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 264&nbsp;km </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;">          <strong>130 km/h</strong> </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                  5.6 km/kWh </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">               17.9 kWh/100km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 214&nbsp;km </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><br />
If the trip ends at a destination/home charger, driving faster simply means
you&rsquo;ll get there faster, by spending more energy (and therefore money).
However, if the journey is longer and requires charging along the route,
driving faster also means waiting more for charging. Here&rsquo;s the time I spent
driving and charging:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/ioniq_efficiency_5.png" title="Graph shows total driving + charging time only decreases slightly by driving faster" ></p>

<p>This table shows the resulting average speeds, which are lower than the cruise
speeds because of the driving off-motorway, and again lower when including the
time to charge the battery back up:</p>

<div class="next-table-sidescroll next-table-striped"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Cruise&nbsp;speed</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Driving&nbsp;average&nbsp;speed</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Average&nbsp;speed&nbsp;incl.&nbsp;charging</strong> </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;">           <strong>90 km/h</strong> </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             85 km/h </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                         64 km/h </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;">          <strong>110 km/h</strong> </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                            100 km/h </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                         68 km/h </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;">          <strong>130 km/h</strong> </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                            113 km/h </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                         70 km/h </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><br />
The Ioniq Electric 38&nbsp;kWh, because of its limited charging speed, is not
too fast on long journeys. In Youtuber <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@bjornnyland">Bjørn Nyland</a>&rsquo;s
<a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1V6ucyFGKWuSQzvI8lMzvvWJHrBS82echMVJH37kwgjE/edit#gid=15442336">1000 km challenge</a> series, the Ioniq 38 achieved an average speed around
<strong>70&nbsp;km/h</strong> in the winter, similar to veteran EVs Nissan Leaf and Renault
Zoe. If you pay a bit more, there are some EVs with a great trade-off between
price and long-distance speed around the <strong>90&nbsp;km/h</strong> mark: Hyundai Kona,
Kia Niro, VW&nbsp;ID.3, Cupra Born, Tesla Model&nbsp;3&nbsp;SR+. Finally, you
can get around <strong>100&nbsp;km/h</strong> and up with the newer Ioniqs, Kia EV6, and
many models from Tesla and the German automakers.</p>

<p>But as seen in Bjørn&rsquo;s videos, sustaining a high average speed on a long
journey means there&rsquo;s almost no time to eat or take breaks on the trip. And
that&rsquo;s why even a slower-charging, affordable EV such as the Ioniq Electric can
be good enough.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bedre elbilsladning i Aalborg [Danish]]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2022/06/11/bedre-elbilsladning-i-aalborg/"/>
    <updated>2022-06-11T10:13:23+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2022/06/11/bedre-elbilsladning-i-aalborg</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/clever_garvergade.jpg" title="Billedet viser elbiler parkeret ved ladestandere ved Garvergade" ></p>

<p>Det er en ny æra for offentlig opladning af elbiler i Aalborg. Efter en meget
begrænset udvikling i 2021 er der i foråret 2022 åbnet flere nye offentlige
ladepladser i Aalborg og Nørresundby. Nu er det næsten altid muligt at finde en
ledig offentlig lader, når man skal bruge den. Dermed er det blevet meget
nemmere at kombinere elbil med at bo i lejlighed, samt at være
plug-in-bils-gæst i Aalborg.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Mulighederne er blevet bedre både for <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2022/05/01/bedre-hurtigladning-i-aalborg/">hurtigladning</a>
(specielt da Circle Ks ladere nu er åbnet igen) og for offentlig
destinationsladning, hvor bilen holder parkeret i et antal timer imens den
oplades. Aalborg Kommune og Clever har i løbet af foråret åbnet 24
destinationsladere fordelt på fire forskellige kommunale P-pladser:</p>

<ul>
<li>Sømandshjemmet, Aalborg: 6 ladere</li>
<li>Vejgaard Bymidte, Aalborg: 6 ladere</li>
<li>Garvergade, Nørresundby: 6 ladere</li>
<li>Havnegade, Nørresundby: 6 ladere.</li>
</ul>


<p>Sømandshjemmet havde i forvejen to af kommunens 2&nbsp;kW-ladestik, som nu er
erstattet af seks 11/22&nbsp;kW-ladestik fra Clever. Aalborg Kongres &amp; Kultur
Center har også længe haft to af kommunens 2&nbsp;kW-ladestik, og disse er også
planlagt til at blive erstattet af Clevers.</p>

<p>Det er skønt at der nu er plads til opladning af seks biler samtidig, i stedet
for de typiske to ad gangen som de fleste ældre ladesteder har. Men der er
flere fordele. For det første har de nye ladere parkeringsregler der er nemme
at forstå (så nemme som parkeringsregler nu kan blive). Dette er også i
modsætning til andre, ældre ladesteder som ofte er på private områder med
uklare regler. Der ikke rart at parkere med frygt for en dyr parkeringsafgift,
så det er rart at de nye kommunale pladser har klare regler.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/clever_havnegade.jpg" title="Billedet viser parkeringsregler ved ladepladserne på Havnegade: 3 timer 8-19 (8-16)" ></p>

<p>For det andet er det vigtigt at de nye kommunale pladser er gratis at holde på.
Den pris man betaler for strøm fra offentlige ladere er i forvejen 2&ndash;3 gange
dyrere pr. kilowatttime end ved hjemmeladning, så det er dejligt at man ikke
skal betale dyr parkering oveni. Specielt hvis man har en ældre eller billigere
elbil der lader med en lavere effekt, kan dyre parkeringspladser (fx
16&nbsp;kr/time) mere end fordoble den i forvejen halvdyre omkostning for at
lade offentligt.</p>

<p>Ud over nye ladere på kommunale P-pladser er der også kommet andre offentlige
ladere til, fx 4&nbsp;stk. ved Nordelektro på Skibsbyggerivej og 4&nbsp;stk.
ved Centrica på Skelagervej. (Desuden flere i dyre P-huse, samt flere
ikke-offentlige ladere ved boligforeninger, arbejdspladser mv.).</p>

<p>Sammen med de nye lademuligheder er æraen for gratis opladning i Aalborg næsten
slut. Circle&nbsp;K har lukket for gratis ladning og Aalborg Kommunes gratis
ladestik til elbiler er halvvejs med at blive erstattet af Clever-ladestandere.
Gratis ladning har været et privilegie som gjorde det muligt at køre elbil
<a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2021/05/24/3000-km-for-under-100/">ekstremt billigt</a> i Aalborg indtil nu. Nu må det nøjes med &ldquo;bare&rdquo; at
være <a href="https://fdm.dk/nyheder/bilist/2021-02-undersoegelse-afsloerer-denne-biltype-er-billigst-eje">billigere end benzin og diesel</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AAWireless First Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2022/06/04/aawireless-first-impressions/"/>
    <updated>2022-06-04T21:20:37+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2022/06/04/aawireless-first-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/aawireless.jpg" width="375" title="Picture shows a car infotainment screen with Google Maps as well as the small AAWireless device plugged in to the car's USB port" ></p>

<p>My <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2021/05/02/hyundai-ioniq-electric/">car</a> supports Android Auto which lets me connect my smartphone and
use the phone&rsquo;s apps on the car&rsquo;s infotainment system including touchscreen,
speakers and microphone. Examples include Google Maps for navigation and
Spotify for music, as well as Google Assistant voice commands.</p>

<p>It normally requires a wired USB connection between phone and car, but
<a href="https://www.aawireless.io/">AAWireless</a> is a device that acts as a wireless bridge between
phone and car while the device stays plugged in to the car, so your phone can
stay in your pocket or bag. I&rsquo;m happy so say it works well so far.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>With the product being crowdfunded, and just being a consumer electronic
product in general, I was prepared for some problems. To my pleasant surprise,
the product Just Works for me. After the initial Bluetooth pairing, the device
connects quickly when I turn the car on, and the car&rsquo;s touchscreen is
responsive. I did not use the accompanying <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=app.aawireless">app</a> to configure or update
the device, as it was not necessary for me, and because I didn&rsquo;t want the app
to update the device&rsquo;s firmware, as some reviews complained about problems with
a recent version of the firmware.</p>

<p>The AAWireless device uses less than 1&nbsp;W of power from the wired USB
connection which is nice. I don&rsquo;t know how the phone&rsquo;s power consumption is
affected and I have not yet tried longer trips with the AAWireless. But based
on my limited experience with it, I&rsquo;m happy with the purchase.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bedre hurtigladning i Aalborg [Danish]]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2022/05/01/bedre-hurtigladning-i-aalborg/"/>
    <updated>2022-05-01T13:37:59+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2022/05/01/bedre-hurtigladning-i-aalborg</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/Q8-skilt.jpg" title="Stort skilt ved Q8 som viser priserne på benzin, diesel og el" ></p>

<p>Foråret har bragt bedre muligheder for offent&shy;lig opladning af elbiler i
Aalborg, til glæde for både gæster og os der bor i lejlighed eller af andre
årsager ikke har egen ladeboks. Situa&shy;tionen er blevet bedre både når det
gælder hurtig&shy;ladning og destinations&shy;ladning. Dette indlæg handler om
det første.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Hurtigladning er den slags ladning hvor man typisk holder 15&ndash;45 minutter
afhængig af bilen, lade&shy;standerens hastighed, og hvor langt man skal køre.
Ofte kan man tilbringe vente&shy;tiden på tank&shy;station, toilet,
lege&shy;plads, indkøbs&shy;center, fastfood&shy;restaurant eller Netflix.</p>

<a name="Indtil.nu"></a>
<h2>Indtil nu</h2>

<p>Hurtigladning i Aalborg har ikke fungeret så godt frem til nu. I 2020 var der
kun tre hurtig&shy;ladere i Stor&shy;aalborg: En ved Stor&shy;centeret, en ved
føtex Eternitten, og en ved Q8 Scheels&shy;mindevej ved Møllen. Hver af disse
ladere er af den gammel&shy;dags slags med kun ét CCS-stik, dvs. at der typisk
kun er plads til hurtig&shy;ladning af én bil ad gangen.</p>

<p>Efterhånden som antallet af elbiler steg i 2021 blev det sværere at få plads
ved de få ladere der var, specielt ved Storcenteret og Eternitten. Eternittens
ladestander var (og er) tilmed låst inde uden for føtex&#8217; åbnings&shy;tid,
hvilket for&shy;værrer problemet. Scheels&shy;mindevej var nem&shy;mest at få
plads ved, måske fordi det var den dyreste lader til 4,90&nbsp;kr/kWh (drevet
af E.ON), mens de andre kostede 3,50&nbsp;kr/kWh (drevet af Clever). Alle tre
havde (og har) en lade&shy;hastighed på 50&nbsp;kW.</p>

<p>I starten af 2021 fik Circle&nbsp;K Hadsundvej en stander med to 150&nbsp;kW
CCS-stik som tilmed var gratis at benytte som del af en længere&shy;varende
prøve&shy;periode der endte med at vare over et år. Det var på den ene side
skønt at lade gratis når man fik plads, men på den anden side gjorde
popular&shy;iteten at det ofte var svært at få plads uden at holde i kø. Jeg
mødte endda nogle som havde mulighed for at lade hjemme, men som alligevel
kørte forbi Circle&nbsp;K for at få gratis strøm. I&nbsp;starten af 2022 fik
Circle&nbsp;K yder&shy;ligere en stander med to stik på Sønderbro.</p>

<p>Tesla, hvis ladere ikke er offentligt til&shy;gængelige i Danmark, har heller
ikke en såkaldt Super&shy;charger hurtig&shy;ladestation i Aalborg.</p>

<a name="Godt.nyt.hos.Q8"></a>
<h2>Godt nyt hos Q8</h2>

<p>I april 2022 har hurtigladning i Aalborg ændret sig betydeligt, med store
ændringer hos tank&shy;station&shy;erne. Q8 har fået <a href="https://migogaalborg.dk/q8-lynladere/">seks nye stik</a> à
150&nbsp;kW, hvilket i sig selv er fantastisk, men de har også gjort en masse
ting rigtigt som gør el nemmere og mere behageligt at bruge:</p>

<ul>
<li>De viser elprisen på pylonen/standeren man kan se ude fra vejen, på lige fod
med benzin- og dieselpriserne, som vist på billedet øverst på siden. (Prisen
er p.t. 4,95 kr/kWh og hvis du er vant til at tænke i liter frem for
kilowatt&shy;timer, så kan jeg anbefale <a href="https://fdm.dk/alt-om-biler/elbil-hybridbil/opladning/saa-meget-koster-en-liter-stroem-til-en-elbil">denne artikel</a> fra FDM.)</li>
<li>De har placeret en af ladestanderne (to stik) under tag, så man kan stå i
tørvejr lige som dem der tanker fossile brænd&shy;stoffer. De resterende
standere står ikke under tag, men til gengæld er der god plads i bredden på
deres parkerings&shy;pladser.</li>
<li>De tager imod Dankort/&#8203;betalingskort, så man ikke er tvunget til at
bruge (endnu) en mobil&shy;app. Der er dog stadig mulighed for at bruge apps.</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/Q8-plads.jpg" title="En ladestander hos Q8 med to stik og rummelige parkeringspladser" ></p>

<p>Desuden har jeg ikke indtryk af at Q8 over&shy;driver den ladehastighed de
tilbyder. De rekla&shy;merer med 150&nbsp;kW, hvilket virker realist&shy;isk at
de kan levere, selvom jeg ikke selv kan teste det. Dette er i mod&shy;sætning
til Circle&nbsp;K som reklamerer med 300&nbsp;kW, men skriver med småt &ldquo;Denne
lade&shy;stander kan lade én bil med op til 300&nbsp;kW, eller to biler med op
til 150&nbsp;kW hver&rdquo;. Desuden har jeg snakket med andre elbilister ved
Circle&nbsp;K og hørt at laderne ikke nød&shy;vendig&shy;vis leverer den lovede
hastighed til de (dyre) biler der kan tage imod så meget. For&shy;håbentlig er
det et problem Circle&nbsp;K får udbedret.</p>

<a name="D..rligt.nyt.hos.Circle.K"></a>
<h2>Dårligt nyt hos Circle K</h2>

<p>Hos Circle&nbsp;K er der også store ændringer her i april. De har længe snakket
om at sætte betal&shy;ing på deres ladere, og nu har de gjort alvor af det. Man
kan læse at de har opsat
<a href="https://www.inputmag.dk/circle-k-har-sat-pris-paa-lynopladning/">betalings&shy;løsninger på alle kædens lade&shy;standere</a>.
Dette er rimeligt og forventet, og er ikke den dårlige nyhed. Endda er det
positivt at det kommer til at mindske træng&shy;slen ved laderne.</p>

<p>Den dårlige nyhed er at alle fire Circle&nbsp;K-lade&shy;stik i Aalborg siden
omkring midt-april har været ude af drift, og ikke har fået monteret
auto&shy;mat til betal&shy;ings&shy;kort endnu. Jeg formoder de fleste
Circle&nbsp;K-&#8203;ladere i Danmark fungerer med betal&shy;ings&shy;system
som medierne siger (og som jeg personligt har set hos Circle&nbsp;K
Framlev&#8203;/&#8203;Harlev vest for Aarhus). For at gøre det værre i Aalborg
henviser de endda fra den ene defekte/&#8203;deaktiv&shy;erede ladestander til
den anden.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/CircleK-ude-af-drift.jpg" title="Den ene Circle K-ladestander i Aalborg er ude af drift og henviser til den anden som også er ude af drift" ></p>

<p>Når de engang i maj forhåbentlig har fået mon&shy;teret betalings&shy;systemet
og genåbnet laderne bliver det skønt med 13 hurtig&shy;ladestik i
Stor&shy;aalborg fordelt på Q8, Circle&nbsp;K, Clever og E.ON. Men det må siges
PR-mæssigt at være en fan&shy;tastisk dårlig afslutning på en ellers fantastisk
god prøve&shy;periode for Circle&nbsp;K i Aalborg.</p>

<a name="Fremtiden"></a>
<h2>Fremtiden</h2>

<p>Til sommer planlægger Clever at åbne
<a href="https://via.ritzau.dk/pressemeddelelse/clever-etablerer-nordjyllands-storste-lynladestation?publisherId=12636953&amp;releaseId=13641390">Nord&shy;jyllands største lade&shy;station</a> med 16 stk.
300&nbsp;kW-&#8203;ladestik i Nørre&shy;sundby. Det blivere mere end en
fordobling af antallet af hurtig&shy;lade&shy;stik i Stor&shy;aalborg, så det
bliver godt.</p>

<p>De stigende elpriser spørger også. Clever har varslet prisstigninger fra juni,
som vil presse deres lynladere (150+&nbsp;kW) op til være marked&shy;ets
dyreste i løssalg (6,50&nbsp;kr/kWh uden abonnement), endda dyrere end Ionity.
Dog vil deres 50&nbsp;kW-ladere med 4,75&nbsp;kr/kWh fortsat være blandt de
billigste, hvilket er dejligt for os med en &ldquo;gammel&shy;dags&rdquo; elbil der ikke
lader hurtig&shy;ere på en lynlader end på en &ldquo;gammel&shy;dags&rdquo;
50&nbsp;kW-hurtiglader.</p>

<p>Folk i den indtil videre lukkede Tesla-klub kan også glæde sig over at der
skulle komme en <a href="https://www.tesla.com/findus/location/supercharger/aalborgsuperchargerq122">Aalborg Supercharger</a> i tredje kvartal i år.</p>

<p>Ud over hurtigladning er destinations&shy;ladning (mens man holder parkeret i
flere timer) også blevet bedre i Aalborg i april, og står til at blive endnu
bedre snart. Det kommer i mit <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2022/06/11/bedre-elbilsladning-i-aalborg/">næste indlæg</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Visual Studio Sounds]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2021/10/02/visual-studio-sounds/"/>
    <updated>2021-10-02T22:35:14+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2021/10/02/visual-studio-sounds</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/vs_sound1.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="right" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/vs_sound2.png"></p>

<p>I have been working with a slightly heavy C# code base that takes around a
minute to build and start up. This is enough time that I&rsquo;ll switch to another
program each time I start a debug or test run. But it&rsquo;s also short enough time
that if I get side&shy;tracked for five minutes, that&rsquo;s four minutes of Visual
Studio sitting idle.</p>

<p>One day I stumbled upon a setting in Visual Studio named &ldquo;Play a sound when
tests finish running&rdquo;, and from there a button to open the main Windows Sound
settings where a number of events in Visual Studio can be configured to trigger
a sound. This feature is simple but great. Now I can switch context and always
hear when I need to come back and work from a breakpoint or a finished test
run. I can also use different sounds to distinguish positive and negative
outcomes. Using the built-in Windows sounds, I found that these work great:</p>

<div class="next-table-striped"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> <strong>Event</strong>          </th>
<th> <strong>Sound</strong>                  </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Breakpoint Hit     </td>
<td> Windows Pop-up Blocked.wav </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Build Failed       </td>
<td> Windows Hardware Fail.wav  </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Build Succeeded    </td>
<td> Windows Print complete.wav </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Test Run Failed    </td>
<td> Windows Hardware Fail.wav  </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Test Run Succeeded </td>
<td> tada.wav                   </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><br /> Especially the Ta-Daaa! fanfare when the tests pass is a nice way to be
called back to Visual Studio. Happy coding!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Motorvejsladning [Danish]]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2021/06/26/motorvejsladning/"/>
    <updated>2021-06-26T10:25:52+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2021/06/26/motorvejsladning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/plugshare_map.png' width='' height='' alt='Offentlige ladepunkter for elbiler --- de orange punkter er hurtigladere. Skærmbillede fra [PlugShare][plugshare].'><span class='caption-text'>Offentlige ladepunkter for elbiler &mdash; de orange punkter er hurtigladere. Skærmbillede fra <a href="https://www.plugshare.com/">PlugShare</a>.</span></span></p>

<p>En elbil oplades typisk i et roligt tempo mens den er parkeret hjemme, på
arbejde eller ved en offentlig destinations&shy;lader. Men når man skal køre
langt benytter man ladere med høj effekt, så man kan komme hurtigt videre.
Dette indlæg handler om <em>hurtig&shy;ladere</em> i Danmark, med fokus på motorvejen
mellem Aalborg og København. På de 416&nbsp;km mellem de to byer er der 64
CCS-stik langs motor&shy;vejen til hurtig&shy;ladning, og nogle flere i byerne
omkring motor&shy;vejen. Dette er et rigtig godt udgangs&shy;punkt når man
kører turen, men for at optimere rejsens tid eller pris kan man med fordel
benytte nogle ladere frem for andre.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I øvrigt håber jeg at dette indlæg bliver hurtigt forældet, i form af
forbedringer af infra&shy;struk&shy;turen. For nylig kom for eksempel nyheden
at Fyn i 2022 får Danmarks <a href="https://via.ritzau.dk/pressemeddelelse/fyn-far-snart-danmarks-storste-lynladestation-til-elbiler?publisherId=12636953&amp;releaseId=13622978">største lyn&shy;ladestation</a> med plads til 28
elbiler. Det siges også at de kommercielle lade&shy;netværk arbejder på et
fælles betalings&shy;system der skal gøre det nemmere at bruge landets ladere
med færre apps og brikker. Men lad os træde et skridt tilbage og fokusere på
nutiden.</p>

<p>Først er der elbilens <a href="https://da.wikipedia.org/wiki/Videokrigen">&ldquo;VHS/Betamax-konflikt&rdquo;</a> omkring hvilket stik og
hvilken teknik man bruger når man hurtig&shy;lader elbiler. Elbilernes Betamax
hedder <em>CHAdeMO</em> og VHS (vinderen) hedder <em>CCS</em> som står for Combined Charging
System. Der findes stadig mange CHAdeMO-stik rundt om i landet, men nye elbiler
i EU sælges nu stort set kun med CCS. Der er også Tesla som har deres eget
system, samtidig med at de afhængig af model og adapter også kan benytte
offentlige ladere af både CHAdeMO- og CCS-typerne. Jeg vil dog kun fokusere på
CCS i det følgende.</p>

<p>En <em>hurtig&shy;lader</em> er en lade&shy;stander som tilbyder bilen mindst
50&nbsp;kW (kilowatt). Det er forskelligt pr. elbil hvor meget af den
tilgængelige effekt som den kan tage imod. Nogle elbiler kan ikke udnytte
50&nbsp;kW fuldt ud, mens andre (dyrere) elbiler kan sluge 250&nbsp;kW eller
mere når det er tilgængeligt. Begrebet <em>lynladning</em> bruges når ladestanderen
tilbyder mindst 100&nbsp;kW, typisk 150&ndash;350&nbsp;kW.</p>

<a name="Fra.Aalborg.til.K..benhavn"></a>
<h2>Fra Aalborg til København</h2>

<p>Der er 64 CCS-stik mellem Aalborg og København inden for 1&nbsp;km fra E45 og
E20. Hvis man kigger op til 5&nbsp;km fra motorvejen er der 13&nbsp;stik mere,
og op til 10&nbsp;km yderligere 10&nbsp;stik. Og hvis man inkluderer
rastepladser på &ldquo;den modsatte side&rdquo; kommer der 10 mere, men dem vil jeg ikke
tælle med da det at anvende sådan en kan medføre en omvej på 10&ndash;30&nbsp;km, da
man ikke bare lige kan krydse over motorvejen. Jeg tæller heller ikke selve
Aalborg og København med i de 64 da det er mere normalt at bruge AC-ladning
(typisk 11&nbsp;kW) når man parkerer nær sin destination. Alt i alt er der en
rimelig mængde hurtig&shy;ladere langs motorvejen, og nogle ekstra der kan
bruges som backup hvis der skulle være trængsel ved en af de primære.</p>

<p>De 64 stik er ikke jævnt fordelt. Nogle findes på en enlig stander der også
ofte inkluderer en til to andre stiktyper, men altså kun ét CCS-stik. Nogle
steder står to, fire eller flere standere sammen. Og nogle steder er flere
forskellige netværk/firmaer repræsenteret på samme lokation inden for nogle
hundrede meter af hinanden. I alt er der 22 lokationer med 1&ndash;10 stik hver, 3 i
gennem&shy;snit. Over de 416&nbsp;km fra Limfjordsbroen i Aalborg til Langebro
i København er der i gennemsnit en lokation hver 19&nbsp;km. Lokationerne er
dog heller ikke jævnt fordelt og spænder fra 2&nbsp;km mellem Nyborg og
Knudshoved til 46&nbsp;km mellem Haverslev og Randers. I den følgende tabel
inkluderer jeg også Horsens og Odense der har hurtig&shy;ladere, selvom de ikke
ligger ud til motorvejen. Tabellen viser <strong>antallet af CCS-stik</strong> fordelt på
netværk og ladehastighed:</p>

<div class="next-table-sidescroll next-table-striped"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> <strong>Sted</strong>              </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Afstand til næste</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Clever 50&nbsp;kW</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>E.ON 50&nbsp;kW</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Clever/E.ON 175&nbsp;kW</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Ionity 350&nbsp;kW</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Hurtige byladere</strong> </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Aalborg               </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 28 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                    5 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Himmerland            </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                  8 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                   1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Haverslev             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 46 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                           2 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      4 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Randers/Gudenåen      </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                  6 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                    1 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Randers/Sdr. Borup    </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 29 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                   1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Aarhus/Tilst          </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 14 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                   1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                    7 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Skanderborg           </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 13 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      4 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                    1 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Ejer Bavnehøj         </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 12 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                   1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Horsens               </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 24 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                    3 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Vejle N               </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                  5 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Vejle C               </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                  5 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                    1 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Vejle S/Skærup        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 17 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                   1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Fredericia            </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                  4 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                           4 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      4 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                    1 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Middelfart            </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 30 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                    1 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kildebjerg            </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 11 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                   1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Odense                </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 33 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                    4 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Nyborg                </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                  2 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                   1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      4 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Knudshoved            </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 19 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                           4 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Korsør/Halsskov       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 16 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                           4 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Slagelse/Antvorskov   </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 18 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                   1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                    3 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sorø/Tuelsø           </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 12 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                   1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Ringsted              </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 24 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                   1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Køge                  </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 10 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                   1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Karlslunde            </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                  3 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                   1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                           2 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Greve                 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 28 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     10 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                    1 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> København             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                  30+ </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><br /> Afstanden mellem ladestederne måler jeg mellem de relevante
motorvejs&shy;afkørsler. Laderne står 0&ndash;1&nbsp;km fra motorvejen, bortset fra
kategorien &ldquo;Hurtige byladere&rdquo; som jeg bruger om hurtig&shy;ladere der står
2&ndash;10&nbsp;km fra motorvejen. Byladerne står primært ved indkøbscentre, hvilket
gør at de oftere end motorvejs&shy;ladere er i brug af folk der bor i
lokal&shy;området. Desuden kan den P-<wbr>plads de står på være aflåst uden for
indkøbs&shy;centerets åbningstid. Alle disse ting gør at jeg kun betragter dem
som en reserveløsning ved motorvejs&shy;rejser. Jeg har ikke optalt
hurtig&shy;laderne i Stor&shy;københavn præcist, men der er mange. Ud over
Clever og E.ON findes der bl.a. også hurtige byladere fra fx Spirii, Sperto,
Circle&nbsp;K og Lidl.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/motorvejsladere.png' width='' height='' alt='Kort over hurtigladere i Aalborg og København, samt langs motorvejen imellem.'><span class='caption-text'>Kort over hurtigladere i Aalborg og København, samt langs motorvejen imellem.</span></span></p>

<a name="Hvilke.ladere.skal.man.v..lge."></a>
<h2>Hvilke ladere skal man vælge?</h2>

<p>Faktisk behøver man slet ikke at vælge da man kan bruge alle ladere vha. apps
som kan opsættes på få minutter. Men laderene koster ikke det samme at bruge.
Et abonnement hos Clever giver adgang til Clevers hurtig&shy;ladere
(50&nbsp;kW) og Clever og E.ONs <a href="https://poweredby.dk/">fælles</a> lynladere (175&nbsp;kW), i
tillæg til mange af 50&nbsp;kW-byladerne som også drives af Clever. Hvis man
betaler efter forbrug, i mod&shy;sætning til fastpris&shy;abonnement, koster
hurtig&shy;laderne 3,50&nbsp;kr/kWh og lynladerne 5,00&nbsp;kr/kWh. (Ud over
apps kan man også bestille en ladebrik/RFID-tag som gør det lidt hurtigere at
starte ladningen på et givet netværk uden at skulle fedte med sin telefon og
afhænge af internet&shy;forbindelse.)</p>

<p>Et abonnement hos E.ON giver adgang til E.ONs hurtig&shy;ladere og
Clever/E.ON-lynladerne, samt nogle hurtig&shy;ladere i København. Til forskel
fra Clever tager E.ON samme pris for hurtig&shy;ladning og lynladning:
4,90&nbsp;kr/kWh. Hvis man har en elbil som ikke kan udnytte lynladernes høj
hastighed, er det en ulempe at man ikke kan spare penge ved at holde sig til de
langsommere hurtig&shy;ladere når man betaler efter forbrug, som hos Clever.
(Prisen man betaler afhænger kun af den effekt laderen tilbyder, og ikke af den
effekt bilen aftager.) Omvendt tager E.ON en marginalt lavere kWh-pris end
Clever for præcis de samme lynladere, igen hvis man ikke har
fastpris&shy;abonnement. (Jeg har ikke inkluderet priser på
fastpris&shy;abonnementerne, da de afhænger af flere ting, men de kan ses hos
<a href="https://clever.dk/produkter/abonnementer/">Clever</a> og <a href="https://www.eon.dk/privat/strom-til-din-elbil.html">E.ON</a>.)</p>

<p>Til sidst er der Ionity som har de hurtigste ladere, men også tager den høje
pris af 6,20&nbsp;kr/kWh. Prisen kan dog reduceres hvis man har et abonnement
via en af de bil&shy;producenter der ejer <a href="https://ionity.eu/en/about.html">Ionity</a>: BMW, Ford, Hyundai,
Mercedes, Volkswagen, Audi og Porsche. Herunder opstiller jeg nogle eksempler
på hvordan man kan udvælge sine favorit&shy;ladere &mdash; og så have alle de andre
i reserve:</p>

<div class="next-table-sidescroll next-table-striped"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> <strong>Foretrukne ladere</strong>      </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Steder</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Stik</strong> </th>
<th> <strong>Hvis man&hellip;</strong>                                       </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Ionity                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">          5 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">       26 </td>
<td> kan udnytte og vil betale for den højeste hastighed   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Clever/E.ON lynladere      </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">          5 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">       16 </td>
<td> synes 50 kW er for langsomt men 350 kW er for dyrt    </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> E.ON inkl. lynladere       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">         16 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">       28 </td>
<td> har fastprisabonnement hos E.ON                       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Clever inkl. lynladere     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">         12 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">       26 </td>
<td> har fastprisabonnement hos Clever                     </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Clever ekskl. lynladere    </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">         10 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">       10 </td>
<td> betaler efter forbrug og ikke kan udnytte lynladning  </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><br /> Jeg har lavet et diagram over om hvornår fastpris&shy;abonnement giver
mening i <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2021/05/24/3000-km-for-under-100/">dette</a> indlæg. Selv benytter jeg primært Clever ekskl.
lynladere, da jeg betaler efter forbrug og Hyundai <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2021/05/02/hyundai-ioniq-electric/">IONIQ 2020</a> kun
har minimal fordel af lynladere. Men hvis jeg havde en bil der kunne udnytte
dem ville jeg benytte lyn&shy;laderne. Antallene af steder og stik i tabellen
medtæller kun motorvejs&shy;laderne, men ikke hurtig&shy;laderne i byerne,
selvom man også får adgang til de fleste af dem med et Clever-abonnement, samt
nogle i København med et E.ON-abonnement. Desuden giver både E.ON og Clever
(men ikke Ionity) adgang til en lang række destinations&shy;ladere/AC-ladere
over hele landet.</p>

<a name="Hvor.mange.opladninger.har.man.behov.for."></a>
<h2>Hvor mange opladninger har man behov for?</h2>

<p>Et oplagt spørgsmål er hvor mange ladere der er behov for og hvor tæt de skal
stå. Derfor vil jeg se på hvor mange <em>opladninger</em> man har behov for. Svaret
afhænger af bilens rækkevidde, som igen afhænger af køre&shy;hastigheden og
vejret. Med Hyundai IONIQ 2020 som eksempel på en elbil med mellemlav
række&shy;vidde (typisk <a href="https://ev-database.org/car/1165/Hyundai-IONIQ-Electric">200&ndash;300&nbsp;km</a>) kan
Aalborg&ndash;København køres på 1&ndash;3 oplad&shy;ninger. Hvis vejret er godt
(15&ndash;25°C) burde man kunne klare turen med én opladning ved at køre med
100&ndash;110&nbsp;km/t. Jeg forudsætter man starter med fuldt batteri og slutter på
10% som en sikkerheds&shy;margin mod uforud&shy;sige&shy;ligheder. Opladningen
efter ankomst kan som regel foretages mens bilen er parkeret ved en
destinations&shy;lader, uden at man behøver at vente i bilen, men en hurtig
bylader kan også bruges hvis man vil flytte bilen igen en halv times tid
senere.</p>

<p>Hvis man synes det er kedeligt at køre under hastigheds&shy;grænsen, kan man
bare køre turen med 130&nbsp;km/t med to opladninger om sommeren eller tre om
vinteren. IONIQ 2020 kommer dog ikke så meget hurtigere frem med 130&nbsp;km/t,
da de ekstra ladestop spiser meget af den vundne tid. Til gengæld får man
ekstra pauser til at strække ben, gå på toilettet, arbejde, spise, hygge, eller
hvad man nu har lyst til. Hvis man synes ovenstående lyder undervældende, så
kan elbiler med større række&shy;vidde og hurtigere ladning heldigvis klare sig
med færre og kortere ladepauser:</p>

<div class="next-table-sidescroll next-table-striped"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> <strong>Bilmodel</strong>                         </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Batteri</strong>      </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Ladestop</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Ladetid</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Køretid</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Samlet</strong> </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Mazda&nbsp;MX-30                     </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">      30&nbsp;kWh </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">            4 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">        2:22 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">        4:12 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">       6:35 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hyundai&nbsp;IONIQ                   </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">      38&nbsp;kWh </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">            2 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">        1:08 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">        3:52 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">       5:00 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Volkswagen&nbsp;ID.3&nbsp;Pro        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">      58&nbsp;kWh </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">            2 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">        0:24 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">        3:54 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">       4:18 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Volkswagen&nbsp;ID.3&nbsp;Pro&nbsp;S </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">      77&nbsp;kWh </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">            1 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">        0:08 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">        3:45 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">       3:54 </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><br /> Jeg brugte <a href="https://abetterrouteplanner.com/">A Better Routeplanner</a> til at sammenligne turen for
nogle forskellige bilmodeller, med resultaterne i tabellen herover. De bedste
elbiler på markedet i dag er allerede der hvor mange mennesker har behov for
flere pauser end bilen har. Og i øvrigt kan de dyrere elbiler ofte også selv
medregne den nødvendige opladning i deres navigations&shy;system, så man ikke
selv behøver planlægge opladningen på turen. Men hvis vi vender tilbage til de
billigere elbiler der skal lade oftere, så er det specielt vigtigt at der er
nok ladere med jævne mellemrum.</p>

<a name="Hvor.mange.ladere.er.der.behov.for."></a>
<h2>Hvor mange ladere er der behov for?</h2>

<p>Jo nemmere det er at lade, jo mere attraktivt er det at køre elbil. For at det
skal være rigtig nemt skal der bl.a. være nok ladere til at der altid er én
ledig når man skal bruge den, der hvor man skal bruge den, således at man ikke
behøver at planlægge turen på forhånd.</p>

<p>Allerede nu er der en god mængde ladestandere i forhold til antallet af elbiler
på vejene. Men efter&shy;hånden som antallet af ladere og elbiler stiger
forventer jeg at det bliver lidt mere forud&shy;sige&shy;ligt at
hurtig&shy;lade. Lige nu er situationen nemlig at mange af ladestanderne er
enkelt&shy;stående. I min begrænsede erfaring er de enkelt&shy;stående
ladestanderne på raste&shy;pladserne som regel ledige når jeg ankommer, men
<em>når</em> en lader er optaget, ved man ikke om det tager 3 eller 30 minutter før
den bliver ledig. Med mindre man er heldig at kunne snakke med den ladende
elbilist, og det viser sig at denne næsten er færdig med at lade, så kan det
være spild af tid at holde og vente. Derfor er det usmart at ankomme til en
enkelt&shy;stående lader med meget lavt batteri, og derfor er det stadig en
fordel at planlægge sin tur på forhånd, i hvert fald hvis man har noget man
skal nå i den anden ende. Nogle synes det er sjovt at nørde med
planlæg&shy;ningen, men flertallet vil nok foretrække ikke at være afhængige af
at skulle gøre det.</p>

<p>I øvrigt kan det være en streg i regningen hvis en enkelt&shy;stående lader er
i stykker &mdash; det kan desværre ske. Clever og E.ON tilbyder
<a href="https://clever.dk/produkter/abonnementer/clever-unlimited-network/">mobilitets&shy;garanti</a>/<wbr><a href="https://www.eon.dk/privat/strom-til-din-elbil/oplad-i-netvaerk/bestil-drive-free.html#Vej">vejhjælp</a> i
tilfælde af en defekt lader, men den kræver at man både er abonnent og har
tjekket inden ankomst at laderen ikke allerede er fejl&shy;meldt (mere
plan&shy;lægning). Og garanti eller ej, så tilføjer vejhjælp en større
forsinkelse. Som alter&shy;nativ til de enkelt&shy;stående standere kan man gå
efter ladesteder med mange stik på samme sted:</p>

<div class="next-table-sidescroll next-table-striped"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> <strong>Sted</strong>           </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Afstand til næste</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Antal stik ved motorvej</strong> </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Aalborg            </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 36 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Haverslev          </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 95 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                           7 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Skanderborg        </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 76 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                           4 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Fredericia         </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 79 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                           8 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Nyborg+Knudshoved  </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 20 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                          10 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Halsskov           </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 82 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                           5 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Greve+Karlslunde   </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                 30 km </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                          13 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> København          </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                       </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                             </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><br /> Fordelen er at en optaget eller evt. defekt lader er et meget mindre
problem, og at der nok snart bliver en ledig plads, hvis der ikke allerede er
det når man ankommer. De fleste af disse mange ladere er også de hurtigste (og
dyreste), hvilket kan være et plus eller et minus afhængig af ens bil og
abonnement. Da der er længere imellem stederne med mange stik er det også godt
at være bevidst om hvor man skal huske at lade (hvis bilen ikke selv guider dig
via navigations&shy;systemet).</p>

<a name="Fremtiden"></a>
<h2>Fremtiden</h2>

<p>Efterhånden som der kommer flere elbiler er der også behov for flere ladere, og
omvendt. Det er en hønen og ægget-situation, men heldigvis står det ikke
stille. Clever udmeldte i oktober 2020 at de vil etablere
<a href="https://via.ritzau.dk/pressemeddelelse/clever-vil-etablere-flere-end-10000-offentlige-ladepunkter-til-elbiler-inden-udgangen-af-2025?publisherId=12636953&amp;releaseId=13602758">10.000</a> nye ladepunkter inden udgangen af 2025, hvoraf 500 skal
være lyn&shy;ladere og 100 skal være normale hurtig&shy;ladere. På kortere sigt
opsætter Circle&nbsp;K og OK hurtig&shy;ladere ved deres tankstationer.
Circle&nbsp;K har allerede bygget fire lynlade&shy;stationer (med mindst to
CCS-stik hver) og har yderligere 14 stationer <a href="https://www.circlek.dk/el">planlagt i år</a>. Man kan
se nogle af disse, samt nogle fra OK og Lidl, under &ldquo;coming soon&rdquo; på
<a href="https://www.plugshare.com/">PlugShare</a>. Det var først for nylig at jeg på denne måde opdagede
Circle&nbsp;K-<wbr>lynladeren i Aalborg. Det viser sig endda at den er gratis
at benytte i en prøveperiode der ind til videre har varet et halvt år!</p>

<p>Langs motorvejen håber jeg at nogle af de eksisterende enkelt&shy;stående
ladere får en makker, så der kommer et ekstra CCS-stik på stedet. Der kunne
også godt bruges enkelte nye lokationer mellem Aalborg og København. De
46&nbsp;km mellem Haverslev i Nordjylland og Gudenåen-raste&shy;pladserne ved
Randers kunne halveres ved at placere en ladestation ved motorvejen nær Hobro.
De 74&nbsp;km over Fyn mellem Middelfart og Nyborg kunne også bruge mere end
den ene nuværende opladnings&shy;mulighed på Kildebjerg-rastepladserne, men
heldigvis skulle der jo være <a href="https://via.ritzau.dk/pressemeddelelse/fyn-far-snart-danmarks-storste-lynladestation-til-elbiler?publisherId=12636953&amp;releaseId=13622978">28 nye lynladere</a> på vej ved motorvejen nær
Odense.</p>

<p>Det er ikke kun gennemrejsende der får glæde af de nye lynladere ved Odense.
Lokale beboere, ikke mindst dem der ikke kan få egen hjemmelader, kan benytte
hurtig&shy;ladere i nærheden som alternativ eller supplement til
destinations&shy;laderne, specielt ind til mængden af destinations&shy;ladere
<a href="https://www.tv2lorry.dk/koebenhavn/markant-flere-ladestandere-til-elbiler-kan-vaere-paa-vej-til-hovedstaden">forhåbentlig</a> kommer til at stige i fremtiden.</p>

<p>Selvom der er plads til mange forbedringer er det allerede nu forholdsvis nemt
at køre elbil for mange danskere, specielt de mange der bor i hus. Selv bor vi
i lejlighed og klarer det også fint. Der er selvfølgelig nogle for hvem det
stadig vil være upraktisk, men for de mange med et normalt kørselsbehov vil jeg
foreslå at springe plugin-hybriden over og gå direkte til ren el. For miljøets
skyld, og for <a href="https://fdm.dk/alt-om-biler/bilen-hverdagen/braendstof-oekonomi/undersoegelse-afsloerer-denne-biltype-er-billigst">pengenes skyld</a>.</p>

<p>Fordi det hele virkede nyt og ukendt valgte vi Hyundai
<a href="https://www.hyundai.dk/privatleasing">privatleasing</a> hvor man kun er bundet i ét år, i
modsætning til de fleste firmaer jeg har fundet som binder én i tre år.
Volkswagen har også et koncept hvor man kan lease en ID.3 i
<a href="https://app.volkswagen.dk/app/web/privat/go/konfigurer/?id=2075">seks måneder</a>. Men nu hvor jeg er blevet vant til elbil tænker
jeg ikke på at slippe af med den igen &mdash; jeg glæder mig bare til næste gang
jeg skal ud at køre.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[3000 km for under €100]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2021/05/24/3000-km-for-under-100/"/>
    <updated>2021-05-24T15:40:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2021/05/24/3000-km-for-under-100</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/hyundai_ioniq_electric_2020_charging.jpg"></p>

<p>Getting an electric vehicle while living in an apartment was a bit of an
experiment. Public charging is still a bit rough around the edges, but it
turned out manageable, and in fact quite cheap, with the help from some free
charging. Here&rsquo;s my experience with EV charging in the past six months.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>From November to April I drove our <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2021/05/02/hyundai-ioniq-electric/">Hyundai IONIQ Electric</a>
<strong>3034 km (1885 mi)</strong> while keeping a charging log. I charged 37 times in
total, on average from 56% to 92% state of charge. This covered various
situations such as a small top-up to 100% before a long trip, a motorway
fast-charge up to at most 80%, a full recharge after a long trip (the biggest
being 11%->100%), and various city charging in between. Some of the charging
sessions were tests to try out the various charger types and charging networks
to get comfortable with the process.</p>

<p>Disregarding the tests, I charged on average every <strong>100 km (62 mi)</strong>. On long
trips I gradually became more comfortable with going farther between charges,
with the longest stretch being <strong>263 km (163 mi)</strong> in the spring. But for city
charging with a limited number of public chargers, it remains practical to
charge when the opportunity arises, without running down to a low state of
charge each time.</p>

<a name="Charging.in.the.City"></a>
<h2>Charging in the City</h2>

<p>Most charging sessions were on slow destination chargers, and most were in
Aalborg where we live. We rely on public chargers as we live in an apartment
and don&rsquo;t have our own home charger. It works like this: Drive to a charger,
find a free socket, plug in, and walk 10&ndash;20 minutes home or to work. Later, I
walk back to pick up the car when I need it again, or when it&rsquo;s done charging.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/hyundai_ioniq_electric_2020_charging_dash.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Remaining charging time at a slow charger.'><span class='caption-text'>Remaining charging time at a slow charger.</span></span></p>

<p>A home charger would be much easier to use, but for city dwellers with EVs,
this is how it works at the moment (unless you drive to work and that workplace
has chargers available). Each city and town will be different in the density,
availability, and reliability of public chargers, and improving this
infrastructure will be an undertaking for the next many years.</p>

<p>Going back and forth to the charger takes a bit of time, but the walk is
healthy. However, driving in vain to find all charger sockets in use is
annoying. For commercial chargers, you can usually look up their availability
status online before going, but not all chargers are commercial, as we&rsquo;ll get
to later. In practice, sharing a limited number of public chargers takes a bit
of foresight. If I know I&rsquo;m going on a long trip, I start trying to charge up
to 100% a few days in advance, so there&rsquo;s time to come back later if the
chargers are all in use the first time around. Another option would be to use
fast-chargers (more) on the trip, but the IONIQ&rsquo;s fast-charging speed is not as
good as many other EVs in that regard.</p>

<a name="Parking.Problems"></a>
<h2>Parking Problems</h2>

<p>You shouldn&rsquo;t block a public charger if you&rsquo;re not using it &mdash; that is
etiquette and usually also part of parking regulations. But it can also make
using public destination chargers a hassle. If you plug in to charge late in
the evening, it might be that the charging will finish in the middle of the
night. Do you get up to move the car in the middle of the night? Do you skip
charging altogether? (Probably not.) Do you pick up your car some time the next
morning, hoping to get there before the parking attendant and other EV drivers
in need of some juice? (Perhaps.) I try to plan my charging so I don&rsquo;t block
the charger unnecessarily, but it&rsquo;s not always practical to do so, neither for
me nor other EV drivers.</p>

<p>For EVs to become mainstream, I think the charging situation needs to become
easier and require much less planning. As a start, the parking rules could be
relaxed so the parking-only-while-charging requirement doesn&rsquo;t apply at night.
Ideally there should be enough parking spaces that you could leave your car
some extra time after charging finishes while someone else could take over the
socket you used. Such a grace period would also be helpful when you want to
charge to 100%, because the car&rsquo;s estimation of when the charging will finish
can be a bit off.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/ev_parking_signs.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Some EV parking signs in Danish. (Elbil is the Scandinavian word for **el**ectric automo**bil**e.)'><span class='caption-text'>Some EV parking signs in Danish. (Elbil is the Scandinavian word for <strong>el</strong>ectric automo<strong>bil</strong>e.)</span></span></p>

<p>In other situations, the parking time is limited. There is a parking lot in
Aalborg where the two EV spots have a two hour limit but their charging sockets
supply at most 11&ndash;12 amps. It&rsquo;s nice to have a few parking spaces that are
reserved for EVs, but with those sockets the charging itself is almost
inconsequential since you add at most 15 km (9 mi) of range per hour. That&rsquo;s
like going to the gas station for only 1 liter of gas!</p>

<p>In another place they had 11 kW outlets and a three hour parking limit. That
will get you far if your EV has a matching 11 kW on-board charger (OBC) which
adds range at up to 60 km/h (37 mph). A plug-in hybrid/PHEV can also typically
fill up its smaller battery completely in three hours. But for cheaper EVs with
slow OBCs like the IONIQ, you&rsquo;ll get at most 20 km/h (12 mph). I think
something needs to be done here to improve the situation for social equality in
EV adoption. The solution at Aalborg Zoo is nice: &ldquo;No time limit while
charging&rdquo;. That way, all EVs get the opportunity to add meaningful range, while
still not allowing blocking the parking spot unnecessarily. The last part just
requires parking attendants to check the charging status and not just the
parking disc. I&rsquo;m not sure, but I have the impression that many parking
attendants don&rsquo;t yet understand or care about EV charging.</p>

<p>Another problem is when many of the public chargers are placed in expensive
parking garages. It might be okay to use them once in a while when out of town,
but when you live in an apartment and rely on local destination chargers in
your daily life, you definitely don&rsquo;t want to pay €15 for an eight-hour
charging session &mdash; on top of the charging cost. Despite these problems, using
an EV in Aalborg and Denmark works fine, and the charging has in fact been very
cheap as we&rsquo;ll get to soon.</p>

<a name="Energy.and.Efficiency"></a>
<h2>Energy and Efficiency</h2>

<p>In total I drove 3034 km (1885 mi) using an estimated 524 kWh of energy, or a
bit less than 14 full charges of the <a href="https://ev-database.org/car/1165/Hyundai-IONIQ-Electric">38.3 kWh</a> battery pack.
That comes out to <strong>5.79 km/kWh (3.60 mi/kWh)</strong>, or 17.3 kWh/100km (27.8
kWh/100mi). This was for the Danish winter half-year, using Continental
AllSeasonContact tires, and my driving comprising 40% city, 20% open road, and
40% motorway. It also gives the average range of 222 km (138 mi) from a full
charge for these conditions.
As described in my <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2021/05/02/hyundai-ioniq-electric/">previous post</a>, efficiency and range
depend heavily on speed and weather. Also, some of the driving was economical
but I also did a lot of unnecessary (but fun!) acceleration.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/hyundai_ioniq_electric_2020_info_dash.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Economical driving from Odense to Aalborg, Denmark.'><span class='caption-text'>Economical driving from Odense to Aalborg, Denmark.</span></span></p>

<p>There are two things to add. First, the total energy is not only used while
driving. The IONIQ, like regular cars, has a 12 V battery that discharges over
time. The IONIQ, unlike regular cars, can keep the 12 V battery in shape
automatically, using a bit of juice from the main driving battery. This will
take around one percentage point of charge from the main battery per week, at
least when it&rsquo;s freezing. My calculated average efficiency and range includes
half a year of parking, so during driving alone, the efficiency and range is a
tiny bit better than the numbers above indicate.</p>

<p>Second, it&rsquo;s not all the energy that comes through the charging cable that
makes it to the battery. During charging, some electricity is lost as heat,
plus the car needs some electronics running, and it might even spend energy on
battery cooling or heating to optimize the charging speed, depending on the car
model. The loss is around 10&ndash;15%. So getting 524 kWh into the IONIQ will
actually have required around <strong>600 kWh</strong> in total. Let&rsquo;s see what this means
for the cost.</p>

<a name="Cost.Complexity"></a>
<h2>Cost Complexity</h2>

<p>EV charging prices vary a lot, at least in Denmark where legislation is
complicated. Most EV price calculations I&rsquo;ve read assume you will install a
home charger, but for many city dwellers that is not an option, so I will
instead exclude home charging. That removes some of the complexity of EV
charging prices, including home charger installation, home charger purchase vs.
rental, combined home and public charger subscription, time dependent
electricity tariffs, electricity tax refunds, and interaction between tax
refunds and the use of solar panels and geothermal heat pumps.</p>

<p>Public charging is still complicated, though: Pay per kWh or a fixed price per
month, or somewhere in between. Use one provider, or multiple, or a meta
provider, or somewhere in between. For fast-charging, the price can depend on
the charging speed, or potential partnerships between EV manufacturers and
charging providers. In some countries you also pay per minute.</p>

<p>You can also be lucky and have access to free charging. Our municipality has a
few sockets in Aalborg for free EV charging, which is a nice &ldquo;carrot&rdquo; for EV
adoption. Some hotels and supermarkets have free charging. For example, Lidl
supermarkets have free chargers in some countries and are getting it in
Denmark. Car manufacturers also sometimes offer some free charging. Hyundai
started giving away six months of free charging with new leases, less than a
week after we got our IONIQ. Tesla also sometimes gives away free charging.</p>

<a name="Charging.Cost.in.Denmark"></a>
<h2>Charging Cost in Denmark</h2>

<p>As mentioned in the previous section, there are many possibilities. Here I will
compare what I do with a few simple alternatives. Blessed with tax-paid
electricity in Aalborg, I mainly use those free sockets when at &ldquo;home&rdquo; &mdash; a
15-minute walk from our apartment. When all the free spots are taken, or when
out of town, I use the <em>Clever</em> charging network, with other networks such as
<em>E.ON</em>, <em>Spirii</em> and <em>Ionity</em> as possible backups. Because I don&rsquo;t use the
commercial operators so much, it&rsquo;s cheaper to pay by the kWh instead of using a
flat rate subscription.</p>

<p>In the last six months I paid only 676 DKK (€91 or $111) for 191 kWh, while
getting the remaining ~409 kWh for free. However, not everyone has the
privilege (or patience) to use free charging, so I&rsquo;m going to show some
alternatives. Electricity prices and taxes vary by country, so I&rsquo;m not going to
convert the following prices as they are not directly comparable to other
countries anyway. But here are the current prices in <strong>DKK/kWh</strong> for some
charging network products and charger speeds (with Aalborg Municipality thrown
in so you can see that my free charging is also slow charging):</p>

<div class="next-table-sidescroll"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Charger&nbsp;power</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Aalborg</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Clever&nbsp;Go</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>E.ON&nbsp;Drive&nbsp;Lite</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Spirii&nbsp;Go</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Ionity&nbsp;(guest)</strong> </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;">            <strong>2&ndash;3 kW</strong> </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                0.00 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                          - </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                                     - </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                                      - </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                               - </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;">          <strong>11&ndash;43 kW</strong> </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                   - </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                       3.50 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                                  3.50 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                             2.25&ndash;3.75 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                               - </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;">          <strong>50&ndash;75 kW</strong> </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                   - </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                       3.50 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                                  4.90 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                                      - </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                               - </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;">        <strong>100&ndash;350 kW</strong> </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                   - </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                       5.00 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                                  4.90 </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                                      - </td>
<td style="text-align:right;">                                            6.20 </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><br />
By mixing some of the above speeds and networks, you&rsquo;ll end up with an average
price per kWh. If you only use public chargers, you might end up at 3&ndash;5
DKK/kWh and if you can mix in free charging, you can get under 3 DKK/kWh. My
average was just over 1 DKK/kWh for the past six months. I&rsquo;m using these rates
in the following graph, which also includes a typical 650 DKK/month flat rate
subscription without a home charger included.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/ev_charging_cost_dk.png"></p>

<p>I made the chart based on a consumption of 5 km/kWh including charging loss,
corresponding to the 5.8 km/kWh vehicle consumption that I got for the Danish
winter half-year. In comparison, every time the <a href="https://ev-database.org/car/1165/Hyundai-IONIQ-Electric">Hyundai IONIQ</a>
drives 5 km, the <a href="https://ev-database.org/car/1337/Mercedes-EQC-400-4MATIC">Mercedes EQC</a> will drive 4 km, and the
<a href="https://ev-database.org/car/1272/Audi-e-tron-S-Sportback-55-quattro">Audi e-tron S Sportback</a> will drive 3 km using the same energy.
However, the majority of <a href="https://ev-database.org/compare/efficiency-electric-vehicle-most-efficient">EVs</a> fall somewhere between the EQC
and the IONIQ &mdash; including Audi&rsquo;s upcoming Q4 models, and the very-long-range
Mercedes EQS.</p>

<p>The chart shows that what is cheapest depends heavily on your driving.
Long-distance drivers will profit greatly from a flat rate subscription, while
I would pay 5&ndash;6 times as much as I currently do. Before getting the IONIQ, I
didn&rsquo;t know it would end up like this &mdash; I just knew I wanted to support the
push toward a greener future (and try out some cool tech while at it). And
while charging turned out way cheaper than gasoline, the total cost still could
have been lower by choosing a conventional car with a weaker internal
combustion engine and a manual transmission. But for comparable cars driving an
average 20,000 km/year or 16,000 mi/year, EVs already have ample opportunity to
have a lower total cost of ownership in <a href="https://fdm.dk/alt-om-biler/bilen-hverdagen/braendstof-oekonomi/undersoegelse-afsloerer-denne-biltype-er-billigst">Denmark</a> as well as
the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2021/01/15/climate/electric-car-cost.html">USA</a>.</p>

<p><em>Update 2021-06-26: Minor fixes.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hyundai IONIQ Electric]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2021/05/02/hyundai-ioniq-electric/"/>
    <updated>2021-05-02T09:31:37+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2021/05/02/hyundai-ioniq-electric</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/hyundai_ioniq_electric_2020.jpg"></p>

<p>In late 2020 we decided to get a car. After relying on the extensive Danish
public transport system for many years, it was time for a &ldquo;socially distanced&rdquo;
means of transportation. My friend Jon had just got a Hyundai Kona Electric &mdash;
a mini-crossover with good range. This sparked my interest in electric cars,
and after a month of research and testing, we ordered its sibling, the 2020
IONIQ Electric. It&rsquo;s a frugal yet fun car with good value but some drawbacks.</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Range.and.Efficiency"></a>
<h2>Range and Efficiency</h2>

<p>The Hyundai IONIQ is a fairly normal small family car, except of course that
it&rsquo;s electric. The first thing people want to know about an electric vehicle
(EV) is the range. In my opinion, charging speed is at least as important as
range but we&rsquo;ll get to that in a bit.</p>

<p>The rated range is <strong>311 km (193 mi)</strong> according to the WLTP standard. However,
the WLTP can be optimistic for the Danish climate, and having a single
&ldquo;combined driving&rdquo; range number in your head can lead to disappointment when
you travel by motorway/highway &mdash; which is where range often matters the most.</p>

<p>Driving an EV makes you more aware of the factors that affect efficiency:
Speed, temperature, weather, tires, weight, aerodynamics, etc. Even though
these affect regular internal combustion engine (ICE) cars as well, you&rsquo;re just
more likely to notice them in an EV. Here&rsquo;s how much it matters:</p>

<p>Driving at 130 km/h (~80 mph) on a dry road just below freezing, with the
heat cranked up, I got:</p>

<ul>
<li>4.3 km/kWh (2.7 mi/kWh) or 23 kWh/100km (37 kWh/100mi), or</li>
<li>38 km/L (89 MPG US) or 2.6 L/100km in fuel equivalents, or</li>
<li><strong>165 km (102 mi) estimated range</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Driving at 80 km/h (50 mph), and slowing down for the occasional town, in 9°C
(48°F) gave:</p>

<ul>
<li>8.8 km/kWh (5.5 mi/kWh) or 11 kWh/100km (18 kWh/100mi), or</li>
<li>78 km/L (183 MPG US) or 1.3 L/100km in fuel equivalents, or</li>
<li><strong>337 km (209 mi) estimated range</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Notice the amazing efficiency. While the Hyundai IONIQ&rsquo;s range is not
fantastic, its efficiency is. It was in fact the world&rsquo;s most efficient
production car, before the Tesla Model 3. But even so, range depends heavily on
speed and weather. I have not yet tried the car in the summer but I expect to
get <strong>250 km (155 mi) of range</strong> on the Danish motorways at 110&ndash;130 km/h
(~70&ndash;80 mph).</p>

<p>For short/city trips, the IONIQ is great. It&rsquo;s snappy, quiet, and clean, and I
never worry about range, only charging it once or twice per month. But for long
trips, charging speed is at least as important as range, and the 2020 IONIQ&rsquo;s
fast-charging speed is unfortunately not especially good &mdash; a trait shared
with most of the least expensive EVs.</p>

<a name="Charging.Basics"></a>
<h2>Charging Basics</h2>

<p>EV charging is complicated, compared to the ol&#8217; gas/petrol fill-ups. Charging
speed varies by a great deal, depending on the power that the charging station
will deliver and the power the car will accept. The power that the charging
station can deliver can roughly be classified into <strong>home/destination</strong> (AC)
charging which takes hours and (DC) <strong>fast-charging</strong> which takes minutes. The
power that the car will accept is governed by the car&rsquo;s battery management
system, and depends on the exact battery technology used in the car, but also
on the state of charge of the battery (fullness percentage), and even the
battery temperature.</p>

<a name="Fast-Charging"></a>
<h2>Fast-Charging</h2>

<p>For long trips, a big battery with a long range is nice for the first leg of
the trip if you start off fully charged. But after that, the big battery is not
of much help if it takes a long time to charge. It would be faster overall to
have a smaller battery that charges quickly. The best is of course a big
battery that charges quickly.</p>

<p>Charging speed is generally expressed in kW (kilowatts a.k.a. kilojoules per
second), but another useful metric is km/h or mph, as in &ldquo;how much range can I
add in one hour of charging&rdquo;. This makes it easy to compare vehicles with
different battery sizes and efficiencies, based on some combined driving style.</p>

<p>According to the EV Database, the <a href="https://ev-database.org/car/1165/Hyundai-IONIQ-Electric">2020 Hyundai IONIQ</a> will
charge at <strong>210 km/h (130 mph)</strong>, when connected to a 50 kW fast-charger &mdash;
that is, a charger that will deliver as much power as the car wants, up to 50
kW. This charging speed is comparable to that of a Chevrolet Bolt, Renault Zoe,
or Nissan Leaf (small battery). While 210 km/h (130 mph) is fast as a driving
speed, it&rsquo;s not a crazy charging speed. In case of the IONIQ it means spending
50 minutes to charge it from 10% to 80% state of charge. (The slow charge from
80% and up is typically reserved for home/destination charging.) Taking a break
once in a while is a good thing, and 50 minutes can be a nice food break on a
roadtrip. But many breaks only need to be short, and with the 2020 IONIQ, up to
a third of your time will be spent charging on long trips.</p>

<p>More expensive EVs will be able to accept charge at a faster rate. Everything
over 300 km/h (~185 mph) also requires faster charging stations providing from
75 kW up to 350 kW, which may be rarer than 50 kW stations. Around <strong>400 km/h
(~250 mph)</strong> charging speed we find cars such as Ford Mustang Mach-E, the long
range versions of Nissan Leaf and Hyundai Kona, and, ironically, the older
2016&ndash;2019 Hyundai IONIQ with a smaller battery. Further up we have the
Polestar 2 and the top versions of Volkswagen ID.3 and ID.4, and Skoda Enyaq.
Even further up we have Audi, Porsche, and Tesla. The upcoming
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c2tHJD6mMbE">IONIQ 5</a> crossover should be able to compete
at the top, at up to <strong>960 km/h (~600 mph)</strong> charging speed.</p>

<p>At the moment, many EVs are great city cars, but only some are great for long
distance. Or rather, they have the potential to be great, if paired with good
charging infrastructure &mdash; this is a topic for another time. I expect to post
an update when I get more personal experience with longer trips. Also note that
while the IONIQ&rsquo;s charging speed is not great, the car <em>is</em> fully capable of
long trips, and has a good range for the price. More city-oriented EVs have
shorter range or will be pushed to their limit at highway speeds.</p>

<a name="Home.Destination.Charging"></a>
<h2>Home/Destination Charging</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/hyundai_ioniq_electric_2020_charging.jpg"></p>

<p>Home or destination charging is slower, but just like fast-charging, available
power vs. receivable power applies. The slowest form of charging is trickle
charging using an ICCB (In-Cable Control Box) cable. All EVs are slow charging
with this type because power is limited by supply rather than demand. A
household outlet might supply at most around 2 kW and should only be used for
prolonged periods in emergencies or if the outlet has been properly installed
for it. Slightly faster are the few CEE camping outlets that our municipality
have installed for public use in the city, where I get 2.6 kW. At this speed, a
full charge of the Hyundai IONIQ&rsquo;s 38 kWh battery from 0% to 100% takes <strong>17
hours</strong>. Cars with bigger batteries will take proportionately longer.</p>

<p>Proper home/destination wallboxes, like the one in the picture above, typically
supply 11 kW using three phases. This is the market standard, and what many EVs
will accept. For example, the long range versions of Hyundai Kona or Tesla
Model 3 will take <strong>7&ndash;8 hours</strong> for a full charge, and often less, because you
don&rsquo;t run the battery down to empty every time (or ever). A few cars, such as
the Renault Zoe, will slurp up 22 kW if the wallbox can supply it.</p>

<p>The Hyundai IONIQ with its single-phase charger is unfortunately more limited.
I might explore this in a future post, but in practice I get only 3.5 kW out of
an 11 or 22 kW wallbox, and a full charge takes <strong>13 hours</strong>. As with
fast-charging, the 2020 IONIQ is slow. On the other hand, home or destination
charging doesn&rsquo;t <em>need</em> to be fast, unless you drive a lot. There&rsquo;s more
interesting stuff about charging such as parking, prices, economy, etiquette,
reliability, and the availability of chargers for people like us who live in an
apartment, but for now I want to talk about the car itself.</p>

<a name="Driving.the.Hyundai.IONIQ.Electric"></a>
<h2>Driving the Hyundai IONIQ Electric</h2>

<p>As with many EVs, the best part about driving the Hyundai IONIQ is the
acceleration. Known as instant torque, an electric motor supplies high torque
from low RPMs whereas an internal combustion engine (ICE) needs high RPMs for
high torque. It also reacts quickly to pedal input, and has no downshifting
delay or turbo lag. Even though it is a modest car with &ldquo;only&rdquo; 100 kW (134 BHP)
and a 9.7 second 0&ndash;100 km/h (0&ndash;62 mph) time, it is still pretty fun in the
city. At medium speeds like 30&ndash;70 km/h (~20&ndash;45 mph), flooring the accelerator
will push you back in your seat. It&rsquo;s no Tesla, but it makes me smile.</p>

<p>At low speeds the acceleration does not feel quite as strong for some reason,
but it can still leave regular city drivers behind when the stop light turns
green, all without making noise. At highway speeds of 110 km/h (~70 mph) and
up, the acceleration feels fairly average. More powerful EVs will still be
snappy at high speeds, and of course extremely snappy at low speeds. Compared
with similarly priced EVs, the IONIQ has a high
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Sz7giPLTCss">top speed</a> of ~180 km/h (~110 mph),
probably thanks to its good aerodynamics.
The car feels very stable on the road, but the suspension feels too firm for a
family car, and I need to go over speed bumps quite slowly.</p>

<a name="Braking"></a>
<h2>Braking</h2>

<p>One of the advantages of electric cars, including hybrids, is that braking
turns the kinetic energy back into usable electrical energy instead of losing
it as heat. In the IONIQ, like in most EVs, the brake pedal will regenerate
power using the motor when pressed lightly, and only apply the disc brakes when
pressed hard. In between the two is a transition that works pretty well.</p>

<p>Power regeneration, and therefore braking, also occurs when letting go of the
accelerator pedal, with the level of <em>regen</em> being configurable in the IONIQ.
The default setting feels exactly as how I remember driving an automatic
transmission ICE car, but it is possible to both lower and increase the regen
from that. Level 0 is like coasting in Neutral, except pressing the accelerator
still speeds up the car. Level 1 is the default mild regen. Levels 2 and 3 get
you into <em>one-pedal driving</em> territory.</p>

<p>In one-pedal driving, the accelerator transitions smoothly between full
acceleration and medium braking, with the brake pedal and disc brakes only
required for emergency braking. Unfortunately, the IONIQ, like older Teslas,
does not brake all the way down to a standstill when you release the
accelerator, and so I still use the brake pedal at stop lights. The Nissan
Leaf, and newer Teslas, allow for complete one-pedal driving all the way down
to zero. (As an aside, Tesla separates itself from other EVs in that the brake
pedal does <em>not</em> regen, and apparently, the <a href="https://electrek.co/2020/10/27/tesla-removes-regenerative-braking-strenght-option-new-cars/">newest Teslas</a> can
<em>only</em> do one-pedal driving &mdash; no coasting.)</p>

<a name="Noise.and.Sound"></a>
<h2>Noise and Sound</h2>

<p>I love the ability of an EV to accelerate quickly without making noise. In
fact, every time I hear a loud car or motorcycle in the city I realize how
considerate EVs are to other people. In mean, please have fun in your sports
(ICE) car, but please do it somewhere else. Even the majority of normal people
in normal ICE cars produce a background level of noise in the city that is
detrimental to our health &mdash; like the emissions.</p>

<p>While I like the lack of noise, the IONIQ can be too quiet. It is actually
equipped with a loudspeaker for its VESS &ldquo;Virtual Engine Sound System&rdquo; which
makes a sci-fi humming sound to alert pedestrians, but it&rsquo;s just not very loud.
We live on the Aalborg waterfront where pedestrians often walk in the middle of
the street and the less observant pedestrians will not hear the car when I
approach from behind. I patiently wait behind them but it would sure be nice to
have a volume knob for the VESS.</p>

<p>While reversing, the VESS plays a distinct and louder &ldquo;ding&rdquo; sound. Again, I&rsquo;d
prefer just having a louder hum but at least the ding is noticeable. In fact so
much that I usually turn it off when parking at night, as the ding can be heard
from inside nearby apartments. It&rsquo;s not as loud as an ICE, but different.</p>

<p>The inside of the car is quiet at low speeds, but somewhat noisy on the highway
due to wind and rolling noise. More expensive cars will have more sound
insulation, but you can&rsquo;t get everything in an economy car.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/hyundai_ioniq_electric_2020b.jpg"></p>

<a name="Practicality.and.Features"></a>
<h2>Practicality and Features</h2>

<p>The good efficiency of the IONIQ comes in part from its good aerodynamics &mdash;
not just a low drag coefficient, but a low cross-sectional area as well. The
car is 145 cm (4&#8217;9&#8221;) tall and that has a few disadvantages. The sloping
liftback roofline means that the back seat does not have a lot of headroom.
Even in the front, with the driver&rsquo;s seat lowered all the way down, my big
lockdown hair sometimes touched the ceiling until my recent haircut (I&rsquo;m ~188
cm (6&#8217;2&#8221;)). The rear window does not have great visibility, and there&rsquo;s no rear
windshield wiper.</p>

<p>The charge port is located on the side of the car like a regular fuel door
which is a bit annoying since many public chargers in Denmark seem to expect
you to charge from the front of the car. Actually, it&rsquo;s probably more correct to
say that the charging stations are annoying.</p>

<p>The IONIQ includes plenty of tech such as automatic lane keeping and emergency
braking, adaptive cruise control, keyless entry and start, Android Auto and
Apple CarPlay, heat pump, heated side-view mirrors, heated seats, heated
steering wheel, parking sensors front + back, backup camera, etc.</p>

<p>Like probably a lot of other new cars it also has a touch screen that doesn&rsquo;t
work with gloves (presumably a capacitive touch screen). At least the climate
control &ldquo;buttons&rdquo; below the touch screen work with gloves (presumably resistive
touch buttons). Thankfully, the steering wheel buttons are old-school push
buttons (unlike in the Volkswagen ID.3 and ID.4).</p>

<a name="On.and.Off"></a>
<h2>On and Off</h2>

<p>The IONIQ is built on a platform that includes a hybrid and a plug-in hybrid
version, and this makes it feel &ldquo;last gen&rdquo; compared to cars built on pure EV
platforms. Among other things because it uses the old on/off paradigm:</p>

<ul>
<li>Get in</li>
<li>Turn car on</li>
<li>Switch to Drive</li>
<li>Drive</li>
<li>Switch to Park</li>
<li>Engage parking brake</li>
<li>Turn car off</li>
<li>Leave car</li>
</ul>


<p>The key is wireless and the parking brake will disengage automatically in
Drive, but it&rsquo;s still more steps than is necessary. It&rsquo;s especially easy to
forget to turn the car off after use because there&rsquo;s no motor noise/vibration
to make you feel that it&rsquo;s on. And if (when) you do forget, the IONIQ lets out
a prolonged, piercing beep when you close the door from the outside. Instead, a
simpler and friendlier sequence would be:</p>

<ul>
<li>Get in</li>
<li>Switch to Drive</li>
<li>Drive</li>
<li>Switch to Park</li>
<li>Leave car</li>
</ul>


<p>The Volkswagen ID.3 and ID.4 work like this, except even switching to
<a href="https://youtu.be/0Zzpsn_D9HA?t=208">Park is optional</a> &mdash; it will automatically apply the
parking brake when you open the door, and turn off when you leave.</p>

<a name="Conclusion"></a>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Overall, the IONIQ Electric is a nice car. It&rsquo;s fantastic for city use, and
unlike cheaper EVs, it&rsquo;s fully capable of long trips &mdash; as long as you are
patient when charging. If long trips are only occasional it is still a good EV
for the price. The best value would be if you have your own home charger and a
medium long daily commute. But in the end, charging speed is the 2020 IONIQ&rsquo;s
Achilles&#8217; heel when it comes to using the car as your only or primary car.</p>

<p>A Tesla Model 3 SR+ would be bigger and better in range, acceleration, and
charging speed, but it would also cost 75% more to purchase in Denmark. In
between the IONIQ and Model 3 are some good options though: Peugeot e-208,
Hyundai Kona, Nissan Leaf e+, Volkswagen ID.3, Volkswagen ID.4, and Skoda
Enyaq. The upcoming <a href="https://www.topgear.com/car-reviews/ioniq-5/first-drive">IONIQ 5</a> and its sister
<a href="https://www.topgear.com/car-news/electric/new-kia-ev6-and-fast-version-will-do-0-62mph-35s">Kia EV6</a> also look very interesting. In general, the future is
set to bring a lot of exciting development in EVs.</p>

<p>If you want to know more about EVs I can recommend the YouTube channel of
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/youtube_bjornnyland">Bjørn Nyland</a> for car reviews and tests, and
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCgBPvqu6vqvO3MmTjQZ0lfg">Plug Life Television</a> with more background info on
charging, economics, society, and the environment, as well as some beautiful EV
roadtrips. Also check out <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/fullychargedshow">Fully Charged Show</a>
including their EV beginner&rsquo;s guides.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RIP Mercurial (on Bitbucket)]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2019/08/28/rip-mercurial-on-bitbucket/"/>
    <updated>2019-08-28T07:39:28+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2019/08/28/rip-mercurial-on-bitbucket</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://bitbucket.org/">Bitbucket</a> is going to <a href="https://bitbucket.org/blog/sunsetting-mercurial-support-in-bitbucket">drop support</a> for the
<a href="https://www.mercurial-scm.org/">Mercurial</a> version control system, due to most people using
<a href="https://git-scm.com/">Git</a> instead. I use both Mercurial (hg) and Git, and while Git has become
the de facto standard today, Mercurial was my first love in the world of
version control systems, and I&rsquo;m sad to see it go.</p>

<p>Of course, Mercurial is not dead, but being removed from Bitbucket is a big
deal (at least to me). But this news also gave me an occasion to reconsider Git
vs. Mercurial, and writing this post has actually given me a newfound, if not
appreciation, then at least understanding of Git.</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Init"></a>
<h2>Init</h2>

<p>When I started university in 2006, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apache_Subversion">SVN</a> had recently replaced <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concurrent_Versions_System">CVS</a>
as the cool thing. So for group work we used SVN and it worked fine. Well,
except for all the file conflicts we got. And the awful tree conflicts. Come to
think of it, it didn&rsquo;t work that great. Luckily
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Distributed_version_control">distributed version control systems</a> had been maturing in the meantime.</p>

<p>In 2009 we started using Mercurial. It was like SVN, except it was actually
good for collaboration! Now you could store a safe snapshot of your own work
before trying to merge other people&rsquo;s changes in. Also merging generally worked
well. Also it was fast.</p>

<p>All was good, but there was also this Git thing people on the internet were
talking about. Coming from SVN, Mercurial made sense and Git didn&rsquo;t. (Linus
Torvalds, being Linus Torvalds, made Git purposely different from the CVS/SVN
family.) Git did seem to be more flexible at the expense of being less elegant.
As was written back then:
<a href="https://importantshock.wordpress.com/2008/08/07/git-vs-mercurial/">Git is MacGyver, Mercurial is James Bond</a>.</p>

<p>My group mates and I kept using Mercurial, but as I started my PhD,
collaboration with new people, not least my supervisor René, made me spend more
time with Git. It got better when I began to understand that the differences
between Mercurial and Git start at fundamental concepts such as branches and
merges.</p>

<a name="Different.Concepts"></a>
<h2>Different Concepts</h2>

<p>&ldquo;Branch&rdquo; doesn&rsquo;t have the same interpretation in Mercurial and Git. In
Mercurial, a branch is a sequence of commits all sharing a (permanent) name. In
Git, a branch is temporary and is represented by a reference to the current
commit at the tip of the branch. Once gone, you can&rsquo;t tell which branch(es)
a commit used to be part of.</p>

<p>In Mercurial branches are also shared between clones of the same repository.
Everybody works on the same branch, and you can <a href="https://www.mercurial-scm.org/repo/hg/help/pull"><code>hg pull</code></a> to get the
newest version of the branch, and then <a href="https://www.mercurial-scm.org/repo/hg/help/update"><code>hg update</code></a> your working
copy. In Git nobody works on the same branch &mdash; there&rsquo;s just people working on
different branches that might or might not have the same name. You can&rsquo;t
&ldquo;update&rdquo; to the newest version because you already have the newest version of
your own branch by definition. But you can <em>merge</em> another branch, possibly
with the same name, into your own.</p>

<p>In Mercurial, merges are used for merging divergent branches or heads. In Git,
everything is a merge, even if only one branch has changed. But at the same
time, a Git merge might or might not create a merge commit. By default, a new
commit will only be created if the two branches had diverged, i.e., work had
been done on both. Otherwise, the current branch will just be updated to point
to the same commit as the branch being merged in. It makes a lot of sense once
you get used to Git, but before that it&rsquo;s just confusing.</p>

<a name="Different.Commands"></a>
<h2>Different Commands</h2>

<p>Learning Git from an SVN/Mercurial background meant relearning a few words.
&ldquo;Revert&rdquo; means something new in Git and &ldquo;shelve&rdquo; is called &ldquo;stash&rdquo;, but that&rsquo;s
not bad. Instead, what is annoying is that many simple Mercurial commands don&rsquo;t
have simple, memorable equivalents in Git:</p>

<p>Show the hash of the current commit:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>hg id
</span><span class='line'>git rev-parse HEAD</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Show which commits would be pulled or pushed:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>hg in
</span><span class='line'>git fetch && git log ..@{u}
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>hg out
</span><span class='line'>git fetch && git log @{u}..</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Mark a file to stop tracking, but don&rsquo;t delete the file. This one is especially
weird in Git because you don&rsquo;t remove something <em>-&#8203;-cached</em>, you cache
(stage) the removal of something:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>hg forget
</span><span class='line'>git rm --cached</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Print the root directory of the repository and the URL of the remote repository:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>hg root
</span><span class='line'>hg path
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>git rev-parse --show-toplevel
</span><span class='line'>git config --get remote.origin.url</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>List the version controlled files:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>hg manifest
</span><span class='line'>git ls-tree -r --name-only --full-tree HEAD</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<a name="Git.is.Git"></a>
<h2>Git is Git</h2>

<p>I have been using the above commands as aliases in Git, but I have wondered if
doing that somehow prevented me from learning the &ldquo;true spirit&rdquo; of Git. I have
now come to the conclusion that the essence of Git is its architecture and data
model, and not its incoherent command line interface. Learning the user
interface is just a chore, and using aliases to smooth it out is fine.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not bashing Git because it&rsquo;s different from Mercurial, but because it is
internally inconsistent and, as another blogger puts it:
<a href="https://stevebennett.me/2012/02/24/10-things-i-hate-about-git/">Git doesn’t so much have a leaky abstraction as no abstraction.</a>
Here are some of the inconsistencies and lacking abstractions:</p>

<ul>
<li>Concepts can have multiple names, like the index a.k.a. the cache a.k.a. the
staging area (which would be okay if Git didn&rsquo;t already have so many
concepts)</li>
<li>The branch <code>origin/master</code> is your (local) remote tracking branch, but
<code>master</code> alone can refer to your local master branch or to the remote&rsquo;s
master branch depending on context</li>
<li>The <a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-checkout"><code>git checkout</code></a> command famously does too much: It can
check out a branch (merging in uncommitted changes in the process if you
want, or creating a new branch manually or automatically if you want), and it
can restore or overwrites individual files in the working copy

<ul>
<li>However, the new Git 2.23 released this month has started experimenting
with the new, more specific, and subject to change
<a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-switch"><code>git switch</code></a> and <a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-restore"><code>git restore</code></a> commands
(similar to <a href="https://www.mercurial-scm.org/repo/hg/help/update"><code>hg update</code></a> and <a href="https://www.mercurial-scm.org/repo/hg/help/revert"><code>hg revert</code></a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The notation <code>A:B</code> sometimes means <code>&lt;src&gt;:&lt;dst&gt;</code> (a refspec) and sometimes
<code>&lt;rev&gt;:&lt;path&gt;</code> (path in a revision &mdash; to be distinguished from a pathspec
which is a third concept that can use the colon in a third way)</li>
<li>The notations <code>A B</code> and <code>A..B</code> mean the same thing to <a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-diff"><code>git diff</code></a>
but not to <a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-log"><code>git log</code></a></li>
<li>The notations <code>A..B</code> and <code>A...B</code> mean somewhat opposite things to
<a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-diff"><code>git diff</code></a> and <a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-log"><code>git log</code></a>

<ul>
<li>To specify branches A and B symmetrically you need <code>git diff A..B</code> but <code>git
log A...B</code></li>
<li><code>git diff A...B</code> and <code>git log A..B</code> mean &ldquo;from the common ancestor of A and
B, to B&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>In the end, I think Git is a good tool despite its command line interface. But
if you&rsquo;re the type of person who needs to understand something in depth to feel
comfortable with it, you have a lot of reading to do. If you already know the
basics, <a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/gitglossary"><code>git help gitglossary</code></a> will get you started on 80+
underlying concepts that will help you on your way to master the world&rsquo;s
favored VCS!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Assistant Currently Unavailable for This Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2019/05/31/google-assistant-currently-unavailable-for-this-language/"/>
    <updated>2019-05-31T11:28:46+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2019/05/31/google-assistant-currently-unavailable-for-this-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One day I said &ldquo;Hey Google&rdquo; and my <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/11/19/google-pixel-2-first-impressions/">Pixel</a> didn&rsquo;t respond. After a few
more unsuccessful tries I went into the settings and saw that Voice Match &mdash;
the feature that lets you activate Google Assistant by voice &mdash; &ldquo;is currently
unavailable for this language&rdquo;. I found this strange since the language was set
to <strong>English</strong>, and it used to work. Now, neither US nor UK English, nor
Danish, could make it work.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/google_assistant_voice_match_unavailable.png"></p>

<p>I googled the problem and found lots of tips, but none of them worked. Later
I found a solution, that I&rsquo;ll post here in the hopes of helping someone else.</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Toward.The.Solution"></a>
<h2>Toward The Solution</h2>

<p>Before I found the solution I checked several things after googling the
problem. I confirmed that the microphone did work in other apps. In fact, it
even worked in the Google app itself when activated by touch instead of voice.
I didn&rsquo;t have other voice assistants installed that could somehow conflict with
Google Assistant. I couldn&rsquo;t retrain the voice model as some recommended since
the whole Voice Match feature was unavailable. I tried rebooting, uninstalling
Google app updates, clearing its cache, reinstalling the updates, rebooting
some more, all to no avail.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/google_assistant_android_language_preferences.png"></p>

<p>Besides the system Voice settings&#8217; language preferences, the Google app&rsquo;s
Assistant settings also have language preferences. Here, I also had English
(tried both US and UK), so that couldn&rsquo;t be the unsupported language either.
Finally I went to the system settings&#8217; main language preferences, which are
a <em>third</em> language setting in the same Google/Android ecosystem. My main
language was set to &ldquo;English (Denmark)&rdquo;.</p>

<a name="Solution"></a>
<h2>Solution</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not enough to use a supported language, the regional variant also has to
be supported and set in the correct one out of three sets of language
preferences. &ldquo;English (Denmark)&rdquo; doesn&rsquo;t work, but setting the main system
language preferences&#8217; top or only language to &ldquo;English (United States)&rdquo; does.
Presumably English from other primarily English-speaking regions works as well.</p>

<p><strong>After changing my <em>main</em> system language to &ldquo;English (United States)&rdquo;
I could now activate Voice Match a.k.a. &ldquo;OK Google&rdquo;/&ldquo;Hey Google&rdquo;.</strong></p>

<a name="Problems"></a>
<h2>Problems</h2>

<p>The above is more of a hack than an actual solution, because it prevents me
from using Danish regional (time, date, number, etc.) formats on Android while
using Voice Match.</p>

<p>When I got my Pixel 2 I had set it myself to &ldquo;English (United States)&rdquo;. This
worked fine until I later installed Google Fit and wanted its calendar view to
use Monday as the first day of the week, rather than Sunday. The app didn&rsquo;t
have it&rsquo;s own setting for this, but it worked after I changed the main system
language to &ldquo;English (Denmark)&rdquo;. I don&rsquo;t use Google Assistant every day, so
when &ldquo;Hey Google&rdquo; later didn&rsquo;t work, I didn&rsquo;t immediately make the connection
to the region change.</p>

<p>If the original error message had been &ldquo;This feature is currently unavailable
for <em>English (Denmark)</em>&rdquo;, rather than the generic &ldquo;this language&rdquo;, it would
have been much easier to fix. Even better, Android should use the Voice
settings&#8217; language as the voice language. Or the Assistant settings&#8217; language
as the assistant language. Or stop having so many language settings! Or let
Voice Match fall back to a supported language variant if the chosen one is
unsupported.</p>

<a name="More.Problems"></a>
<h2>More Problems</h2>

<p>Speaking of Google Assistant problems, I just <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2019/may/28/a-white-collar-sweatshop-google-assistant-contractors-allege-wage-theft">read</a> that many of the
linguists that helped create Google Assistant were treated with mistrust and
being paid less than 20% of what permanent staff makes, while also expected to
do unlogged overtime. I appreciate that not all skills are in equal demand, and
therefore pay, but that&rsquo;s no excuse to treat people with a lack of respect <em>on
top of</em> low pay and inferior health insurance. I think Google should choose to
treat <em>all</em> its workers with dignity. #DontBeEvil</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Pin RemoteApps to the Taskbar]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2019/04/24/how-to-pin-remoteapps-to-the-taskbar/"/>
    <updated>2019-04-24T00:09:57+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2019/04/24/how-to-pin-remoteapps-to-the-taskbar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/pin_remoteapps_pin_start.png"></p>

<p>In Microsoft Windows you can &ldquo;pin&rdquo; apps to the taskbar so you can launch them
with a single click. You can right click and pin an app when it is running in
the taskbar, or anytime through the start menu. But some apps, such as
<a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/Enterprise-Mobility-Security/Introducing-RemoteApp-and-Desktop-Connections/ba-p/246803">RemoteApps and Desktop Connections</a>, cannot be pinned.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><span class='caption-wrapper center' style='width: 568px'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/pin_remoteapps_remoteapp_no_pin_running.png' width='550' height='131' alt='No "Pin to taskbar" option from running RemoteApp'><span class='caption-text'>No &ldquo;Pin to taskbar&rdquo; option from running RemoteApp</span></span></p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center' style='width: 678px'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/pin_remoteapps_remoteapp_no_pin_start.png' width='660' height='365' alt='No "Pin to taskbar" option from the start menu'><span class='caption-text'>No &ldquo;Pin to taskbar&rdquo; option from the start menu</span></span></p>

<a name="Solution"></a>
<h2>Solution</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/pin_remoteapps_remoteapp_props.png"></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how I pin RemoteApps to the taskbar for easy access:</p>

<ol>
<li>Open the file location of the RemoteApp from the start menu (see image
above)</li>
<li>Open the Properties dialog for the RemoteApp shortcut and copy the Target</li>
<li>Pin a random app to the taskbar, e.g. Command Prompt, to be a temporary
placeholder.</li>
<li>In File Explorer, go to the folder <div><em>%appdata%\Microsoft\Internet
Explorer\Quick Launch\User Pinned\TaskBar</em></div></li>
<li>Open the Properties dialog for the placeholder app shortcut</li>
<li>Overwrite the Target by pasting from the clipboard, and click OK</li>
<li><strong>In the start menu, the RemoteApp can now be pinned</strong></li>
<li>Unpin the placeholder from the taskbar</li>
</ol>


<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/pin_remoteapps_remoteapp_pin_start.png"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/pin_remoteapps_remoteapp_pinned.png"></p>

<a name="Details"></a>
<h2>Details</h2>

<p>It might seem like a roundabout way to deal with multiple shortcuts instead of
simply adding the desired shortcut to <em>%appdata%\Microsoft\Internet
Explorer\Quick Launch\User Pinned\TaskBar</em>. Unfortunately, simply adding
a shortcut in the TaskBar folder will not make it show up in the taskbar. This
is because the registry decides what is displayed. (The relevant information is
at <em>HKCU\Software\Microsoft\Windows\CurrentVersion\Explorer\Taskband</em> but it is
not easy to edit by hand.) The recipe above tricks Windows into letting the
RemoteApp be added the normal way so the registry gets the correct info. Tested
on Windows 10 Enterprise, version 1803.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spar penge med Rejsekortets mængderabat [Danish]]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2019/01/17/spar-penge-med-rejsekortets-maengderabat/"/>
    <updated>2019-01-17T07:52:10+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2019/01/17/spar-penge-med-rejsekortets-maengderabat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort.jpg"></p>

<p>Jeg prøver noget nyt og skriver på dansk. Jeg startede med at skrive denne
artikel på engelsk, men nu hvor jeg har skiftet til dansk føler jeg ikke vores
allesammens <a href="https://www.rejsekort.dk/">Rejsekort</a> behøver nogen introduktion. Det er normalt
for tech-bloggere at komme ind på it-sikkerhed eller brugervenlighed når det
gælder Rejsekortet, men i dag vil jeg snakke om noget lidt andet, nemlig
hvordan man undgår at snyde sig selv i Rejsekortets indviklede rabatsystem.
Vest for Storebælt kan man nemlig i flere tilfælde spare penge ved at rejse
<em>mere</em> hver måned.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>(Men først lige én kommentar om grafisk design: Sort tekst på en blå baggrund,
som på billedet af mit rejsekort herover, er dårligt design. Min
billedbehandling overdriver lidt her, men illustrerer faktisk fint hvor svært
det er at læse sort på blåt under dårlige lysforhold. Nå, tilbage til
rabatten.)</p>

<a name="Rejsekortets.Rabatter"></a>
<h2>Rejsekortets Rabatter</h2>

<p>Rejsekortet giver <a href="https://www.rejsekort.dk/brug-rejsekort/priser-for-rejser/">to typer rabat</a> på rejser: tidsrabat og
mængderabat. Tidsrabat gives når rejsen starter uden for myldretiden, mens
mængderabat afhænger af hvor mange rejser man har haft i de foregående tre
måneder. Rabatterne afhænger desuden af typen af rejsekort, transportmidlet,
samt både udgangspunktet og destinationen.</p>

<p>Tidsrabatten er nem at få &mdash; man skal lægge sin rejse uden for myldretiden
(som kan være kl. 7&ndash;11 og 13&ndash;18 på hverdage, men det afhænger af region,
transportmiddel og type af rejsekort, naturligvis) &mdash; men derudover afhænger
den ikke af noget. Derfor fokuserer jeg på mængderabatten, som på mere
indviklet vis påvirkes af fortiden. Jeg antager desuden at man benytter et
personligt rejsekort for voksne &mdash; I modsætning til flex, anonym, barn, ung,
pensionist, handicappet, hund/cykel, pendler, pendler kombi,
erhverv/institution, glemte jeg nogen?</p>

<a name="Rejsekortets.m..ngderabat"></a>
<h2>Rejsekortets mængderabat</h2>

<p>Mængderabatten afhænger af både udgangspunkt og destination, og forudsætter at
mindst én af disse to ligger vest for Storebælt (sorry, sjællændere). Rejser
<em>over</em> Storebælt har én rabatskala, mens rejser udelukkende vest for Storebælt
har en anden, som jeg her vil arbejde videre med. Rejsekortet har teknisk set
otte forskellige rabattrin, men vest for Storebælt giver flere af dem samme
rabatsats, så jeg arbejder blot med fire rabattrin.</p>

<p>Mængderabatsatserne i procent er ens mellem regionerne, men rejsens grundpris
varierer mellem regionerne, og kan også afhænge af transportmidlet. Jeg
benytter priserne fra Nordjylland gældende fra 20. januar 2019 i det følgende,
men grundprincippet er det samme uanset gamle og nye priser samt region. Det
fulde prisblad findes <a href="https://www.rejseplanen.dk/bin/help.exe/mn?L=vs_rkfc&amp;tpl=prisblad">her</a>.</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Rejser/måned</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Rabat</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Pris for 2 zoner</strong> </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 0&ndash;3             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 0%                                </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 16,90 kr.                                    </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 4&ndash;15            </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 10%                               </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 15,21 kr.                                    </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 16&ndash;33           </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 25%                               </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 12,67 kr.                                    </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 34&ndash;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 40%                               </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 10,14 kr.                                    </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><br>
Rabattrinnet i en given måned sættes ud fra den af de tre sidste måneder med
flest rejser. Måned skal dog ikke nødvendigvis forstås som kalendermåned.
I stedet har man en <em>rabatskiftedato</em> (fx den 5. i hver måned) som afhænger af
hvornår ens rejsekort blev taget i brug. For at det ikke skal blive for nemt
kan man ikke aflæse sin rabatskiftedato på Rejsekortets
<a href="https://selvbetjening.rejsekort.dk/">selvbetjening</a>, men skal i stedet ringe til kundeservice for at
få den oplyst.</p>

<a name="Beregning.med.m..ngderabat"></a>
<h2>Beregning med mængderabat</h2>

<p>Hvis vi forudsætter at man rejser det samme antal ture hver måned, så betaler
man i alt følgende pr. måned afhængig af antallet af rejser:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort_rabat1.png"></p>

<p>Rejser man 14, 15 eller 28&ndash;33 rejser pr. måned, betaler man mere pr. måned end
hvis man rejste lidt mere. Man kan altså spare penge, fra og med næste måned,
ved at rejse lidt mere. Så hvis man har flere steder, man skal hen, kan man
blot nyde turen og de 10&ndash;72 kr. man sparer hver måned.</p>

<p>Men har man ikke behov for at rejse mere, er der stadig penge at spare ved at
foretage nogle få ekstra rejser. Så længe man har opnået et højere rabattrin
end normalt gælder det nemlig i tre måneder, hvori ens normale antal rejser
også bliver billigere, og man dermed opnår en besparelse:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort_rabat2.png"></p>

<p>Prisen for at opnå denne besparelse er at rejse nogle ekstra rejser for at nå
op på det næste rabattrin, dvs. nå op på 4, 16 eller 34 rejser i én måned.
Dette kan være så lidt som én ekstra rejse eller så meget som 18 rejser for at
nå fra 16 til 34. Omkostningen ved disse skal lægges i én måned, men fordelen
gælder i tre, så derfor viser jeg her omkostningen pr. måned, dvs. delt med
tre:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort_rabat3.png"></p>

<p>Jo færre ekstrarejser der er behov for, jo lavere er den samlede ekstrapris.
Befinder man sig i de store spænd 11&ndash;15 eller 22&ndash;33 rejser pr. måned, er
besparelsen større end omkostningen. I den laveste del af disse spænd er den
samlede besparelse mindst og tidsforbruget ved at rejse de ekstra rejser
størst, så man må selv vurdere om man synes besparelsen er indsatsen værd. Mest
får man ud af de ekstra rejser hvis man normalt ligger på 30&ndash;33 rejser, da man
her kan spare 60&ndash;80 kr. om måneden vha. nogle få ekstra rejser.</p>

<p>Omkostningen kan bringes yderligere ned: De ekstra rejser kan foretages uden
for myldretiden, dvs. med 20% tidsrabat, hvorved de fordelagtige spænd udvides
til 3, 10&ndash;15 og 20&ndash;33. Hvis man tre måneder senere vil gentage manøvren,
gøres det denne gang ud fra det højere rabattrin, man har opnået, og spændene
er nu, inkl. tidsrabat, 3, 10&ndash;15 og 18&ndash;33. Med andre ord er det kun hvis man
rejser 0&ndash;2, 4&ndash;9, 16 eller 17 gange om måneden at det <em>ikke</em> kan betale sig at
opnå et højere rabattrin.</p>

<a name="L..ngere.rejser"></a>
<h2>Længere rejser</h2>

<p>Jeg vil også nævne muligheden for pendlerkort. I Nordjylland koster 2 zoner
i 30 dage 380 kr., dvs. ca. 385 kr. for en gennemsnitlig måned, hvilket er
billigere end 31&ndash;33 rejser pr. måned på næsthøjeste rabattrin og 39+ rejser på
højeste rabattrin med det almindelige rejsekort:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort_rabat4.png"></p>

<p>Jeg foretrækker dog det almindelige rejsekort over pendlerkortet, herunder
pendler kombi, da den rabat jeg opsparer på mine daglige, korte rejser også
gælder på længere rejser vest for Storebælt med det almindelige rejsekort. Med
40% mængderabat sparer jeg 150 kr. på én tur/retur Aalborg&ndash;Aarhus, og 290 kr.
for Aalborg&ndash;Odense.</p>

<p>Hvis man dagligt eller ofte rejser længere end 2 zoner kan man også spare penge
i dagligdagen med metoden med ekstrarejser. Her er fordelen at de ekstra rejser
er billigere end de normale, da man kan nøjes med at rejse 2 zoner på
ekstrarejserne, da det udelukkende er antallet af rejser &mdash; ikke længden &mdash;
der afgør rabattrinnet. Dermed bliver omkostningen mindre i forhold til
besparelsen. Som eksempel ser vi her på 8 zoner, som er afstanden fra Aalborg
til Hjørring eller Hobro:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort_rabat5.png"></p>

<p>Allerede fra seks månedlige rejser på 8 zoner er det en fordel at opnå det
næste rabattrin. Ved 30&ndash;33 rejser er der 250&ndash;300 kr. at hente hver måned
i gennemsnit (besparelse fraregnet omkostning). Ved 26 zoner sparer man <em>altid</em>
penge ved at opnå det næste rabattrin, op til 837 kr./måned! Det har jeg
illustreret i følgende diagram.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort_rabat6.png"></p>

<p>Hvis man lige som før gentager de ekstra rejser efter tre måneder med tidsrabat
og det opnåede næste rabattrin, er der endda lidt mere at spare:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort_rabat7.png"></p>

<p>Det er nok de færreste der kan klemme sig op i højre hjørne, specielt uden at
investere i et pendlerkort hvis man pendler langt, men det er vildt at
muligheden er der. Man skal dog huske at det kun hjælper hvis man i forvejen
rejser færre end 34 rejser pr. måned. Er man først deroppe, er der ikke flere
rabatniveauer at opnå &mdash; man kan blot kigge på om et pendlerkort er billigere.</p>

<p><em>Opdatering 2019-08-28: Lille sprogfejl rettet.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Android 9 Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/11/06/android-9-impressions/"/>
    <updated>2018-11-06T08:43:18+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/11/06/android-9-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/android9_homescreen.png"></p>

<p>Last year I got the <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/11/19/google-pixel-2-first-impressions/">Google Pixel 2</a> smartphone to try the pure Android
experience. It took a bit of time to get used to but I have come to appreciate
its simplicity and cleanness. But the main purpose was getting OS updates
directly from Google, without waiting for the OEMs. Besides monthly security
updates, the new Android 9 came in August. Here are my impressions after two
months, including Gesture Navigation, the Overview, Adaptive Battery, and
Digital Wellbeing, as well as my thoughts on the Pixel 2 after a year.</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Pixel.2.a.Year.Later"></a>
<h2>Pixel 2 a Year Later</h2>

<p>The two things I initially liked best about the Pixel 2 are still the best: The
speed and the screen. The speed and responsiveness of the device is still
amazing one year and OS update later. This is what using a computer &mdash; because
a smartphone is a computer &mdash; in 2018 should feel like. (Running Windows 10 on
a laptop does, incidentally, not feel like 2018.)</p>

<p>The brightness range of the screen is also still great. Not perfect, but
I certainly find myself needing <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.haxor">Screen Filter</a> less often than
before I got an OLED screen. The always-on screen feature that shows the time
and notifications when the screen is &ldquo;off&rdquo; was also neat at first, but I&rsquo;ve
since grown so accustomed to it that a device that doesn&rsquo;t have it now feels
antiquated. Similarly, the fingerprint sensor on the back was ok at first but
now makes the phone feel like a natural extension of my hand
(<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/shortcuts/2018/oct/30/get-a-grip-are-smartphones-ruining-our-manual-dexterity">for better or worse</a>).
And unlike the <a href="https://youtu.be/hrHf6XQpmk0?t=94">in-screen fingerprint sensor</a> of the new OnePlus 6T, the
traditional sensor does not blind you with its bright light at night.</p>

<p>The camera and speakers are still great, and I can still get through the day
with battery left to spare. To mention a few negatives, the volume rocker is
still too stiff, and I&rsquo;ve disabled the Active Edge squeeze feature completely
as it was more likely to be activated accidentally than when I actually needed
it.</p>

<a name="Android.9"></a>
<h2>Android 9</h2>

<p>Android 9 was released in August. Installing the update was extremely fast,
just like booting up the Pixel 2 was when I first turned it on a year ago.
Again, this feels like 2018. Other improvements made me wonder why they weren&rsquo;t
made sooner. The sound volume control now defaults to controlling media volume
instead of ringer volume, also when no media is playing. Now you can lower the
volume <em>before</em> your embarrassing video starts playing. Simple yet great.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/android9_rotate_button.png' width='497' height='138' alt='The rotate button works with and without gesture navigation enabled.'><span class='caption-text'>The rotate button works with and without gesture navigation enabled.</span></span></p>

<p>Another such feature is the screen rotation button. I prefer having screen
auto-rotate disabled so I can keep reading while lying on my side in bed or in
the sofa. But for the few times I did want the screen to rotate, it was
annoying to have to enable the auto-rotate feature and then disable it later
after use. Now in Android 9, if auto-rotate is disabled but the phone senses
it&rsquo;s been rotated, a little rotate button appears that let&rsquo;s you rotate the
screen, once, without messing with the general auto-rotate setting. If you
ignore it, the button goes away after some seconds. Made me wonder why this
wasn&rsquo;t built in many years ago.</p>

<a name="App.Switching.and.Overview"></a>
<h2>App Switching and Overview</h2>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/android9_overview.png' width='' height='' alt='The Overview/app switching screen of Android 9'><span class='caption-text'>The Overview/app switching screen of Android 9</span></span></p>

<p>As seen in the picture with the rotate button above, there are now two
different ways to navigate around Android 9. The new gesture navigation with
the &ldquo;pill&rdquo; button, as well as the traditional navigation bar.</p>

<p>In the traditional mode, the &ldquo;Overview button&rdquo; (the square) opens the Overview
where you can see recently used apps and switch to them. A second press of the
Overview button switches to the next most recently used app. This can be done
quickly, i.e., double tapping the Overview button to switch to the next most
recently used app.</p>

<p>Using gesture navigation, swiping up from the pill (or in fact anywhere on the
bottom of the screen) opens the Overview, while instead dragging the pill to
the right scrolls through recently used apps until you release it.</p>

<p>The Overview mode, besides app switching, lets you select and copy text, even
from apps that don&rsquo;t allow this during normal usage, which is a great feature.
It&rsquo;s also from the Overview that apps can be sent to split screen mode.</p>

<a name="To.Gesture.or.Not.to.Gesture"></a>
<h2>To Gesture or Not to Gesture</h2>

<p>Since I got the Pixel 2 last year, I have loved double tapping the Overview
button, so it was not like I desperately wanted a different way of navigating.
Happily, upgrading to Android 9 didn&rsquo;t force the switch to the new gesture
navigation. In fact, I had to enable it myself, by activating the &ldquo;Swipe up on
Home button&rdquo; gesture.</p>

<p>Swiping up is very smooth, and while you do it, the active app shrinks down to
the rectangle/preview shown in the Overview. If you continue swiping up, the
app drawer opens. In the Overview you can scroll sideways between the previews,
and to select one, you can tap it, or swipe it back down and out to full
screen. This part works well.</p>

<p>The sideways drag feature is a mixed bag. It&rsquo;s good for switching to the
previous app with a short, quick sideways swipe &mdash; even simpler than the old
double tap. If you hold and drag further, the sideways scroll snaps to each app
with satisfying haptic feedback, which is even better than the regular
Overview. But. The problem with the sideways drag is that in one-handed
operation, it invariably leads your thumb into an uncomfortable position.</p>

<p>This is why I prefer the short sideways swipe for the previous app and swiping
up to the Overview if I want to go further back. But this leads to a mental
overhead: Now I stop and think before gesturing. The old Overview button didn&rsquo;t
have this problem: Every switch starts with a press of the button. Gesture
navigation <em>looks</em> fancy, but I have to say my thumb prefers the old way.</p>

<a name="Adaptive.Battery"></a>
<h2>Adaptive Battery</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/android9_adaptive_battery.png"></p>

<p>According to android.com, &ldquo;Adaptive Battery learns how you like to use your
phone, so the apps and services you don&rsquo;t use as much aren&rsquo;t a battery drain&rdquo;.
Unlike gesture navigation, this feature was enabled automatically when
I upgraded.</p>

<p>When I travel for work, I book a taxi to the airport ahead of time, and in the
early morning on my travel day, the app notifies me when the taxi is ready to
pick me up. Except this didn&rsquo;t happen after I had upgraded to Android 9. In the
same vein, the airline app notifies me when the online check-in opens. Didn&rsquo;t
happen either. So mine and Android&rsquo;s ideas of &ldquo;using an app&rdquo; are not the same.
I also use the Dropbox app to upload my photos in the background &mdash; also
delayed from the &ldquo;optimization&rdquo;. Luckily, you can stop individual apps from
being optimized. On the other hand, I guess this feature also optimizes tons of
apps that I don&rsquo;t need to run in the background. So it&rsquo;s probably fine after
you have set up your exclusions.</p>

<a name="Digital.Wellbeing"></a>
<h2>Digital Wellbeing</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/android9_digital_wellbeing.png"></p>

<p>Finally, Android 9 brings the <a href="https://wellbeing.google/">Digital Wellbeing</a> feature which shows you
how much you use your smartphone, and offers you ways to reduce interruptions
and screen time.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s interesting to see how much I use my smartphone. The picture to the right
is from one of the aforementioned travel days, which brings my usage a bit
higher than usual. But besides the statistics I don&rsquo;t feel that the feature
brings me much. It helps reduce the number of notifications, but I have already
disabled the most nagging notifications myself, including all email
notifications (try it, it&rsquo;s great for your sanity).</p>

<p>It allows you to set time limits for app use, but I have already uninstalled my
time wasters such as the Facebook app. The &ldquo;Wind Down&rdquo; feature helps you go to
bed by enabling Do Not Disturb mode and turning the screen grayscale. I already
have DND and Night Light on a schedule. The grayscale mode is kinda cool, but
I often end up disabling it to see what I&rsquo;m doing.</p>

<p>I think Digital Wellbeing is a good idea, but I already knew that, it seems.
But I could see how many people could benefit from easy access to all these
settings to nudge them into reclaiming a bit of non-phone time.</p>

<p>All in all, Android 9 feels like evolution rather than revolution, but that&rsquo;s
fair. Smartphones themselves were a revolution that started only around ten
years ago, even though they have now invaded our lives. But we might start
seeing some bigger changes to the smartphone market already when next years
<a href="https://www.gsmarena.com/samsung_teases_galaxy_f_foldable_phone_days_before_its_developers_conference-news-34061.php">folds around</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using a Calendar as a To-Do List]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/07/29/using-a-calendar-as-a-to-do-list/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-29T11:45:42+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/07/29/using-a-calendar-as-a-to-do-list</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8679/16294164331_ea66ce297d_b.jpg' width='450' height='0' alt='[Improved LEGO Calendar Front](https://www.flickr.com/photos/billward/16294164331) by [Bill Ward](https://www.flickr.com/photos/billward/) / [CC BY 2.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/)'><span class='caption-text'><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/billward/16294164331">Improved LEGO Calendar Front</a> by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/billward/">Bill Ward</a> / <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">CC BY 2.0</a></span></span></p>

<p>Writing a to-do list is a useful way to create an overview of your tasks at
work, school, or home. But to-do lists sometimes grow faster than you check the
items off, and a long to-do list can drain your motivation rather than focus
it. I found a practical way to keep my to-do list short and useful: Use
a calendar.</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="The.Problem.With.To-Do.Lists"></a>
<h2>The Problem With To-Do Lists</h2>

<p>Often, there&rsquo;s simply not enough time to do all the stuff we want to do. If you
keep a list of your tasks, checking off and adding items over time, then you
will probably have seen your list grow longer and longer, unless you are very
realistic about the kinds of tasks you plan to do.</p>

<p>As the list grows longer, it becomes less useful. The many items distract you
from what is actually important, and checking off items feels like emptying the
ocean with a spoon. After some time you are more likely to start a new list
than to keep using the old one. And this is okay if it helps you get things
done that you care about. But it won&rsquo;t be long before the new list is also long
and &ldquo;icky&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I think it&rsquo;s normal to wish to get more stuff done than what you have time for,
but the cycle of starting and discarding to-do lists is not very productive.
It&rsquo;s mainly useful at the start of each cycle when the list is short. I found
that a practical way to <em>keep</em> my to-do list short (apart from having more
hours in a day) is to put it in my calendar.</p>

<a name="Using.a.Calendar"></a>
<h2>Using a Calendar</h2>

<p>By using a calendar, I mean that each task you write down should have
a specific date, time, and duration, and live among your &ldquo;normal&rdquo; appointments
and events. This helps you move from the abstract to-do list world where you
have all the time you need, to the real world where you have to be at least
a bit realistic about when you can start a task, and how much time you can
allot to it.</p>

<p>Considering the time something takes also forces you to be more specific about
what you are actually planning to do &mdash; which is the part you should write
down in the calendar! A concrete task description is much more likely to spur
you into action later. Vague, abstract goals are a major cause of
procrastination &mdash; whether you use a calendar or not.</p>

<p>Interruptions and a base level of unscheduled activities are likely both at
work and at home, so I leave time for these when I set the event duration.
I especially use the system at home where I also want to relax after work in
the evenings and weekends, so there my time estimation is very loose. I might
fill a small ten minute task into a one- or two-hour slot. My goal is not to do
focused work in all of the calendar event&rsquo;s duration. Instead, the goal is to
fill my calendar with no more tasks than I will realistically do in a day or
evening. Each day thus contains a <em>short to-do list</em>.</p>

<a name="The.Passage.of.Time"></a>
<h2>The Passage of Time</h2>

<p>If you overestimate your own capacity to perform tasks stuffing too much into
a single day, there will be undone tasks. This is another critical point where
a calendar separates itself from a regular old to-do list. An undone item in
a to-do list stays there, as a future activity. An undone item in a calendar
lies in the past where you will probably forget about it. This is a feature,
not a bug!</p>

<p>If you did not have time to perform a task, you can reschedule it to a less
burdened day. If the task is important to you, you are also likely to remember
to reschedule it immediately.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/google_calendar_todo.png' width='' height='' alt='Google Calendar trying to be helpful.'><span class='caption-text'>Google Calendar trying to be helpful.</span></span></p>

<p>But often, &ldquo;not having time&rdquo; simply means not caring enough, and in that case,
it&rsquo;s also likely that you will even forget to reschedule the task, which is
good because it prevents that unimportant task from clogging up your future
to-do lists/days.</p>

<p>While tasks may be unimportant from their inception, others become obsolete
because an alternate solution to the problem was found or because of changing
priorities. Sometimes you will reschedule a task multiple times before
realizing that it is not important enough to keep. Or perhaps you will finally
do the task after seven reschedulings, because you eventually had more time or
willpower. The system adapts to your capacity over time.</p>

<p>The way that a regular to-do list keeps all undone tasks is the cause of long,
icky lists. Requiring a manual action to keep an undone task highlights the
absurdity of indefinite postponement. (Indefinitely rescheduling a few tasks is
certainly possible, but as you try to do it with more and more tasks, the extra
work of rescheduling should remind you that this is not a sustainable
solution.)</p>

<p>Any calendar should do the trick; I use Google Calendar. But sometimes when
I add a new event that sounds like a to-do, it suggests converting it to one
instead of creating an event. This is a disservice. I <em>do</em> want the passage of
time to clean up the stuff I&rsquo;m never going to get done anyway.</p>

<a name="What.is.Important."></a>
<h2>What is Important?</h2>

<p>In the previous section I say that importance influences what you get done and
what you should reschedule. What is important is of course up to you. But why
do we even have unimportant tasks? I don&rsquo;t think it should be seen as an
either-or. Instead, it depends on how much time and energy we have available.</p>

<p>In my case, I have many ideas for small home improvements and hobby projects
that the dreaming part of me wants to do but the actual me doesn&rsquo;t feel like
doing. It&rsquo;s not that I strictly don&rsquo;t have time, it&rsquo;s just that I would rather
be doing something else. So they are not actually important. Buying someone
a birthday present or doing my taxes would be important.</p>

<p>Some tasks are given to you by other people, perhaps especially at work. Does
that mean that they are important? Some of them of course, but not necessarily
all of them. Just like the tasks you set for yourself, tasks given by someone
else can also fall in the nice-to-have category. Or they are &ldquo;important&rdquo; to
your boss, but there are fifty things that are even more important. Other
times, the important thing is the goal, and reaching the goal through steps
X-Y-Z can make steps A-B-C obsolete. (Remember, a to-do list should contain
<em>doable</em> tasks, not goals.)</p>

<p>A classic distinction in time management and productivity is between
<a href="http://observer.com/2017/03/urgent-vs-important-the-simplest-way-to-stay-productive-and-do-the-right-work/">urgent and important</a> tasks. By using the calendar I do not mean
you should focus on time and urgency over importance. The only goal is to keep
your daily to-do list short enough as to boost motivation rather than drain it.
As with a regular to-do list, it&rsquo;s up to you to figure out what is important in
your life.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yousician "No tempo definitions found"]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/07/28/yousician-no-tempo-definitions-found/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-28T12:23:29+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/07/28/yousician-no-tempo-definitions-found</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/yousician_no_tempo_definitions.png"></p>

<p>This summer my girlfriend and I started practicing piano with <a href="https://yousician.com">Yousician</a>,
which is a kind of gamified music tutor, that listens to your playing and gives
instant feedback. It contains songs of gradually increasing difficulty, plus
you can upload your own songs in the <a href="https://www.musicxml.com/">MusicXML</a> format.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Adding songs is very easy&rdquo;, claims <a href="https://yousician.zendesk.com/hc/en-us/articles/207247365-What-is-MusicXML-file-and-how-to-upload-it">the documentation</a>, but at our
first attempt we were met with this error message: <strong>&ldquo;No tempo definitions
found. Please specify tempo in the file.&rdquo;</strong> Googling the error message gave no
results at all, so hopefully this post will change that.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="left" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/musicxml_hello_world.gif"></p>

<p>MusicXML is an interchange format with files typically generated or exported
from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scorewriter">scorewriter programs</a>. But us being programmers, we looked
to the XML itself to fix the problem. To find a
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimal_Working_Example">minimal working example</a>, we tried the
<a href="https://www.musicxml.com/tutorial/hello-world/">MusicXML &ldquo;Hello World&rdquo;</a> example. Uploaded to Yousician, it gave the
same error message about the tempo missing.</p>

<a name="Solution"></a>
<h2>Solution</h2>

<p>If you control the scorewriter generating the MusicXML file and it allows
including tempo when you export, that should be the simple solution. Otherwise,
in the first <code>&lt;measure&gt;</code> element, add <code>&lt;sound tempo="120"/&gt;</code> with your desired
tempo in BPM:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='xml'><span class='line'><span class="cp">&lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot; standalone=&quot;no&quot;?&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="cp">&lt;!DOCTYPE score-partwise PUBLIC</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="cp">    &quot;-//Recordare//DTD MusicXML 3.1 Partwise//EN&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="cp">    &quot;http://www.musicxml.org/dtds/partwise.dtd&quot;&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;score-partwise</span> <span class="na">version=</span><span class="s">&quot;3.1&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;part-list&gt;</span> ... <span class="nt">&lt;/part-list&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;part</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">&quot;P1&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&lt;measure</span> <span class="na">number=</span><span class="s">&quot;1&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;sound</span> <span class="na">tempo=</span><span class="s">&quot;120&quot;</span><span class="nt">/&gt;</span>  <span class="c">&lt;!-- ADD THIS ELEMENT --&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;attributes&gt;</span> ... <span class="nt">&lt;/attributes&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;note&gt;</span> ... <span class="nt">&lt;/note&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      ...
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<a name="Details"></a>
<h2>Details</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think Yousician complies completely with the MusicXML standard.
Two things from the documentation of the <a href="https://usermanuals.musicxml.com/MusicXML/Content/CT-MusicXML-sound.htm">sound element</a>:</p>

<ul>
<li>The sound element [&hellip;] can stand alone within a part/measure [&hellip;]</li>
<li>If [the tempo is] 0, the sound-generating program should prompt the user at
the time of compiling a sound (MIDI) file.</li>
</ul>


<p>Yousician doesn&rsquo;t recognize a sound element in a part, only in a measure.
Second, if we see Yousician as a &ldquo;sound-generating program&rdquo; (it can play the
uploaded piece as a practice help, as well as play accompaniments), then it
doesn&rsquo;t satisfy the second part either. Tempo 0 will result in the message
&ldquo;Unfortunately something went wrong with file import.&rdquo; It would be better if it
prompted the user for a tempo, in case of both 0 and missing tempo.</p>

<p>However, tempo 1 was blindly accepted, resulting in a song slower than molasses
in January!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ubiquitous Language Problems]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/06/17/ubiquitous-language-problems/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-17T12:38:16+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/06/17/ubiquitous-language-problems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Language is tricky. Take the this post, for instance. It&rsquo;s not about language
problems that are ubiquitous. It&rsquo;s about problems related to <em>Ubiquitous
Language</em> &mdash; whether the problems themselves are ubiquitous or not.</p>

<p>Ubiquitous Language is a term from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain-driven_design">Domain-Driven Design</a> software
development practice. It refers to a set of well-defined project terms shared
by all participants: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subject-matter_expert">Domain experts</a>, business analysts, developers,
users. The term was coined by Eric Evans in his <a href="http://dddcommunity.org/book/evans_2003/">DDD book</a>. I haven&rsquo;t
actually read it, but the idea seems sensible: If developers live and breathe
the domain by speaking its language, their output is more likely to fit the
business needs, and developers and domain experts are more likely to understand
one another.</p>

<p>As a business analyst and developer, your task is to adopt the language of the
domain experts, <em>not</em> the other way around. But that doesn&rsquo;t mean that the
domain experts are home free. Changes are probably required to turn their
jargon into a well-defined set of terms that will ensure precise and
unambiguous communication in the project and to the users. Here are some of the
challenges I&rsquo;ve encountered in this process.</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Two.Words..One.Concept"></a>
<h2>Two Words, One Concept</h2>

<p>One problem is that people may use different words for the same concept. It is
preferable to use one word per concept, because it will simplify design
discussions and remove confusion arising from the possibility that the words
<em>could</em> have different meanings. The code and the user interface will also be
much easier to understand for developers and users, respectively, if a concept
always has the same name.</p>

<p>As an example, different project participants use the terms User and Employee.
If the business or system has only employees as users, either word is fine.
Picking one over the other risks having a winner and a loser in the process.
Sometimes finding a third term can be a good move, politically or socially.
Perhaps the term Account can cover the concept and satisfy both parties.</p>

<p>Other times, it turns out that the terms actually have different meanings.
Maybe not all users are employees or not all employees are users. In this case,
both terms can stay in the vocabulary, and their exact relationship will have
to be uncovered.</p>

<a name="One.Word..Two.Concepts"></a>
<h2>One Word, Two Concepts</h2>

<p>Another problem is that the same word may be used for different concepts.
Sometimes by different people, sometimes even by the same people. Take the term
Account from the previous section. There, it was taken to mean a user account.
But Account could also mean a bank account, or a even a client (one managed by
an account manager).</p>

<p>If the main business domain (such as banking, accounting, customer relationship
management) already has a specific interpretation of the term, the other
meanings should probably find other names (such as Client, User Account, or
Bank Account). I prefer avoiding partially overlapping terms, so if Account is
already taken, User is better than User Account &mdash; unless User also has
a meaning distinct from User Account.</p>

<a name="Types.and.Instances"></a>
<h2>Types and Instances</h2>

<p>A specific version of the One Word, Two Concepts problem is when the same word
is used about both instances and types. Perhaps the word Service is used about
a service provided to a customer on a specific date and time (such as
a haircut), but also about the type of service the company provides (such as
a haircut). Or Product can mean both a product from the product catalog and
a product in the context of a specific Order.</p>

<p>For these examples, possible concept names could be Service and Service Type as
well as Product and Order Product. It&rsquo;s a first step, but as easy as it is to
add a prefix or suffix, as easy it drop it again in conversation. A better
option is to choose names that don&rsquo;t have anything in common. An Order Product
could be an Order Line (which is actually a well-known concept). A Service
could be an Appointment, while the term Service refers to the type. Or perhaps
Service stays in the appointment interpretation, and Service Type could be
named Function.</p>

<a name="Software.Development.as.Domain"></a>
<h2>Software Development as Domain</h2>

<p>Service and Function are not to be confused with what a software developer
might understand by these terms. Software is a business domain on its own
right, but unless the <em>project&rsquo;s</em> domain is software, developers should let the
business domain take precedence.</p>

<p>It might be necessary for developers to discuss technical design involving
software terms that clash with the domain model (such as Class, Strategy,
Factory, Visitor). It doesn&rsquo;t make sense to rename well-known concepts from the
software domain, but unless the domain experts need to know about them, they
shouldn&rsquo;t be part of the domain model, and so they should only be used
internally between technical designers and developers.</p>

<p>But even inside the software domain, I have observed the One Word, Two Concepts
problem at work. The term Entity, itself used in DDD, can refer to both a type
and an instance. Peter Chen, who introduced the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entity%E2%80%93relationship_model">Entity-Relationship Model</a>, used the term Entity to mean an instance of
some <em>Entity Type</em>. What I mentioned earlier about dropping suffixes also
applies here, and many people, myself included, use Entity in the type meaning.
Ideally, the instance meaning is then referred to by a different word, such as
Object.</p>

<a name="Microsoft.Dynamics.CRM"></a>
<h2>Microsoft Dynamics CRM</h2>

<p>The Microsoft Dynamics Customer Relationship Management (CRM) software
interests me in two ways in relation to DDD and ubiquitous language.
Superficially, Microsoft CRM uses the terms Entity and Record in the above
mentioned type and instance meanings, respectively. But then in the Danish
translation of the software, they use the Danish word <em>objekt</em> &mdash; not
<em>entitet</em> &mdash; as the translation of Entity. (In fact my colleague recently
found out the whole system is translated by Bing!)</p>

<p>Second, Microsoft CRM is somewhat anti-DDD in the sense that the built-in
customer relationship management domain model can conflict with that of the
user organization. It&rsquo;s possible to adapt the built-in data model with new
entities, attributes, and relationships, and by renaming existing items. But
the renaming only applies to the user interface, not the code and database.
This forces developers to think in terms of the built-in model and to translate
back and forth between that and the organization&rsquo;s domain, which is exactly the
thing ubiquitous language tells you to avoid.</p>

<a name="Multiple.Contexts"></a>
<h2>Multiple Contexts</h2>

<p>In this post I have been touching on the matching of words and concepts, both
in general and in software development. In this, I have been simplifying by
focusing on building a single ubiquitous language and domain model for
a project. Part of DDD is acknowledging that a project can be too large for
a single unified model, and instead of trying to make such a model, you should
allow for multiple <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/BoundedContext.html">bounded contexts</a> and instead make sure to define
their boundaries and relationships. But inside each single context, make sure
to use one word per concept.</p>

<p>The more I think about it, the more I see that software development is itself
far too large to be a single context. Words such as <em>prototype</em> or
<em>implementation</em> have multiple meanings. A prototype can be a
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_prototyping">software product</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Function_prototype">function declaration</a>, or
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prototype_pattern">cloneable object</a>. Programmers will understand <em>implementation</em> as the
process of and result of turning the human readable design description into
executable computer code. But implementation can also mean taking that same
executable computer code &mdash; the software product &mdash; and embedding it
successfully in the organization that is going to use it.</p>

<p>So two things are important in achieving clear communication. First, make each
context internally sound, and second, be aware of the existence of multiple
contexts, especially when you are speaking with someone who normally thinks and
works in another context from you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flying in the Front Row]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/05/10/flying-in-the-front-row/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-10T15:50:10+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/05/10/flying-in-the-front-row</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I regularly fly to Copenhagen for work, and once in a while I&rsquo;m assigned
a front row seat &mdash; an ostensible upgrade. This must happen randomly as I have
not requested or paid for it. But after experiencing it few times, I&rsquo;d be
inclined to pay to <em>not</em> sit there again.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/wing_sunset.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>One of the joys of business trips is traveling light. For a one or two day
trip, I can fit all I need in my briefcase, and there&rsquo;s no need to queue early
to be sure to get a space for my carry-on suitcase in the overhead bins. (I
entirely avoid checking bags when I can.)</p>

<p>After boarding I work until it&rsquo;s time to take off, and then I slide my laptop
in my briefcase and the briefcase under the seat in front of me. Once we&rsquo;re in
the air, I slide it back out and get some more work done, without asking my
fellow passengers to get up while I get my bag. Easy peasy.</p>

<a name="Bags.Must.Be.Stowed"></a>
<h2>Bags Must Be Stowed</h2>

<p>The first problem of the front row stems from the rule that bags must be stowed
in the overhead bins during takeoff and landing.</p>

<p>If I board early, I can put my bag in the overhead bin and sit down without
access to my stuff while everyone else is boarding, with the added bonus that
if I sit in the 1C aisle seat, every third backpack-wearing passenger will bump
their backpack into me as they pass.</p>

<p>If I board late, I get to the second problem: There&rsquo;s very little overhead
space for the first row passengers because a lot of the bin space is reserved
for kit needed by the cabin crew. The little space gets filled quickly and I&rsquo;ll
have to go further down the rows until I find an empty slot. This is not
a problem at first, but after landing, once the disembarkation stampede begins,
getting from row 1 to 4 to get my bag while a hundred people are impatiently
going the opposite direction is not great.</p>

<p>I think one of the supposed advantages of the front row is to be one of the
first people to get off the plane. But that&rsquo;s not likely to happen if you have
baggage. Row 2 and 3 are better. Therefore I was happy when I was recently
assigned seat 2E. That lasted until I got on the plane and it turned out that,
on the right side (D-E-F), row 2 <em>was</em> the front row on that plane &mdash; no row
1.</p>

<a name="Longer.Flights"></a>
<h2>Longer Flights</h2>

<p>The above is just my annoyances with a process I&rsquo;d like to run smoothly as part
of a routine. On the short flight from Aalborg to Copenhagen, more time is
spent boarding, preparing, taxiing, and disembarking, than the actual 30
minutes in the air. On rarer, longer trips the efficiency of getting on and off
the plane seems less important, and the leg room perhaps more important.</p>

<p>Leg room depends on how the airline configures the seats. I often fly with
<em>Norwegian</em> and despite their label as a low-cost airline, they have enough
room in standard economy to fit my long legs &mdash; perhaps because they&rsquo;re
Scandinavian. Either way, the value of a front row seat in this regard will
depend on your legs compared with the leg room of your chosen airline.</p>

<p>But the extra room can be useful to others as well. What I&rsquo;ve found is that the
(not <em>that</em> large, by the way) space in front of the front row seats is where
the front toilet queue goes to stand every time the crew needs to pass with
a trolley.</p>

<p>All this is by the way as it relates to short-haul single-aisle aircraft with
no business class seats &mdash; only &ldquo;economy with extra legroom&rdquo;. These extra
legroom seats are exactly the ones I&rsquo;d like to avoid. The emergency exit rows
have some of the same problems as the front row, but with more overhead bin
space and less toilet queue. But I&rsquo;d take a standard economy seat over that as
well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Weird Keyboard]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/04/14/my-weird-keyboard/"/>
    <updated>2018-04-14T16:57:10+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/04/14/my-weird-keyboard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I use a weird computer keyboard: The <a href="https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/shop/advantage2/">Kinesis Advantage</a>.
It&rsquo;s a concave, columnar, split, tented, mechanical keyboard with thumb keys.
It&rsquo;s very comfortable and much better than anything Logitech or Microsoft have
ever labeled ergonomic.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/kinesis_advantage2.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Ergonomic.Features"></a>
<h2>Ergonomic Features</h2>

<p><strong>Columnar</strong> means that the keys are laid out in straight columns, so you don&rsquo;t
have to bend your fingers sideways as you curl and extend them &mdash; unlike on
a standard, staggered keyboard, where especially the left hand fingers need to
move unnaturally. The <strong>split</strong> also helps avoiding sideways bends for the
wrists. For more details, see the illustration of the <a href="https://www.trulyergonomic.com/store/unique-symmetric-columnar-key-arrangement--truly-ergonomic-mechanical-keyboard--orthogonal-matrix-non-staggered">Truly Ergonomic
keyboard</a> (which I haven&rsquo;t tried (yet)).</p>

<p><strong>Tented</strong> means that the thumb side of each hand sits higher than the pinky
side. This gives the wrists a more natural rotation. The Advantage only tilts
20 degrees &mdash; other keyboards such as the
<a href="https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/shop/freestyle2-for-pc-us/">Kinesis Freestyle</a> and the <a href="http://safetype.com">SafeType</a> can tent
(up to) 90 degrees (while <a href="https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/frreestyle2-ascent-90-1.jpg">looking</a> even less
conventional than the Advantage).</p>

<p>The <strong>thumb key</strong> clusters make more keys reachable without moving the hand
away from its home position, and it offloads Backspace and Enter from the
overworked right pinky and onto the stronger thumbs.</p>

<p>The <strong>mechanical</strong> keyswitches (Cherry MX brown or red) register the keypress
when the key is halfway depressed (2 out of 4 millimeters). This is opposed to
standard rubber dome keyboards that require you to bottom out &mdash; fully depress
the key until the finger is jolted to a stop.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/kinesis_advantage2_side.jpg"></p>

<p>The best feature of the Advantage is the <strong>concave</strong> keywells: The scooped-out
parts of the keyboard where the alphanumeric keys reside. They serve several
purposes:</p>

<ul>
<li>As you curl and extend your fingers, the keys remain at the same distance
from your fingertips, so you don&rsquo;t need to stretch your fingers much to
reach. This also makes it easy to access all five (!) rows of keys.</li>
<li>The same happens when you move your index finger to the side (like T, G, B),
reducing sideways-twisting finger motions.</li>
<li>The depths of the columns are matched with the corresponding fingers, so they
all rest naturally in the home position.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Switching"></a>
<h2>Switching</h2>

<p>I got my first Kinesis Advantage in 2011. As I recall, it only took a few days
to adapt to this weird keyboard. The best part is that I can still switch
effortlessly between the Advantage and standard, flat, staggered keyboards. Not
that I particularly enjoy it, but I can do it, which is very practical for
traveling. The Advantage is actually narrower than a standard 104/105-key
keyboard, but it&rsquo;s bigger in the two other dimensions and therefore not easy to
transport.</p>

<p>However, the physical shape of my keyboard is not the only weird thing about my
typing. The <em>logical</em> layout I use &mdash; <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2015/02/27/4-years-with-colemak/">Colemak</a> &mdash; is weird too.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/kinesis_advantage_custom_keycaps_right.jpg"></p>

<p>Switching logical layout is much harder for me than switching physical layout.
Even though the Advantage is firmware remappable, I set my logical layout in
the computer OS, so I will keep the logical layout for all keyboards, including
the laptop keyboard.</p>

<p>Some people retain their QWERTY touch typing skills while learning an
alternative layout by associating logical layout with physical keyboard, e.g.,
typing Colemak on the Advantage and QWERTY on standard keyboards. And I did
actually get the Advantage the same year I switched to Colemak, but I much
prefer typing Colemak on my laptop while traveling over maintaining my QWERTY
skills.</p>

<a name="Legends"></a>
<h2>Legends</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not really necessary have Colemak legends on the keys, but I did get a set
of custom keycaps made by <a href="http://www.wasdkeyboards.com/">WASD keyboards</a> for one of my two Advantages
&mdash; complete with my Danish variation of Colemak &mdash; as shown in the images
above and below. It&rsquo;s mostly for show, because the legends are not necessary
for touch typing, and the Advantage is not so good anyway for one-handed use
where the legends might be relevant.</p>

<p>In fact, hunt-and-peck typing is for some reason easier for me with QWERTY
legends, even while I type Colemak. My eyes are more used to the common QWERTY
layout, I guess. I just know that pressing the QWERTY &rsquo;T&#8217; key produces a &lsquo;G&rsquo; in
Colemak. If I look down and the key shows a &lsquo;G&rsquo;, my eyes get confused, even
though my fingers knows exactly where to press to get the &lsquo;G&rsquo; while touch
typing.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/kinesis_advantage_custom_keycaps_left.jpg"></p>

<a name="Downsides"></a>
<h2>Downsides</h2>

<p>The Advantage is not great for everything. Split keyboards are not good for the
occasional one-handed use (e.g., while holding a drink, phone, piece of paper).</p>

<p>The Advantage is not the best for gaming either. The arrow keys are spread on
both sides of the split which is fine for two-handed office and programming
use, but not ideal for gaming. The key positions are matched to finger lengths,
so the WASD keys will not work well with the normal WASD-fingers. ESDF should
be perfect, though.</p>

<p>For a long time, the typical complaint of the Advantage was the low quality of
the rubber F-keys. In 2016, the Advantage2 was launched, with Cherry ML
switches instead of rubber dome F-keys, and more programming options. This is
the product I link to in the top of the post because the product page for the
old version seems to be gone. I haven&rsquo;t tried it, but I can only imagine it&rsquo;s
an improvement.</p>

<p>Another problem partially solved by time is the built-in combined USB hub and
PS/2-to-USB converter. It &mdash; and the whole keyboard with it &mdash; didn&rsquo;t work
with Windows 7. Kinesis did sell a cable conversion kit to work around this,
but I went DIY and installed a PS/2-to-USB adapter myself, bypassing the
problematic USB hub, on my &ldquo;work&rdquo; board.</p>

<p>My &ldquo;home&rdquo; board always worked fine with Linux (and Windows 10), but it&rsquo;s also
not recognized by the BIOS of my desktop computer&rsquo;s motherboard. A smaller
problem but I&rsquo;m considering giving this board a USB hubectomy as well. The
Advantage2 has supposedly also solved this problem.</p>

<p>There are a few problems with the Advantage, but they are minor compared to the
Advantage (heh) of using an extremely comfortable keyboard for my 10+ daily
hours of computer usage.</p>

<a name="Key.Remapping"></a>
<h2>Key Remapping</h2>

<p>My remaining complaints were solved with easy firmware remapping, which is in
fact just a testament to the Advantage&rsquo;s flexibility:</p>

<ul>
<li>I swapped Space and Backspace because I have for some reason always used my
left hand&rsquo;s thumb for Space.</li>
<li>I use the Alt+Tab shortcut all the time, so I moved the Alt key closer to my
thumb in the left thumb cluster.</li>
<li>I made the key above Tab work as an Escape key.</li>
<li>I made the key below Tab work as a Control key because that&rsquo;s how control
freaks control.</li>
<li>I put Down to the left of Up because that&rsquo;s how Vim users roll.</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Update 2018-11-06: Minor clarifications.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Roland Boutique Needs]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/02/25/what-roland-boutique-needs/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-25T16:46:09+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/02/25/what-roland-boutique-needs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Roland Boutique is a series of small form factor electronic music instruments.
The line debuted in 2015 with recreations of three iconic Roland 1980s synths.
I got the JP-08 which I wrote about <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/06/25/roland-jp-08-review/">here</a>. Since then I&rsquo;ve been
watching the series grow with interest.</p>

<p>By now, the <a href="https://www.roland.com/us/promos/roland_boutique/">Boutique line</a> includes nine products recreating
Roland&rsquo;s back catalog: Five subtractive synths (JP-08, JU-06, JX-03, TB-03,
SH-01A), the VP-03 vocoder, the TR-08 and TR-09 drum machines, and finally the
D-05 &ldquo;linear synthesizer&rdquo; mixing sampling and synthesis.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/boutique_hero.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In 2017, Roland ventured outside their own history. Teaming up with Studio
Electronics, they released the Minimoog-inspired analog monosynth SE-02. Having
started down this path, they might make an FM (frequency modulation) synth.
Missing from the lineup is also perhaps a sampler/sample player/sample mangler?</p>

<p>That would at least match miniatures produced by other manufacturers in the
last few years. The very small and affordable Korg Volca series has the
straightforwardly named Beats, Bass, Keys, Sample, and FM. The first four
predated the original Boutique trio by 1-2 years, while the FM was released in
2016.</p>

<p>Swedish manufacturer Elektron also recently went small with the less toylike
&mdash; and less affordable &mdash; Digitakt sampler and Digitone FM-synth, with the
latter being announced just one month ago.</p>

<p>The 2015 Yamaha Reface series also has CS, DX, YC, and CP, doing synth, FM,
electric organ, and electric piano, respectively. And this leads me toward what
I would most like to see in the Roland Boutique series.</p>

<a name="Give.Me.a.Piano."></a>
<h2>Give Me a Piano!</h2>

<p>When you think of a digital piano, you are more likely to think of 88 weighted
keys than 25 non-weighted &ldquo;synth action&rdquo; minikeys. But one of the advantages of
the Boutiques is that they can both slot into the K-25m keyboard module and
perform as a sound module/desktop synth.</p>

<p>I would love to have a Roland Boutique piano with high-quality, natural,
acoustic piano sounds as well as high-quality electric pianos, organs, strings,
etc. I guess the model number would be in the form of FP-0x or RD-0x. I would
use such a Boutique piano module both as a sound module plugged into a MIDI
keyboard, and in the sofa as a plaything and/or compositional tool with the
K-25m keyboard attached.</p>

<p>The D-05 unfortunately does not fill this role. When the D-50 was launched in
1987 it certainly came closer than any analog synth to sounding like acoustic
instruments, but that doesn&rsquo;t mean it could actually pass for one. I went to my
local music store to try out the D-05, and while it does have a dozen patches
with &ldquo;piano&rdquo; in their name, none of them sound like an acoustic piano. It can
do electric pianos and organs, but overall I think the D-50/D-05 has a certain
80s/90s &ldquo;lo-fi&rdquo; sound. It excels at some things, but not acoustic piano.</p>

<a name="The.Panel"></a>
<h2>The Panel</h2>

<p>Some of the Boutiques have too many buttons crammed into the limited space on
the panel. This includes the <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/06/25/roland-jp-08-review/">JP-08</a>, and judging from pictures, also
the TR-08, TR-09 and SE-02. Some have a more reasonable amount, such as the
JU-06, SH-01A, and VP-03. The D-05 doesn&rsquo;t have too many buttons per se, but it
faithfully recreates the dreary menu diving experience of the &ldquo;digital age&rdquo; (to
achieve more hands-on programming of the D-50/D-550/D-05, you need the enormous
PG-1000 programmer). But, digital pianos typically do not have a lot of
buttons. So what do I want on the Boutique piano panel?</p>

<p>I can think of a lot!</p>

<ul>
<li>Better speaker(s), perhaps even front facing</li>
<li>Dedicated octave up/down buttons</li>
<li>A good pitch/modulation stick (yes, electric organs can <a href="http://www.organforum.com/forums/showthread.php?22171-Pitch-bending-on-a-Hammond-A-mystery">pitch bend</a>)</li>
<li>Effects! Reverb, Leslie, Overdrive, Chorus, you name it.</li>
<li>Loop machine</li>
<li>Tape recorder</li>
<li>Sequencer</li>
<li>Arpeggiator</li>
<li>Chord memory</li>
<li>Scale/chord library (like a <a href="https://www.islainstruments.com/product/kordbot/">KordBot</a>?)</li>
</ul>


<p>Finally, such a module shouldn&rsquo;t be expensive. Unless it would have several of
the above features, it should be closer to 150 €/$ than to 400 €/$. It&rsquo;s
a ripoff that the K-25m keyboard is already 100 €/$.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
