<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Erik Ramsgaard Wognsen]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/"/>
  <updated>2019-04-24T00:11:09+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.erw.dk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Ramsgaard Wognsen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Pin RemoteApps to the Taskbar]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2019/04/24/how-to-pin-remoteapps-to-the-taskbar/"/>
    <updated>2019-04-24T00:09:57+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2019/04/24/how-to-pin-remoteapps-to-the-taskbar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/pin_remoteapps_pin_start.png"></p>

<p>In Microsoft Windows you can &ldquo;pin&rdquo; apps to the taskbar so you can launch them
with a single click. You can right click and pin an app when it is running in
the taskbar, or anytime through the start menu. But some apps, such as
<a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/Enterprise-Mobility-Security/Introducing-RemoteApp-and-Desktop-Connections/ba-p/246803">RemoteApps and Desktop Connections</a>, cannot be pinned.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><span class='caption-wrapper center' style='width: 568px'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/pin_remoteapps_remoteapp_no_pin_running.png' width='550' height='131' alt='No "Pin to taskbar" option from running RemoteApp'><span class='caption-text'>No &ldquo;Pin to taskbar&rdquo; option from running RemoteApp</span></span></p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center' style='width: 678px'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/pin_remoteapps_remoteapp_no_pin_start.png' width='660' height='365' alt='No "Pin to taskbar" option from the start menu'><span class='caption-text'>No &ldquo;Pin to taskbar&rdquo; option from the start menu</span></span></p>

<a name="Solution"></a>
<h2>Solution</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/pin_remoteapps_remoteapp_props.png"></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how I pin RemoteApps to the taskbar for easy access:</p>

<ol>
<li>Open the file location of the RemoteApp from the start menu (see image
above)</li>
<li>Open the Properties dialog for the RemoteApp shortcut and copy the Target</li>
<li>Pin a random app to the taskbar, e.g. Command Prompt, to be a temporary
placeholder.</li>
<li>In File Explorer, go to the folder <div><em>%appdata%\Microsoft\Internet
Explorer\Quick Launch\User Pinned\TaskBar</em></div></li>
<li>Open the Properties dialog for the placeholder app shortcut</li>
<li>Overwrite the Target by pasting from the clipboard, and click OK</li>
<li><strong>In the start menu, the RemoteApp can now be pinned</strong></li>
<li>Unpin the placeholder from the taskbar</li>
</ol>


<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/pin_remoteapps_remoteapp_pin_start.png"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/pin_remoteapps_remoteapp_pinned.png"></p>

<a name="Details"></a>
<h2>Details</h2>

<p>It might seem like a roundabout way to deal with multiple shortcuts instead of
simply adding the desired shortcut to <em>%appdata%\Microsoft\Internet
Explorer\Quick Launch\User Pinned\TaskBar</em>. Unfortunately, simply adding
a shortcut in the TaskBar folder will not make it show up in the taskbar. This
is because the registry decides what is displayed. (The relevant information is
at <em>HKCU\Software\Microsoft\Windows\CurrentVersion\Explorer\Taskband</em> but it is
not easy to edit by hand.) The recipe above tricks Windows into letting the
RemoteApp be added the normal way so the registry gets the correct info. Tested
on Windows 10 Enterprise, version 1803.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spar penge med Rejsekortets mængderabat [Danish]]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2019/01/17/spar-penge-med-rejsekortets-maengderabat/"/>
    <updated>2019-01-17T07:52:10+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2019/01/17/spar-penge-med-rejsekortets-maengderabat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort.jpg"></p>

<p>Jeg prøver noget nyt og skriver på dansk. Jeg startede med at skrive denne
artikel på engelsk, men nu hvor jeg har skiftet til dansk føler jeg ikke vores
allesammens <a href="https://www.rejsekort.dk/">Rejsekort</a> behøver nogen introduktion. Det er normalt
for tech-bloggere at komme ind på it-sikkerhed eller brugervenlighed når det
gælder til Rejsekortet, men i dag vil jeg snakke om noget lidt andet, nemlig
hvordan man undgår at snyde sig selv i Rejsekortets indviklede rabatsystem.
Vest for Storebælt kan man nemlig i flere tilfælde spare penge ved at rejse
<em>mere</em> hver måned.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>(Men først lige én kommentar om grafisk design: Sort tekst på en blå baggrund,
som på billedet af mit rejsekort herover, er dårligt design. Min
billedbehandling overdriver lidt her, men illustrerer faktisk fint hvor svært
det er at læse sort på blåt under dårlige lysforhold. Nå, tilbage til
rabatten.)</p>

<a name="Rejsekortets.Rabatter"></a>
<h2>Rejsekortets Rabatter</h2>

<p>Rejsekortet giver <a href="https://www.rejsekort.dk/brug-rejsekort/priser-for-rejser/">to typer rabat</a> på rejser: tidsrabat og
mængderabat. Tidsrabat gives når rejsen starter uden for myldretiden, mens
mængderabat afhænger af hvor mange rejser man har haft i de foregående tre
måneder. Rabatterne afhænger desuden af typen af rejsekort, transportmidlet,
samt både udgangspunktet og destinationen.</p>

<p>Tidsrabatten er nem at få &mdash; man skal lægge sin rejse uden for myldretiden
(som kan være kl. 7&ndash;11 og 13&ndash;18 på hverdage, men det afhænger af region,
transportmiddel og type af rejsekort, naturligvis) &mdash; men derudover afhænger
den ikke af noget. Derfor fokuserer jeg på mængderabatten, som på mere
indviklet vis påvirkes af fortiden. Jeg antager desuden at man benytter et
personligt rejsekort for voksne &mdash; I modsætning til flex, anonym, barn, ung,
pensionist, handicappet, hund/cykel, pendler, pendler kombi,
erhverv/institution, glemte jeg nogen?</p>

<a name="Rejsekortets.m..ngderabat"></a>
<h2>Rejsekortets mængderabat</h2>

<p>Mængderabatten afhænger af både udgangspunkt og destination, og forudsætter at
mindst én af disse to ligger vest for Storebælt (sorry, sjællændere). Rejser
<em>over</em> Storebælt har én rabatskala, mens rejser udelukkende vest for Storebælt
har en anden, som jeg her vil arbejde videre med. Rejsekortet har teknisk set
otte forskellige rabattrin, men vest for Storebælt giver flere af dem samme
rabatsats, så jeg arbejder blot med fire rabattrin.</p>

<p>Mængderabatsatserne i procent er ens mellem regionerne, men rejsens grundpris
varierer mellem regionerne, og kan også afhænge af transportmidlet. Jeg
benytter priserne fra Nordjylland gældende fra 20. januar 2019 i det følgende,
men grundprincippet er det samme uanset gamle og nye priser samt region. Det
fulde prisblad findes <a href="https://www.rejseplanen.dk/bin/help.exe/mn?L=vs_rkfc&amp;tpl=prisblad">her</a>.</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right;"> <strong>Rejser/måned</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Rabat</strong> </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Pris for 2 zoner</strong> </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 0&ndash;3             </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 0%                                </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 16,90 kr.                                    </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 4&ndash;15            </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 10%                               </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 15,21 kr.                                    </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 16&ndash;33           </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 25%                               </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 12,67 kr.                                    </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 34&ndash;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 40%                               </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 10,14 kr.                                    </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><br>
Rabattrinnet i en given måned sættes ud fra den af de tre sidste måneder med
flest rejser. Måned skal dog ikke nødvendigvis forstås som kalendermåned.
I stedet har man en <em>rabatskiftedato</em> (fx den 5. i hver måned) som afhænger af
hvornår ens rejsekort blev taget i brug. For at det ikke skal blive for nemt
kan man ikke aflæse sin rabatskiftedato på Rejsekortets
<a href="https://selvbetjening.rejsekort.dk/">selvbetjening</a>, men skal i stedet ringe til kundeservice for at
få den oplyst.</p>

<a name="Beregning.med.m..ngderabat"></a>
<h2>Beregning med mængderabat</h2>

<p>Hvis vi forudsætter at man rejser det samme antal ture hver måned, så betaler
man i alt følgende pr. måned afhængig af antallet af rejser:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort_rabat1.png"></p>

<p>Rejser man 14, 15 eller 28&ndash;33 rejser pr. måned, betaler man mere pr. måned end
hvis man rejste lidt mere. Man kan altså spare penge, fra og med næste måned,
ved at rejse lidt mere. Så hvis man har flere steder, man skal hen, kan man
blot nyde turen og de 10&ndash;72 kr. man sparer hver måned.</p>

<p>Men har man ikke behov for at rejse mere, er der stadig penge at spare ved at
foretage nogle få ekstra rejser. Så længe man har opnået et højere rabattrin
end normalt gælder det nemlig i tre måneder, hvori ens normale antal rejser
også bliver billigere, og man dermed opnår en besparelse:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort_rabat2.png"></p>

<p>Prisen for at opnå denne besparelse er at rejse nogle ekstra rejser for at nå
op på det næste rabattrin, dvs. nå op på 4, 16 eller 34 rejser i én måned.
Dette kan være så lidt som én ekstra rejse eller så meget som 18 rejser for at
nå fra 16 til 34. Omkostningen ved disse skal lægges i én måned, men fordelen
gælder i tre, så derfor viser jeg her omkostningen pr. måned, dvs. delt med
tre:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort_rabat3.png"></p>

<p>Jo færre ekstrarejser der er behov for, jo lavere er den samlede ekstrapris.
Befinder man sig i de store spænd 11&ndash;15 eller 22&ndash;33 rejser pr. måned, er
besparelsen større end omkostningen. I den laveste del af disse spænd er den
samlede besparelse mindst og tidsforbruget ved at rejse de ekstra rejser
størst, så man må selv vurdere om man synes besparelsen er indsatsen værd. Mest
får man ud af de ekstra rejser hvis man normalt ligger på 30&ndash;33 rejser, da man
her kan spare 60&ndash;80 kr. om måneden vha. nogle få ekstra rejser.</p>

<p>Omkostningen kan bringes yderligere ned: De ekstra rejser kan foretages uden
for myldretiden, dvs. med 20% tidsrabat, hvorved de fordelagtige spænd udvides
til 3, 10&ndash;15 og 20&ndash;33. Hvis man tre måneder senere vil gentage manøvren,
gøres det denne gang ud fra det højere rabattrin, man har opnået, og spændene
er nu, inkl. tidsrabat, 3, 10&ndash;15 og 18&ndash;33. Med andre ord er det kun hvis man
rejser 0&ndash;2, 4&ndash;9, 16 eller 17 gange om måneden at det <em>ikke</em> kan betale sig at
opnå et højere rabattrin.</p>

<a name="L..ngere.rejser"></a>
<h2>Længere rejser</h2>

<p>Jeg vil også nævne muligheden for pendlerkort. I Nordjylland koster 2 zoner
i 30 dage 380 kr., dvs. ca. 385 kr. for en gennemsnitlig måned, hvilket er
billigere end 31&ndash;33 rejser pr. måned på næsthøjeste rabattrin og 39+ rejser på
højeste rabattrin med det almindelige rejsekort:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort_rabat4.png"></p>

<p>Jeg foretrækker dog det almindelige rejsekort over pendlerkortet, herunder
pendler kombi, da den rabat jeg opsparer på mine daglige, korte rejser også
gælder på længere rejser vest for Storebælt med det almindelige rejsekort. Med
40% mængderabat sparer jeg 150 kr. på én tur/retur Aalborg&ndash;Aarhus, og 290 kr.
for Aalborg&ndash;Odense.</p>

<p>Hvis man dagligt eller ofte rejser længere end 2 zoner kan man også spare penge
i dagligdagen med metoden med ekstrarejser. Her er fordelen at de ekstra rejser
er billigere end de normale, da man kan nøjes med at rejse 2 zoner på
ekstrarejserne, da det udelukkende er antallet af rejser &mdash; ikke længden &mdash;
der afgør rabattrinnet. Dermed bliver omkostningen mindre i forhold til
besparelsen. Som eksempel ser vi her på 8 zoner, som er afstanden fra Aalborg
til Hjørring eller Hobro:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort_rabat5.png"></p>

<p>Allerede fra seks månedlige rejser på 8 zoner er det en fordel at opnå det
næste rabattrin. Ved 30&ndash;33 rejser er der 250&ndash;300 kr. at hente hver måned
i gennemsnit (besparelse fraregnet omkostning). Ved 26 zoner sparer man <em>altid</em>
penge ved at opnå det næste rabattrin, op til 837 kr./måned! Det har jeg
illustreret i følgende diagram.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort_rabat6.png"></p>

<p>Hvis man lige som før gentager de ekstra rejser efter tre måneder med tidsrabat
og det opnåede næste rabattrin, er der endda lidt mere at spare:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rejsekort_rabat7.png"></p>

<p>Det er nok de færreste der kan klemme sig op i højre hjørne, specielt uden at
investere i et pendlerkort hvis man pendler langt, men det er vildt at
muligheden er der. Man skal dog huske at det kun hjælper hvis man i forvejen
rejser færre end 34 rejser pr. måned. Er man først deroppe, er der ikke flere
rabatniveauer at opnå &mdash; man kan blot kigge på om et pendlerkort er billigere.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Android 9 Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/11/06/android-9-impressions/"/>
    <updated>2018-11-06T08:43:18+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/11/06/android-9-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/android9_homescreen.png"></p>

<p>Last year I got the <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/11/19/google-pixel-2-first-impressions/">Google Pixel 2</a> smartphone to try the pure Android
experience. It took a bit of time to get used to but I have come to appreciate
its simplicity and cleanness. But the main purpose was getting OS updates
directly from Google, without waiting for the OEMs. Besides monthly security
updates, the new Android 9 came in August. Here are my impressions after two
months, including Gesture Navigation, the Overview, Adaptive Battery, and
Digital Wellbeing, as well as my thoughts on the Pixel 2 after a year.</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Pixel.2.a.Year.Later"></a>
<h2>Pixel 2 a Year Later</h2>

<p>The two things I initially liked best about the Pixel 2 are still the best: The
speed and the screen. The speed and responsiveness of the device is still
amazing one year and OS update later. This is what using a computer &mdash; because
a smartphone is a computer &mdash; in 2018 should feel like. (Running Windows 10
a laptop does, incidentally, not feel like 2018.)</p>

<p>The brightness range of the screen is also still great. Not perfect, but
I certainly find myself needing <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.haxor">Screen Filter</a> less often than
before I got an OLED screen. The always-on screen feature that shows the time
and notifications when the screen is &ldquo;off&rdquo; was also neat at first, but I&rsquo;ve
since grown so accustomed to it that a device that doesn&rsquo;t have it now feels
antiquated. Similarly, the fingerprint sensor on the back was ok at first but
now makes the phone feel like a natural extension of my hand
(<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/shortcuts/2018/oct/30/get-a-grip-are-smartphones-ruining-our-manual-dexterity">for better or worse</a>).
And unlike the <a href="https://youtu.be/hrHf6XQpmk0?t=94">in-screen fingerprint sensor</a> of the new OnePlus 6T, the
traditional sensor does not blind you with its bright light at night.</p>

<p>The camera and speakers are still great, and I can still get through the day
with battery left to spare. To mention a few negatives, the volume rocker is
still too stiff, and I&rsquo;ve disabled the Active Edge squeeze feature completely
as it was more likely to be activated accidentally than when I actually needed
it.</p>

<a name="Android.9"></a>
<h2>Android 9</h2>

<p>Android 9 was released in August. Installing the update was extremely fast,
just like booting up the Pixel 2 was when I first turned it on a year ago.
Again, this feels like 2018. Other improvements made me wonder why they weren&rsquo;t
made sooner. The sound volume control now defaults to controlling media volume
instead of ringer volume, also when no media is playing. Now you can lower the
volume <em>before</em> your embarrassing video starts playing. Simple yet great.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/android9_rotate_button.png' width='497' height='138' alt='The rotate button works with and without gesture navigation enabled.'><span class='caption-text'>The rotate button works with and without gesture navigation enabled.</span></span></p>

<p>Another such feature is the screen rotation button. I prefer having screen
auto-rotate disabled so I can keep reading while lying on my side in bed or in
the sofa. But for the few times I did want the screen to rotate, it was
annoying to have to enable the auto-rotate feature and then disable it later
after use. Now in Android 9, if auto-rotate is disabled but the phone senses
it&rsquo;s been rotated, a little rotate button appears that let&rsquo;s you rotate the
screen, once, without messing with the general auto-rotate setting. If you
ignore it, the button goes away after some seconds. Made me wonder why this
wasn&rsquo;t built in many years ago.</p>

<a name="App.Switching.and.Overview"></a>
<h2>App Switching and Overview</h2>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/android9_overview.png' width='' height='' alt='The Overview/app switching screen of Android 9'><span class='caption-text'>The Overview/app switching screen of Android 9</span></span></p>

<p>As seen in the picture with the rotate button above, there are now two
different ways to navigate around Android 9. The new gesture navigation with
the &ldquo;pill&rdquo; button, as well as the traditional navigation bar.</p>

<p>In the traditional mode, the &ldquo;Overview button&rdquo; (the square) opens the Overview
where you can see recently used apps and switch to them. A second press of the
Overview button switches to the next most recently used app. This can be done
quickly, i.e., double tapping the Overview button to switch to the next most
recently used app.</p>

<p>Using gesture navigation, swiping up from the pill (or in fact anywhere on the
bottom of the screen) opens the Overview, while instead dragging the pill to
the right scrolls through recently used apps until you release it.</p>

<p>The Overview mode, besides app switching, lets you select and copy text, even
from apps that don&rsquo;t allow this during normal usage, which is a great feature.
It&rsquo;s also from the Overview that apps can be sent to split screen mode.</p>

<a name="To.Gesture.or.Not.to.Gesture"></a>
<h2>To Gesture or Not to Gesture</h2>

<p>Since I got the Pixel 2 last year, I have loved double tapping the Overview
button, so it was not like I desperately wanted a different way of navigating.
Happily, upgrading to Android 9 didn&rsquo;t force the switch to the new gesture
navigation. In fact, I had to enable it myself, by activating the &ldquo;Swipe up on
Home button&rdquo; gesture.</p>

<p>Swiping up is very smooth, and while you do it, the active app shrinks down to
the rectangle/preview shown in the Overview. If you continue swiping up, the
app drawer opens. In the Overview you can scroll sideways between the previews,
and to select one, you can tap it, or swipe it back down and out to full
screen. This part works well.</p>

<p>The sideways drag feature is a mixed bag. It&rsquo;s good for switching to the
previous app with a short, quick sideways swipe &mdash; even simpler than the old
double tap. If you hold and drag further, the sideways scroll snaps to each app
with satisfying haptic feedback, which is even better than the regular
Overview. But. The problem with the sideways drag is that in one-handed
operation, it invariably leads your thumb into an uncomfortable position.</p>

<p>This is why I prefer the short sideways swipe for the previous app and swiping
up to the Overview if I want to go further back. But this leads to a mental
overhead: Now I stop and think before gesturing. The old Overview button didn&rsquo;t
have this problem: Every switch starts with a press of the button. Gesture
navigation <em>looks</em> fancy, but I have to say my thumb prefers the old way.</p>

<a name="Adaptive.Battery"></a>
<h2>Adaptive Battery</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/android9_adaptive_battery.png"></p>

<p>According to android.com, &ldquo;Adaptive Battery learns how you like to use your
phone, so the apps and services you don&rsquo;t use as much aren&rsquo;t a battery drain&rdquo;.
Unlike gesture navigation, this feature was enabled automatically when
I upgraded.</p>

<p>When I travel for work, I book a taxi to the airport ahead of time, and in the
early morning on my travel day, the app notifies me when the taxi is ready to
pick me up. Except this didn&rsquo;t happen after I had upgraded to Android 9. In the
same vein, the airline app notifies me when the online check-in opens. Didn&rsquo;t
happen either. So mine and Android&rsquo;s ideas of &ldquo;using an app&rdquo; are not the same.
I also use the Dropbox app to upload my photos in the background &mdash; also
delayed from the &ldquo;optimization&rdquo;. Luckily, you can stop individual apps from
being optimized. On the other hand, I guess this feature also optimizes tons of
apps that I don&rsquo;t need to run in the background. So it&rsquo;s probably fine after
you have set up your exclusions.</p>

<a name="Digital.Wellbeing"></a>
<h2>Digital Wellbeing</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/android9_digital_wellbeing.png"></p>

<p>Finally, Android 9 brings the <a href="https://wellbeing.google/">Digital Wellbeing</a> feature which shows you
how much you use your smartphone, and offers you ways to reduce interruptions
and screen time.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s interesting to see how much I use my smartphone. The picture to the right
is from one of the aforementioned travel days, which brings my usage a bit
higher than usual. But besides the statistics I don&rsquo;t feel that the feature
brings me much. It helps reduce the number of notifications, but I have already
disabled the most nagging notifications myself, including all email
notifications (try it, it&rsquo;s great for your sanity).</p>

<p>It allows you to set time limits for app use, but I have already uninstalled my
time wasters such as the Facebook app. The &ldquo;Wind Down&rdquo; feature helps you go to
bed by enabling Do Not Disturb mode and turning the screen grayscale. I already
have DND and Night Light on a schedule. The grayscale mode is kinda cool, but
I often end up disabling it to see what I&rsquo;m doing.</p>

<p>I think Digital Wellbeing is a good idea, but I already knew that, it seems.
But I could see how many people could benefit from easy access to all these
settings to nudge them into reclaiming a bit of non-phone time.</p>

<p>All in all, Android 9 feels like evolution rather than revolution, but that&rsquo;s
fair. Smartphones themselves were a revolution that started only around ten
years ago, even though they have now invaded our lives. But we might start
seeing some bigger changes to the smartphone market already when next years
<a href="https://www.gsmarena.com/samsung_teases_galaxy_f_foldable_phone_days_before_its_developers_conference-news-34061.php">folds around</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using a Calendar as a To-Do List]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/07/29/using-a-calendar-as-a-to-do-list/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-29T11:45:42+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/07/29/using-a-calendar-as-a-to-do-list</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8679/16294164331_ea66ce297d_b.jpg' width='450' height='0' alt='[Improved LEGO Calendar Front](https://www.flickr.com/photos/billward/16294164331) by [Bill Ward](https://www.flickr.com/photos/billward/) / [CC BY 2.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/)'><span class='caption-text'><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/billward/16294164331">Improved LEGO Calendar Front</a> by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/billward/">Bill Ward</a> / <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">CC BY 2.0</a></span></span></p>

<p>Writing a to-do list is a useful way to create an overview of your tasks at
work, school, or home. But to-do lists sometimes grow faster than you check the
items off, and a long to-do list can drain your motivation rather than focus
it. I found a practical way to keep my to-do list short and useful: Use
a calendar.</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="The.Problem.With.To-Do.Lists"></a>
<h2>The Problem With To-Do Lists</h2>

<p>Often, there&rsquo;s simply not enough time to do all the stuff we want to do. If you
keep a list of your tasks, checking off and adding items over time, then you
will probably have seen your list grow longer and longer, unless you are very
realistic about the kinds of tasks you plan to do.</p>

<p>As the list grows longer, it becomes less useful. The many items distract you
from what is actually important, and checking off items feels like emptying the
ocean with a spoon. After some time you are more likely to start a new list
than to keep using the old one. And this is okay if it helps you get things
done that you care about. But it won&rsquo;t be long before the new list is also long
and &ldquo;icky&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I think it&rsquo;s normal to wish to get more stuff done than what you have time for,
but the cycle of starting and discarding to-do lists is not very productive.
It&rsquo;s mainly useful at the start of each cycle when the list is short. I found
that a practical way to <em>keep</em> my to-do list short (apart from having more
hours in a day) is to put it in my calendar.</p>

<a name="Using.a.Calendar"></a>
<h2>Using a Calendar</h2>

<p>By using a calendar, I mean that each task you write down should have
a specific date, time, and duration, and live among your &ldquo;normal&rdquo; appointments
and events. This helps you move from the abstract to-do list world where you
have all the time you need, to the real world where you have to be at least
a bit realistic about when you can start a task, and how much time you can
allot to it.</p>

<p>Considering the time something takes also forces you to be more specific about
what you are actually planning to do &mdash; which is the part you should write
down in the calendar! A concrete task description is much more likely to spur
you into action later. Vague, abstract goals are a major cause of
procrastination &mdash; whether you use a calendar or not.</p>

<p>Interruptions and a base level of unscheduled activities are likely both at
work and at home, so I leave time for these when I set the event duration.
I especially use the system at home where I also want to relax after work in
the evenings and weekends, so there my time estimation is very loose. I might
fill a small ten minute task into a one- or two-hour slot. My goal is not to do
focused work in all of the calendar event&rsquo;s duration. Instead, the goal is to
fill my calendar with no more tasks than I will realistically do in a day or
evening. Each day thus contains a <em>short to-do list</em>.</p>

<a name="The.Passage.of.Time"></a>
<h2>The Passage of Time</h2>

<p>If you overestimate your own capacity to perform tasks stuffing too much into
a single day, there will be undone tasks. This is another critical point where
a calendar separates itself from a regular old to-do list. An undone item in
a to-do list stays there, as a future activity. An undone item in a calendar
lies in the past where you will probably forget about it. This is a feature,
not a bug!</p>

<p>If you did not have time to perform a task, you can reschedule it to a less
burdened day. If the task is important to you, you are also likely to remember
to reschedule it immediately.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/google_calendar_todo.png' width='' height='' alt='Google Calendar trying to be helpful.'><span class='caption-text'>Google Calendar trying to be helpful.</span></span></p>

<p>But often, &ldquo;not having time&rdquo; simply means not caring enough, and in that case,
it&rsquo;s also likely that you will even forget to reschedule the task, which is
good because it prevents that unimportant task from clogging up your future
to-do lists/days.</p>

<p>While tasks may be unimportant from their inception, others become obsolete
because an alternate solution to the problem was found or because of changing
priorities. Sometimes you will reschedule a task multiple times before
realizing that it is not important enough to keep. Or perhaps you will finally
do the task after seven reschedulings, because you eventually had more time or
willpower. The system adapts to your capacity over time.</p>

<p>The way that a regular to-do list keeps all undone tasks is the cause of long,
icky lists. Requiring a manual action to keep an undone task highlights the
absurdity of indefinite postponement. (Indefinitely rescheduling a few tasks is
certainly possible, but as you try to do it with more and more tasks, the extra
work of rescheduling should remind you that this is not a sustainable
solution.)</p>

<p>Any calendar should do the trick; I use Google Calendar. But sometimes when
I add a new event that sounds like a to-do, it suggests converting it to one
instead of creating an event. This is a disservice. I <em>do</em> want the passage of
time to clean up the stuff I&rsquo;m never going to get done anyway.</p>

<a name="What.is.Important."></a>
<h2>What is Important?</h2>

<p>In the previous section I say that importance influences what you get done and
what you should reschedule. What is important is of course up to you. But why
do we even have unimportant tasks? I don&rsquo;t think it should be seen as an
either-or. Instead, it depends on how much time and energy we have available.</p>

<p>In my case, I have many ideas for small home improvements and hobby projects
that the dreaming part of me wants to do but the actual me doesn&rsquo;t feel like
doing. It&rsquo;s not that I strictly don&rsquo;t have time, it&rsquo;s just that I would rather
be doing something else. So they are not actually important. Buying someone
a birthday present or doing my taxes would be important.</p>

<p>Some tasks are given to you by other people, perhaps especially at work. Does
that mean that they are important? Some of them of course, but not necessarily
all of them. Just like the tasks you set for yourself, tasks given by someone
else can also fall in the nice-to-have category. Or they are &ldquo;important&rdquo; to
your boss, but there are fifty things that are even more important. Other
times, the important thing is the goal, and reaching the goal through steps
X-Y-Z can make steps A-B-C obsolete. (Remember, a to-do list should contain
<em>doable</em> tasks, not goals.)</p>

<p>A classic distinction in time management and productivity is between
<a href="http://observer.com/2017/03/urgent-vs-important-the-simplest-way-to-stay-productive-and-do-the-right-work/">urgent and important</a> tasks. By using the calendar I do not mean
you should focus on time and urgency over importance. The only goal is to keep
your daily to-do list short enough as to boost motivation rather than drain it.
As with a regular to-do list, it&rsquo;s up to you to figure out what is important in
your life.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yousician "No tempo definitions found"]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/07/28/yousician-no-tempo-definitions-found/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-28T12:23:29+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/07/28/yousician-no-tempo-definitions-found</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/yousician_no_tempo_definitions.png"></p>

<p>This summer my girlfriend and I started practicing piano with <a href="https://yousician.com">Yousician</a>,
which is a kind of gamified music tutor, that listens to your playing and gives
instant feedback. It contains songs of gradually increasing difficulty, plus
you can upload your own songs in the <a href="https://www.musicxml.com/">MusicXML</a> format.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Adding songs is very easy&rdquo;, claims <a href="https://yousician.zendesk.com/hc/en-us/articles/207247365-What-is-MusicXML-file-and-how-to-upload-it">the documentation</a>, but at our
first attempt we were met with this error message: <strong>&ldquo;No tempo definitions
found. Please specify tempo in the file.&rdquo;</strong> Googling the error message gave no
results at all, so hopefully this post will change that.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="left" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/musicxml_hello_world.gif"></p>

<p>MusicXML is an interchange format with files typically generated or exported
from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scorewriter">scorewriter programs</a>. But us being programmers, we looked
to the XML itself to fix the problem. To find a
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimal_Working_Example">minimal working example</a>, we tried the
<a href="https://www.musicxml.com/tutorial/hello-world/">MusicXML &ldquo;Hello World&rdquo;</a> example. Uploaded to Yousician, it gave the
same error message about the tempo missing.</p>

<a name="Solution"></a>
<h2>Solution</h2>

<p>If you control the scorewriter generating the MusicXML file and it allows
including tempo when you export, that should be the simple solution. Otherwise,
in the first <code>&lt;measure&gt;</code> element, add <code>&lt;sound tempo="120"/&gt;</code> with your desired
tempo in BPM:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='xml'><span class='line'><span class="cp">&lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot; standalone=&quot;no&quot;?&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="cp">&lt;!DOCTYPE score-partwise PUBLIC</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="cp">    &quot;-//Recordare//DTD MusicXML 3.1 Partwise//EN&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="cp">    &quot;http://www.musicxml.org/dtds/partwise.dtd&quot;&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;score-partwise</span> <span class="na">version=</span><span class="s">&quot;3.1&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;part-list&gt;</span> ... <span class="nt">&lt;/part-list&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;part</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">&quot;P1&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&lt;measure</span> <span class="na">number=</span><span class="s">&quot;1&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;sound</span> <span class="na">tempo=</span><span class="s">&quot;120&quot;</span><span class="nt">/&gt;</span>  <span class="c">&lt;!-- ADD THIS ELEMENT --&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;attributes&gt;</span> ... <span class="nt">&lt;/attributes&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;note&gt;</span> ... <span class="nt">&lt;/note&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      ...
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<a name="Details"></a>
<h2>Details</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think Yousician complies completely with the MusicXML standard.
Two things from the documentation of the <a href="https://usermanuals.musicxml.com/MusicXML/Content/CT-MusicXML-sound.htm">sound element</a>:</p>

<ul>
<li>The sound element [&hellip;] can stand alone within a part/measure [&hellip;]</li>
<li>If [the tempo is] 0, the sound-generating program should prompt the user at
the time of compiling a sound (MIDI) file.</li>
</ul>


<p>Yousician doesn&rsquo;t recognize a sound element in a part, only in a measure.
Second, if we see Yousician as a &ldquo;sound-generating program&rdquo; (it can play the
uploaded piece as a practice help, as well as play accompaniments), then it
doesn&rsquo;t satisfy the second part either. Tempo 0 will result in the message
&ldquo;Unfortunately something went wrong with file import.&rdquo; It would be better if it
prompted the user for a tempo, in case of both 0 and missing tempo.</p>

<p>However, tempo 1 was blindly accepted, resulting in a song slower than molasses
in January!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ubiquitous Language Problems]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/06/17/ubiquitous-language-problems/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-17T12:38:16+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/06/17/ubiquitous-language-problems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Language is tricky. Take the this post, for instance. It&rsquo;s not about language
problems that are ubiquitous. It&rsquo;s about problems related to <em>Ubiquitous
Language</em> &mdash; whether the problems themselves are ubiquitous or not.</p>

<p>Ubiquitous Language is a term from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain-driven_design">Domain-Driven Design</a> software
development practice. It refers to a set of well-defined project terms shared
by all participants: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subject-matter_expert">Domain experts</a>, business analysts, developers,
users. The term was coined by Eric Evans in his <a href="http://dddcommunity.org/book/evans_2003/">DDD book</a>. I haven&rsquo;t
actually read it, but the idea seems sensible: If developers live and breathe
the domain by speaking its language, their output is more likely to fit the
business needs, and developers and domain experts are more likely to understand
one another.</p>

<p>As a business analyst and developer, your task is to adopt the language of the
domain experts, <em>not</em> the other way around. But that doesn&rsquo;t mean that the
domain experts are home free. Changes are probably required to turn their
jargon into a well-defined set of terms that will ensure precise and
unambiguous communication in the project and to the users. Here are some of the
challenges I&rsquo;ve encountered in this process.</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Two.Words..One.Concept"></a>
<h2>Two Words, One Concept</h2>

<p>One problem is that people may use different words for the same concept. It is
preferable to use one word per concept, because it will simplify design
discussions and remove confusion arising from the possibility that the words
<em>could</em> have different meanings. The code and the user interface will also be
much easier to understand for developers and users, respectively, if a concept
always has the same name.</p>

<p>As an example, different project participants use the terms User and Employee.
If the business or system has only employees as users, either word is fine.
Picking one over the other risks having a winner and a loser in the process.
Sometimes finding a third term can be a good move, politically or socially.
Perhaps the term Account can cover the concept and satisfy both parties.</p>

<p>Other times, it turns out that the terms actually have different meanings.
Maybe not all users are employees or not all employees are users. In this case,
both terms can stay in the vocabulary, and their exact relationship will have
to be uncovered.</p>

<a name="One.Word..Two.Concepts"></a>
<h2>One Word, Two Concepts</h2>

<p>Another problem is that the same word may be used for different concepts.
Sometimes by different people, sometimes even by the same people. Take the term
Account from the previous section. There, it was taken to mean a user account.
But Account could also mean a bank account, or a even a client (one managed by
an account manager).</p>

<p>If the main business domain (such as banking, accounting, customer relationship
management) already has a specific interpretation of the term, the other
meanings should probably find other names (such as Client, User Account, or
Bank Account). I prefer avoiding partially overlapping terms, so if Account is
already taken, User is better than User Account &mdash; unless User also has
a meaning distinct from User Account.</p>

<a name="Types.and.Instances"></a>
<h2>Types and Instances</h2>

<p>A specific version of the One Word, Two Concepts problem is when the same word
is used about both instances and types. Perhaps the word Service is used about
a service provided to a customer on a specific date and time (such as
a haircut), but also about the type of service the company provides (such as
a haircut). Or Product can mean both a product from the product catalog and
a product in the context of a specific Order.</p>

<p>For these examples, possible concept names could be Service and Service Type as
well as Product and Order Product. It&rsquo;s a first step, but as easy as it is to
add a prefix or suffix, as easy it drop it again in conversation. A better
option is to choose names that don&rsquo;t have anything in common. An Order Product
could be an Order Line (which is actually a well-known concept). A Service
could be an Appointment, while the term Service refers to the type. Or perhaps
Service stays in the appointment interpretation, and Service Type could be
named Function.</p>

<a name="Software.Development.as.Domain"></a>
<h2>Software Development as Domain</h2>

<p>Service and Function are not to be confused with what a software developer
might understand by these terms. Software is a business domain on its own
right, but unless the <em>project&rsquo;s</em> domain is software, developers should let the
business domain take precedence.</p>

<p>It might be necessary for developers to discuss technical design involving
software terms that clash with the domain model (such as Class, Strategy,
Factory, Visitor). It doesn&rsquo;t make sense to rename well-known concepts from the
software domain, but unless the domain experts need to know about them, they
shouldn&rsquo;t be part of the domain model, and so they should only be used
internally between technical designers and developers.</p>

<p>But even inside the software domain, I have observed the One Word, Two Concepts
problem at work. The term Entity, itself used in DDD, can refer to both a type
and an instance. Peter Chen, who introduced the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entity%E2%80%93relationship_model">Entity-Relationship Model</a>, used the term Entity to mean an instance of
some <em>Entity Type</em>. What I mentioned earlier about dropping suffixes also
applies here, and many people, myself included, use Entity in the type meaning.
Ideally, the instance meaning is then referred to by a different word, such as
Object.</p>

<a name="Microsoft.Dynamics.CRM"></a>
<h2>Microsoft Dynamics CRM</h2>

<p>The Microsoft Dynamics Customer Relationship Management (CRM) software
interests me in two ways in relation to DDD and ubiquitous language.
Superficially, Microsoft CRM uses the terms Entity and Record in the above
mentioned type and instance meanings, respectively. But then in the Danish
translation of the software, they use the Danish word <em>objekt</em> &mdash; not
<em>entitet</em> &mdash; as the translation of Entity. (In fact my colleague recently
found out the whole system is translated by Bing!)</p>

<p>Second, Microsoft CRM is somewhat anti-DDD in the sense that the built-in
customer relationship management domain model can conflict with that of the
user organization. It&rsquo;s possible to adapt the built-in data model with new
entities, attributes, and relationships, and by renaming existing items. But
the renaming only applies to the user interface, not the code and database.
This forces developers to think in terms of the built-in model and to translate
back and forth between that and the organization&rsquo;s domain, which is exactly the
thing ubiquitous language tells you to avoid.</p>

<a name="Multiple.Contexts"></a>
<h2>Multiple Contexts</h2>

<p>In this post I have been touching on the matching of words and concepts, both
in general and in software development. In this, I have been simplifying by
focusing on building a single ubiquitous language and domain model for
a project. Part of DDD is acknowledging that a project can be too large for
a single unified model, and instead of trying to make such a model, you should
allow for multiple <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/BoundedContext.html">bounded contexts</a> and instead make sure to define
their boundaries and relationships. But inside each single context, make sure
to use one word per concept.</p>

<p>The more I think about it, the more I see that software development is itself
far too large to be a single context. Words such as <em>prototype</em> or
<em>implementation</em> have multiple meanings. A prototype can be a
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_prototyping">software product</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Function_prototype">function declaration</a>, or
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prototype_pattern">cloneable object</a>. Programmers will understand <em>implementation</em> as the
process of and result of turning the human readable design description into
executable computer code. But implementation can also mean taking that same
executable computer code &mdash; the software product &mdash; and embedding it
successfully in the organization that is going to use it.</p>

<p>So two things are important in achieving clear communication. First, make each
context internally sound, and second, be aware of the existence of multiple
contexts, especially when you are speaking with someone who normally thinks and
works in another context from you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flying in the Front Row]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/05/10/flying-in-the-front-row/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-10T15:50:10+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/05/10/flying-in-the-front-row</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I regularly fly to Copenhagen for work, and once in a while I&rsquo;m assigned
a front row seat &mdash; an ostensible upgrade. This must happen randomly as I have
not requested or paid for it. But after experiencing it few times, I&rsquo;d be
inclined to pay to <em>not</em> sit there again.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/wing_sunset.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>One of the joys of business trips is traveling light. For a one or two day
trip, I can fit all I need in my briefcase, and there&rsquo;s no need to queue early
to be sure to get a space for my carry-on suitcase in the overhead bins. (I
entirely avoid checking bags when I can.)</p>

<p>After boarding I work until it&rsquo;s time to take off, and then I slide my laptop
in my briefcase and the briefcase under the seat in front of me. Once we&rsquo;re in
the air, I slide it back out and get some more work done, without asking my
fellow passengers to get up while I get my bag. Easy peasy.</p>

<a name="Bags.Must.Be.Stowed"></a>
<h2>Bags Must Be Stowed</h2>

<p>The first problem of the front row stems from the rule that bags must be stowed
in the overhead bins during takeoff and landing.</p>

<p>If I board early, I can put my bag in the overhead bin and sit down without
access to my stuff while everyone else is boarding, with the added bonus that
if I sit in the 1C aisle seat, every third backpack-wearing passenger will bump
their backpack into me as they pass.</p>

<p>If I board late, I get to the second problem: There&rsquo;s very little overhead
space for the first row passengers because a lot of the bin space is reserved
for kit needed by the cabin crew. The little space gets filled quickly and I&rsquo;ll
have to go further down the rows until I find an empty slot. This is not
a problem at first, but after landing, once the disembarkation stampede begins,
getting from row 1 to 4 to get my bag while a hundred people are impatiently
going the opposite direction is not great.</p>

<p>I think one of the supposed advantages of the front row is to be one of the
first people to get off the plane. But that&rsquo;s not likely to happen if you have
baggage. Row 2 and 3 are better. Therefore I was happy when I was recently
assigned seat 2E. That lasted until I got on the plane and it turned out that,
on the right side (D-E-F), row 2 <em>was</em> the front row on that plane &mdash; no row
1.</p>

<a name="Longer.Flights"></a>
<h2>Longer Flights</h2>

<p>The above is just my annoyances with a process I&rsquo;d like to run smoothly as part
of a routine. On the short flight from Aalborg to Copenhagen, more time is
spent boarding, preparing, taxiing, and disembarking, than the actual 30
minutes in the air. On rarer, longer trips the efficiency of getting on and off
the plane seems less important, and the leg room perhaps more important.</p>

<p>Leg room depends on how the airline configures the seats. I often fly with
<em>Norwegian</em> and despite their label as a low-cost airline, they have enough
room in standard economy to fit my long legs &mdash; perhaps because they&rsquo;re
Scandinavian. Either way, the value of a front row seat in this regard will
depend on your legs compared with the leg room of your chosen airline.</p>

<p>But the extra room can be useful to others as well. What I&rsquo;ve found is that the
(not <em>that</em> large, by the way) space in front of the front row seats is where
the front toilet queue goes to stand every time the crew needs to pass with
a trolley.</p>

<p>All this is by the way as it relates to short-haul single-aisle aircraft with
no business class seats &mdash; only &ldquo;economy with extra legroom&rdquo;. These extra
legroom seats are exactly the ones I&rsquo;d like to avoid. The emergency exit rows
have some of the same problems as the front row, but with more overhead bin
space and less toilet queue. But I&rsquo;d take a standard economy seat over that as
well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Weird Keyboard]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/04/14/my-weird-keyboard/"/>
    <updated>2018-04-14T16:57:10+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/04/14/my-weird-keyboard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I use a weird computer keyboard: The <a href="https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/shop/advantage2/">Kinesis Advantage</a>.
It&rsquo;s a concave, columnar, split, tented, mechanical keyboard with thumb keys.
It&rsquo;s very comfortable and much better than anything Logitech or Microsoft have
ever labeled ergonomic.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/kinesis_advantage2.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Ergonomic.Features"></a>
<h2>Ergonomic Features</h2>

<p><strong>Columnar</strong> means that the keys are laid out in straight columns, so you don&rsquo;t
have to bend your fingers sideways as you curl and extend them &mdash; unlike on
a standard, staggered keyboard, where especially the left hand fingers need to
move unnaturally. The <strong>split</strong> also helps avoiding sideways bends for the
wrists. For more details, see the illustration of the <a href="https://www.trulyergonomic.com/store/unique-symmetric-columnar-key-arrangement--truly-ergonomic-mechanical-keyboard--orthogonal-matrix-non-staggered">Truly Ergonomic
keyboard</a> (which I haven&rsquo;t tried (yet)).</p>

<p><strong>Tented</strong> means that the thumb side of each hand sits higher than the pinky
side. This gives the wrists a more natural rotation. The Advantage only tilts
20 degrees &mdash; other keyboards such as the
<a href="https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/shop/freestyle2-for-pc-us/">Kinesis Freestyle</a> and the <a href="http://safetype.com">SafeType</a> can tent
(up to) 90 degrees (while <a href="https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/frreestyle2-ascent-90-1.jpg">looking</a> even less
conventional than the Advantage).</p>

<p>The <strong>thumb key</strong> clusters make more keys reachable without moving the hand
away from its home position, and it offloads Backspace and Enter from the
overworked right pinky and onto the stronger thumbs.</p>

<p>The <strong>mechanical</strong> keyswitches (Cherry MX brown or red) register the keypress
when the key is halfway depressed (2 out of 4 millimeters). This is opposed to
standard rubber dome keyboards that require you to bottom out &mdash; fully depress
the key until the finger is jolted to a stop.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/kinesis_advantage2_side.jpg"></p>

<p>The best feature of the Advantage is the <strong>concave</strong> keywells: The scooped-out
parts of the keyboard where the alphanumeric keys reside. They serve several
purposes:</p>

<ul>
<li>As you curl and extend your fingers, the keys remain at the same distance
from your fingertips, so you don&rsquo;t need to stretch your fingers much to
reach. This also makes it easy to access all five (!) rows of keys.</li>
<li>The same happens when you move your index finger to the side (like T, G, B),
reducing sideways-twisting finger motions.</li>
<li>The depths of the columns are matched with the corresponding fingers, so they
all rest naturally in the home position.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Switching"></a>
<h2>Switching</h2>

<p>I got my first Kinesis Advantage in 2011. As I recall, it only took a few days
to adapt to this weird keyboard. The best part is that I can still switch
effortlessly between the Advantage and standard, flat, staggered keyboards. Not
that I particularly enjoy it, but I can do it, which is very practical for
traveling. The Advantage is actually narrower than a standard 104/105-key
keyboard, but it&rsquo;s bigger in the two other dimensions and therefore not easy to
transport.</p>

<p>However, the physical shape of my keyboard is not the only weird thing about my
typing. The <em>logical</em> layout I use &mdash; <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2015/02/27/4-years-with-colemak/">Colemak</a> &mdash; is weird too.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/kinesis_advantage_custom_keycaps_right.jpg"></p>

<p>Switching logical layout is much harder for me than switching physical layout.
Even though the Advantage is firmware remappable, I set my logical layout in
the computer OS, so I will keep the logical layout for all keyboards, including
the laptop keyboard.</p>

<p>Some people retain their QWERTY touch typing skills while learning an
alternative layout by associating logical layout with physical keyboard, e.g.,
typing Colemak on the Advantage and QWERTY on standard keyboards. And I did
actually get the Advantage the same year I switched to Colemak, but I much
prefer typing Colemak on my laptop while traveling over maintaining my QWERTY
skills.</p>

<a name="Legends"></a>
<h2>Legends</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not really necessary have Colemak legends on the keys, but I did get a set
of custom keycaps made by <a href="http://www.wasdkeyboards.com/">WASD keyboards</a> for one of my two Advantages
&mdash; complete with my Danish variation of Colemak &mdash; as shown in the images
above and below. It&rsquo;s mostly for show, because the legends are not necessary
for touch typing, and the Advantage is not so good anyway for one-handed use
where the legends might be relevant.</p>

<p>In fact, hunt-and-peck typing is for some reason easier for me with QWERTY
legends, even while I type Colemak. My eyes are more used to the common QWERTY
layout, I guess. I just know that pressing the QWERTY &rsquo;T&#8217; key produces a &lsquo;G&rsquo; in
Colemak. If I look down and the key shows a &lsquo;G&rsquo;, my eyes get confused, even
though my fingers knows exactly where to press to get the &lsquo;G&rsquo; while touch
typing.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/kinesis_advantage_custom_keycaps_left.jpg"></p>

<a name="Downsides"></a>
<h2>Downsides</h2>

<p>The Advantage is not great for everything. Split keyboards are not good for the
occational one-handed use (e.g., while holding a drink, phone, piece of paper).</p>

<p>The Advantage is not the best for gaming either. The arrow keys are spread on
both sides of the split which is fine for two-handed office and programming
use, but not ideal for gaming. The key positions are matched to finger lengths,
so the WASD keys will not work well with the normal WASD-fingers. ESDF should
be perfect, though.</p>

<p>For a long time, the typical complaint of the Advantage was the low quality of
the rubber F-keys. In 2016, the Advantage2 was launched, with Cherry ML
switches instead of rubber dome F-keys, and more programming options. This is
the product I link to in the top of the post because the product page for the
old version seems to be gone. I haven&rsquo;t tried it, but I can only imagine it&rsquo;s
an improvement.</p>

<p>Another problem partially solved by time is the built-in combined USB hub and
PS/2-to-USB converter. It &mdash; and the whole keyboard with it &mdash; didn&rsquo;t work
with Windows 7. Kinesis did sell a cable conversion kit to work around this,
but I went DIY and installed a PS/2-to-USB adapter myself, bypassing the
problematic USB hub, on my &ldquo;work&rdquo; board.</p>

<p>My &ldquo;home&rdquo; board always worked fine with Linux (and Windows 10), but it&rsquo;s also
not recognized by the BIOS of my desktop computer&rsquo;s motherboard. A smaller
problem but I&rsquo;m considering giving this board a USB hubectomy as well. The
Advantage2 has supposedly also solved this problem.</p>

<p>There are a few problems with the Advantage, but they are minor compared to the
Advantage (heh) of using an extremely comfortable keyboard for my 10+ daily
hours of computer usage.</p>

<a name="Key.Remapping"></a>
<h2>Key Remapping</h2>

<p>My remaining complaints were solved with easy firmware remapping, which is in
fact just a testament to the Advantage&rsquo;s flexibility:</p>

<ul>
<li>I swapped Space and Backspace because I have for some reason always used my
left hand&rsquo;s thumb for Space.</li>
<li>I use the Alt+Tab shortcut all the time, so I moved the Alt key closer to my
thumb in the left thumb cluster.</li>
<li>I made the key above Tab work as an Escape key.</li>
<li>I made the key below Tab work as a Control key because that&rsquo;s how control
freaks control.</li>
<li>I put Down to the left of Up because that&rsquo;s how Vim users roll.</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Update 2018-11-06: Minor clarifications.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Roland Boutique Needs]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/02/25/what-roland-boutique-needs/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-25T16:46:09+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/02/25/what-roland-boutique-needs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Roland Boutique is a series of small form factor electronic music instruments.
The line debuted in 2015 with recreations of three iconic Roland 1980s synths.
I got the JP-08 which I wrote about <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/06/25/roland-jp-08-review/">here</a>. Since then I&rsquo;ve been
watching the series grow with interest.</p>

<p>By now, the <a href="https://www.roland.com/us/promos/roland_boutique/">Boutique line</a> includes nine products recreating
Roland&rsquo;s back catalog: Five subtractive synths (JP-08, JU-06, JX-03, TB-03,
SH-01A), the VP-03 vocoder, the TR-08 and TR-09 drum machines, and finally the
D-05 &ldquo;linear synthesizer&rdquo; mixing sampling and synthesis.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/boutique_hero.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In 2017, Roland ventured outside their own history. Teaming up with Studio
Electronics, they released the Minimoog-inspired analog monosynth SE-02. Having
started down this path, they might make an FM (frequency modulation) synth.
Missing from the lineup is also perhaps a sampler/sample player/sample mangler?</p>

<p>That would at least match miniatures produced by other manufacturers in the
last few years. The very small and affordable Korg Volca series has the
straightforwardly named Beats, Bass, Keys, Sample, and FM. The first four
predated the original Boutique trio by 1-2 years, while the FM was released in
2016.</p>

<p>Swedish manufacturer Elektron also recently went small with the less toylike
&mdash; and less affordable &mdash; Digitakt sampler and Digitone FM-synth, with the
latter being announced just one month ago.</p>

<p>The 2015 Yamaha Reface series also has CS, DX, YC, and CP, doing synth, FM,
electric organ, and electric piano, respectively. And this leads me toward what
I would most like to see in the Roland Boutique series.</p>

<a name="Give.Me.a.Piano."></a>
<h2>Give Me a Piano!</h2>

<p>When you think of a digital piano, you are more likely to think of 88 weighted
keys than 25 non-weighted &ldquo;synth action&rdquo; minikeys. But one of the advantages of
the Boutiques is that they can both slot into the K-25m keyboard module and
perform as a sound module/desktop synth.</p>

<p>I would love to have a Roland Boutique piano with high-quality, natural,
acoustic piano sounds as well as high-quality electric pianos, organs, strings,
etc. I guess the model number would be in the form of FP-0x or RD-0x. I would
use such a Boutique piano module both as a sound module plugged into a MIDI
keyboard, and in the sofa as a plaything and/or compositional tool with the
K-25m keyboard attached.</p>

<p>The D-05 unfortunately does not fill this role. When the D-50 was launched in
1987 it certainly came closer than any analog synth to sounding like acoustic
instruments, but that doesn&rsquo;t mean it could actually pass for one. I went to my
local music store to try out the D-05, and while it does have a dozen patches
with &ldquo;piano&rdquo; in their name, none of them sound like an acoustic piano. It can
do electric pianos and organs, but overall I think the D-50/D-05 has a certain
80s/90s &ldquo;lo-fi&rdquo; sound. It excels at some things, but not acoustic piano.</p>

<a name="The.Panel"></a>
<h2>The Panel</h2>

<p>Some of the Boutiques have too many buttons crammed into the limited space on
the panel. This includes the <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/06/25/roland-jp-08-review/">JP-08</a>, and judging from pictures, also
the TR-08, TR-09 and SE-02. Some have a more reasonable amount, such as the
JU-06, SH-01A, and VP-03. The D-05 doesn&rsquo;t have too many buttons per se, but it
faithfully recreates the dreary menu diving experience of the &ldquo;digital age&rdquo; (to
achieve more hands-on programming of the D-50/D-550/D-05, you need the enormous
PG-1000 programmer). But, digital pianos typically do not have a lot of
buttons. So what do I want on the Boutique piano panel?</p>

<p>I can think of a lot!</p>

<ul>
<li>Better speaker(s), perhaps even front facing</li>
<li>Dedicated octave up/down buttons</li>
<li>A good pitch/modulation stick (yes, electric organs can <a href="http://www.organforum.com/forums/showthread.php?22171-Pitch-bending-on-a-Hammond-A-mystery">pitch bend</a>)</li>
<li>Effects! Reverb, Leslie, Overdrive, Chorus, you name it.</li>
<li>Loop machine</li>
<li>Tape recorder</li>
<li>Sequencer</li>
<li>Arpeggiator</li>
<li>Chord memory</li>
<li>Scale/chord library (like a <a href="https://www.islainstruments.com/product/kordbot/">KordBot</a>?)</li>
</ul>


<p>Finally, such a module shouldn&rsquo;t be expensive. Unless it would have several of
the above features, it should be closer to 150 €/$ than to 400 €/$. It&rsquo;s
a ripoff that the K-25m keyboard is already 100 €/$.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AoC 2017 Day 8: Fell Into a Python Pitfall]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/12/10/aoc-2017-day-8-fell-into-a-python-pitfall/"/>
    <updated>2017-12-10T20:43:47+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2017/12/10/aoc-2017-day-8-fell-into-a-python-pitfall</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been using and enjoying <a href="https://www.python.org/">Python</a> since 2009, but while doing
<a href="http://adventofcode.com">Advent of Code</a> again this year, I stumbled upon a Python feature that
led to a subtle bug. Advent of Code spoiler ahead.</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="The.Puzzle"></a>
<h2>The Puzzle</h2>

<p>In AoC 2017 you travel inside Santa&rsquo;s computer, fixing and computing things so
the Naughty or Nice List can be printed on time for Santa to deliver the
presents on time.</p>

<p>The puzzle for <a href="http://adventofcode.com/2017/day/8">Day 8</a> gives you a textual input such as</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='Pascal'><span class='line'><span class="n">b</span> <span class="nb">inc</span> <span class="mi">5</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">a</span> <span class="nb">inc</span> <span class="mi">1</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">b</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="mi">5</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">c</span> <span class="nb">dec</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">10</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">&gt;=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">c</span> <span class="nb">inc</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">20</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">c</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="mi">10</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>and asks you to find the largest value in any register after executing the
given instructions (on some imagined CPU). The registers (which are <code>a</code>, <code>b</code>,
and <code>c</code> in the above), are all initialized to zero. The largest value in the
example is 1, which is in the <code>a</code> register at the end.</p>

<p>The real puzzle input is much larger and requires an automated solution. My
approach was to build a register valuation dictionary, update it according to
the instructions, and then find the largest value.</p>

<a name="My.Solution"></a>
<h2>My Solution</h2>

<p>I wrote this code (refactored):</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='Python'><span class='line'><span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">operator</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">lt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">gt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">le</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ge</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">eq</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ne</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">day8</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">input</span><span class="p">):</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">instructions</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="n">line</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">split</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">line</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nb">input</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">splitlines</span><span class="p">()]</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">register_names</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nb">set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">instruction</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">instruction</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">instructions</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">registers</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="n">register_name</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="mi">0</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">register_name</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">register_names</span><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">mod_reg</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">mod_op</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">mod_amt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">_</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">cond_reg</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">cond_op</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">cond_const</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">instructions</span><span class="p">:</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">eval_cond</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">registers</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">cond_reg</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="n">cond_op</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">cond_const</span><span class="p">):</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="n">registers</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">mod_reg</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">mod_op</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="s">&#39;inc&#39;</span> <span class="k">else</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nb">int</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">mod_amt</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nb">max</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">registers</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">values</span><span class="p">())</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">eval_cond</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">cond_op</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">b</span><span class="p">):</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="s">&#39;&lt;&#39;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">lt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&#39;&gt;&#39;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">gt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&#39;&lt;=&#39;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">le</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&#39;&gt;=&#39;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">ge</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&#39;==&#39;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">eq</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&#39;!=&#39;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">ne</span><span class="p">}[</span><span class="n">cond_op</span><span class="p">](</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">b</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>I ran it on the test input, and the test passed. Good! Then I ran it on the
main puzzle input, got a nice looking number, and submitted my result.</p>

<p>Incorrect&hellip; Huh.</p>

<p>Can you spot the mistake?</p>

<p>I later fixed it in line 10, and it relates to types.</p>

<a name="Strong.and.Weak.Typing"></a>
<h2>Strong and Weak Typing</h2>

<p>One of the things I like about Python compared with other dynamically typed
languages is that Python is also strongly typed.</p>

<p>JavaScript &mdash; which is dynamically and weakly typed &mdash; implicitly converts
types, such as from number to string:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='Python'><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="s">&#39;2&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s">&#39;22&#39;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Python doesn&rsquo;t &mdash; it forces you to choose:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='Python'><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="s">&#39;2&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">Traceback</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">most</span> <span class="n">recent</span> <span class="n">call</span> <span class="n">last</span><span class="p">):</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">File</span> <span class="s">&quot;&lt;stdin&gt;&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">line</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">module</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="ne">TypeError</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">unsupported</span> <span class="n">operand</span> <span class="nb">type</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">s</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="o">+</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s">&#39;int&#39;</span> <span class="ow">and</span> <span class="s">&#39;str&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nb">int</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&#39;2&#39;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">4</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="nb">str</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="s">&#39;2&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s">&#39;22&#39;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>But ok, let&rsquo;s try mixed type comparison in JavaScript:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='Python'><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">3</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="s">&#39;5&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">true</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">30</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="s">&#39;5&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">false</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And Python:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='Python'><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="mi">3</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="s">&#39;5&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="bp">True</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="mi">30</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="s">&#39;5&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="bp">True</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>(!)</p>

<p>In fact, any integer compares less than any string in CPython 2.</p>

<p>This was the reason for my bug &mdash; I kept comparing integer register values to
unparsed text strings:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='Python'><span class='line'>    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">eval_cond</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">registers</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">cond_reg</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="n">cond_op</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">cond_const</span><span class="p">):</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>After adding the integer parsing, it worked as expected:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='Python'><span class='line'>    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">eval_cond</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">registers</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">cond_reg</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="n">cond_op</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nb">int</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">cond_const</span><span class="p">)):</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<a name="Why.Does.It.Work.Like.This."></a>
<h2>Why Does It Work Like This?</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not that I had expected Python to suddenly do implicit type conversion for
comparison &mdash; I had just forgot the call to <code>int</code> &mdash; even though I had
remembered it while parsing the modification amount <code>mod_amt</code>.</p>

<p>What I would have hoped for was a loud error rather than a subtle bug. It turns
out there is both a reason for the subtle behavior in Python 2 and the option
to get a loud error &mdash; by using Python 3.</p>

<p>From the <a href="https://docs.python.org/2/library/stdtypes.html#comparisons">Python 2 docs</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Objects of different types [&hellip;] are ordered consistently but arbitrarily (so
that sorting a heterogeneous array yields a consistent result).</p></blockquote>

<p>From the <a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/stdtypes.html#comparisons">Python 3 docs</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>The &lt;, &lt;=, > and >= operators will raise a TypeError exception [&hellip;] when the
objects are of different types that cannot be compared [&hellip;].</p></blockquote>

<a name="Mixed-Type.Operators.Can.Be.Good"></a>
<h2>Mixed-Type Operators Can Be Good</h2>

<p>A little <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/2384139">history lesson</a> on stackoverflow.com explains why
heterogeneous lists are not cool anymore, and I&rsquo;m happy about the change in
comparison from Python 2 to 3.</p>

<p>But that does not mean that different types should never be combined with
operators.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take another look at JavaScript:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='Python'><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="s">&#39;3&#39;</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="mi">4</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">12</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And Python:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='Python'><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="s">&#39;3&#39;</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="mi">4</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s">&#39;3333&#39;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If you were expecting this to evaluate to 12 &mdash; either because you came from
a weakly typed language, or because you simply forgot to parse the string as an
integer &mdash; you might also be confused. But I really like this Python behavior.</p>

<p>&ldquo;String multiplication&rdquo;, or rather <em>sequence replication</em>, is much more useful
than heterogeneous list sorting &mdash; so useful that it is acceptable for it to
risk being confusing to newcomers.</p>

<p>And as opposed to string/integer comparison, it&rsquo;s also less likely to lead to
subtle bugs. While the string/integer comparison returned a boolean just like
integer/integer comparison, string/integer multiplication returns a string, and
not the integer a novice might be expecting.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Pixel 2 - First Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/11/19/google-pixel-2-first-impressions/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-19T15:58:03+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2017/11/19/google-pixel-2-first-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just bought a new smartphone. After three HTC models (Desire Z, One X, One
M8) I decided to go for the pure Android experience with a Google Pixel 2 (I
went with the Clearly White, non-XL version). Here are my thoughts after two
weeks.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/pixel2.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The first thing I noticed was the <strong>speed</strong>. Booting it up for the first time
took what I remember as mere seconds. Coming from a 3.5 year old smartphone,
this was a big improvement. Not so relevant on a daily basis, but a good first
impression. But the Pixel 2 also feels very snappy in use, especially compared
with my old smartphone burdened by the newest, hungriest apps.</p>

<p>The second great thing I noticed is the <strong>screen</strong>. It looks fine, but what I&rsquo;m
really happy about is its ability to reduce the brightness to a fairly low
level so I don&rsquo;t get blinded in low light conditions. I guess older OLED
smartphones might have been able to do the same, but it&rsquo;s certainly the first
smartphone I have owned where I have been satisfied with the low brightness
level. The automatic brightness adjustment is also excellent. On top of that,
the Night Light feature is great. As a <a href="http://jonls.dk/redshift/">Redshift</a> (similar to
<a href="https://justgetflux.com/">f.lux</a>) user I was happy to see it built in to the OS.</p>

<p>Third, the <strong>battery</strong> life is good. As a test, I skipped charging one night,
and just used it regularly two days in a row. When I went to bed the second
night, it still had 19% left. And that&rsquo;s even with two battery-eating always-on
features enabled: Ambient display (showing date, time, and notification icons)
and Now Playing (which does <em>offline</em> analysis of ambient sound to identify
playing songs).</p>

<a name="The.Stuff.People.Talk.About"></a>
<h2>The Stuff People Talk About</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/pixel2front.jpg" width="370"></p>

<p>On-device song identification is pretty cool. Another hypey feature is the
&ldquo;Active Edge&rdquo; which let&rsquo;s you <strong>squeeze</strong> the sides of the phone to activate
Google Assistant. It&rsquo;s fun to play with, but not very useful in my opinion.
I have to shift the phone in my hand to squeeze the right area, and half of the
time, the &ldquo;meat&rdquo; of the base of my thumb folds up and taps something unwanted
on the screen. So it&rsquo;s better to just launch Assistant the regular way: by long
pressing the home button.</p>

<p>In other news, the <strong>bezels</strong> have taken flak for being too large for 2017. And
I guess they are. On the plus side, I can comfortably reach both top and bottom
of the screen with my thumb, and they have room for front-facing stereo
speakers.</p>

<p>They didn&rsquo;t leave room for a <strong>headphone jack</strong>, though. The phone&rsquo;s packaging
included a (somewhat bulky) converter but no wired USB C headphones &mdash; to get
more people to look at the <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=Pixel+Buds">Pixel Buds</a>, I guess.</p>

<p>Finally, the Pixel 2&rsquo;s <strong>camera</strong> is supposedly really, really good. I don&rsquo;t
disagree so far, but I&rsquo;ll know more when I get around to trying it somewhere
more picturesque than my desk.</p>

<a name="Small.Annoyances"></a>
<h2>Small Annoyances</h2>

<p>Overall, I&rsquo;m fairly satisfied with the Pixel 2. But there are a few small
annoyances:</p>

<ul>
<li>No support for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miracast">Miracast</a> - only Chromecast</li>
<li>The Pixel 2 is not officially for sale in Denmark, which means that the
<a href="https://store.google.com/product/pixel_2">Google Store</a> webpage will not even acknowledge that the Pixel 2 or
its accessories exist, if you access it from Denmark without tricks</li>
<li>The ambient display, which is white text on a black background, <em>strobes</em>,
which you can see when you move the phone around</li>
<li>Dust and debris gets stuck in the speaker grills
<span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/android8_notification_collapse.png' width='' height='' alt='Areas for expanding/collapsing notifications'><span class='caption-text'>Areas for expanding/collapsing notifications</span></span></li>
<li>The device/screen vibrates when the speakers are playing, which can be felt
in the 120&ndash;700 Hz range</li>
<li>The power button and volume rocker require too much pressure to press</li>
<li>Most Android 8 notifications can be expanded/collapsed, to which a large
part of their surface is reserved. This means that unlike older Android
notifications, I kinda have to aim when I tap them.</li>
<li>Going for pure Android is not as cool as I had imagined, and the default
launcher and dialler are disappointing</li>
<li>Since the bezels are there anyway, a fingerprint reader on the front would be
nice, for those times I want to use the phone flat on the table</li>
</ul>


<p>Come to think of it, many of these feel like a step down from my HTC One M8.
But they&rsquo;re not a big problem compared to the improvements in speed, screen
blackness, camera, and battery, all in a thinner, lighter body.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll get to see over the coming months and years if the &ldquo;full Google
experience&rdquo; is worth the price. At least I should be getting updates quickly
for <a href="https://www.androidauthority.com/google-pixel-2-xl-update-804779/">three years</a>, which is better than many OEMs. I just hope the
Pixel 2 will stay snappy as the updates come.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Roland JP-08 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/06/25/roland-jp-08-review/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-25T17:06:23+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2017/06/25/roland-jp-08-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the early 1980s Roland produced a number of synthesizers that aged into
classics. The flagship Jupiter-8 is perhaps the most famous, used by electronic
artists such as Jean Michel Jarre, Depeche Mode, and Moby, as well as pop
artists like Michael Jackson, Madonna, and Abba.</p>

<p>Today, a used Jupiter-8 in good condition can cost more than a new top end
modern synthesizer, which is to say a lot. Luckily, in late 2015 Roland
released miniature versions of these classics, at relatively affordable prices.
Jupiter-8 became JP-08, and I got to own a little piece of music history.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/boutiques.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Three originals (Juno-106, Jupiter-8, JX-3P) above the three new 'Boutique' versions (JU-06, JP-08, JX-03)'><span class='caption-text'>Three originals (Juno-106, Jupiter-8, JX-3P) above the three new &lsquo;Boutique&rsquo; versions (JU-06, JP-08, JX-03)</span></span></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a bit late for a review, one and a half year after the release, but on the
other hand, the Jupiter-8 came out before I was born, so in comparison, the new
version is still very recent!</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Sound.in.a.Box"></a>
<h2>Sound in a Box</h2>

<p>One might ask why you need a box like this when you can generate the same
sounds in your computer. But the new Roland releases are in fact just software
in boxes &mdash; digital emulations of the original electronics. The point is that
a box with the right buttons, knobs, and sliders makes the experience of sound
exploration tactile and immediate.</p>

<p>Plus, in this age of multi purpose devices, there is just something fascinating
about a device that does just one thing, does it well, and doesn&rsquo;t let you
connect to Facebook.</p>

<div class="video-container">
<iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/C1zdcqoe8qg?feature=player_detailpage" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<a name="A.Small.Box"></a>
<h2>A Small Box</h2>

<p>Compared with the Jupiter-8, the JP-08 is tiny. It has the footprint of an A4
sheet of paper (somewhere between letter and legal for you North Americans),
and that&rsquo;s <em>with</em> the optional mini-keyboard attached. Since it can also be
powered from batteries, that means it&rsquo;s <em>portable</em>. You can bring it on trips,
to the park, or just the sofa. (Or bring it to bed, according to
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/junkiexlofficial">JunkieXL</a>!)</p>

<p>As part of the portability, the unit even has a built-in speaker so you can
play it without attaching a sound system or headphones. As practical as this
is, the speaker has no bass and a tendency to make the chassis rattle and
resonate. So I recommend skipping it altogether because that will sound much
better and make you appreciate the unit more.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/jp-08.jpg"></p>

<a name="Too.Small.a.Box"></a>
<h2>Too Small a Box</h2>

<p>The portable coolness however comes at a cost. To fit all of the controls of
the Jupiter-8 into such a small areal, they have been arranged in two rows.
Thus the sliders only have a throw of 1 cm, which means they require delicate
hand movements. This detracts from the overall hand-on experience, even though
they are usable with patience. The worst part is that it&rsquo;s very hard to sweep
the filter or pulse width smoothly.</p>

<p>However diminutive they are, controls dedicated to exactly one sound parameter
provide much of the immediacy of the overall experience. Unfortunately, the
auxiliary controls are tucked away under button combinations &mdash; a few
labelled, most not.</p>

<ul>
<li>The solo/unison/poly mode buttons have moved from dedicated buttons to
(labelled) combinations. This is acceptable because this is not something
you&rsquo;re likely to need to switch quickly.</li>
<li>The portamento settings also glided (pun intended) into a combination, with
the glide time set by sliding the modulation ribbon with the &lsquo;dual&rsquo; button
held down. This is a bit sad, since I could imaging tweaking the glide time
while playing.</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s worse for features native to the JP-08 such as delay effect parameters,
transpose, pitch bend range, MIDI channel, and especially keyboard octave
selection which is not easily done while playing the mini keyboard.</li>
<li>Also, the pitch bend and modulation features have devolved: The VCO/VCF
destination sliders and selectors have disappeared, and the crude ribbon
makes it difficult to do smooth or precise pitch bends.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Better.With.a.MIDI.Controller"></a>
<h2>Better With a MIDI Controller</h2>

<p>Many of the above problems can be solved by a separate MIDI controller:</p>

<ul>
<li>More octaves can be played directly, or at least octaves can be selected more
easily</li>
<li>Bigger knobs and sliders can be used to obtain smoother sweeps and precise
parameter input</li>
<li>The portamento glide time can be adjusted with a single knob or slider</li>
<li>The Jupiter-8 hold (sustain) feature, missing from the JP-08, can be mapped
to a button</li>
<li>The Jupiter-8 arpeggiator, also sadly missing from the JP-08, can be restored
with an arpeggiating controller such as the Arturia KeyStep</li>
</ul>


<p>Using a separate controller defeats the portability, but seen from the bright
side it just means you can switch between portability and better control.</p>

<a name="Signal.Routing"></a>
<h2>Signal Routing</h2>

<p>Also lost in the miniaturization were the little orange signal routing hints
scattered around the original Jupiter-8 panel:</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/jupiter-8-panel.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Image used with permission from Nikolaus Riehm / Studio Repair'><span class='caption-text'>Image used with permission from Nikolaus Riehm / Studio Repair</span></span></p>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t know of these when I got my JP-08, so it was somewhat confusing. The
source mix knob was the first one I figured out: It mixes between the two only
sound sources &mdash; the two oscillators.</p>

<p>Then there&rsquo;s also routing between the two oscillators. VCO-1 has a &lsquo;cross mod&rsquo;
slider and VCO-2 has a &lsquo;sync&rsquo; switch. What&rsquo;s missing from the panel is the
direction of the routing (and even that routing is going on, if you don&rsquo;t know
what &lsquo;cross mod&rsquo; or &lsquo;sync&rsquo; means).</p>

<p>Cross modulation allows the pitch of VCO-1 to be affected by the pitch of
VCO-2, creating crazy bends or new timbres, depending on the frequency of
VCO-2. Sync allows VCO-2 to return to the start of its cycle at the frequency
of VCO-1, creating new timbres out of existing wave forms. After figuring out
the routing, the JP-08 made a lot more sense.</p>

<p>Perhaps most difficult is keeping track of what the two envelopes control.
ENV-1 can affect the pulse width of both oscillators, the frequency of either
or both oscillators, and the filter cutoff frequency. ENV-2 controls the VCA
and the filter frequency. The filter has a switch choosing which envelope
currently controls the filter.</p>

<a name="Docking.Looks.Better"></a>
<h2>Docking Looks Better</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/jp-08_k-25m.jpg"></p>

<p>The JP-08 itself is a sturdy metal panel on top of a plastic box. In its
unmounted form it appears somewhat naked. Adding the optional K-25m keyboard
module really helps completing the look of the device.</p>

<p>Before I got the keyboard module, the device looked somehow messy and
unfinished on my desk. Now, it makes me smile when I look at it. So I&rsquo;m happy
I got the keyboard module even though it is both expensive and only mediocre as
a keyboard. For use mainly with an external keyboard, the synth can also dock
in the keyboard-less, cheaper DK-01 dock.</p>

<p>Also, the metal surfaces have a satisfying ability to not pick up fingerprints.</p>

<a name="More.Like.JP-04"></a>
<h2>More Like JP-04</h2>

<p>The &lsquo;8&rsquo; in Jupiter-8 meant eight voices. The JP-08 only has four voices,
meaning only 4 notes can sound at the same time. This has irritated a lot of
people, including me. I mean, it&rsquo;s not that I play 9th chords all the time, but
Roland, did you really need to go for the minimum effort here, to try to sell
more boxes?</p>

<p>Roland happily claims that you can connect more units to increase the polyphony
by four each time. This is better than nothing, but it&rsquo;s also only partially
true. Because while you can play 4<em>n</em> notes <em>simultaneously</em>, there&rsquo;s still
voice stealing when you play notes sequentially (which is called&hellip; music&hellip;
you might have heard of it, Roland). That means that if you play a sound that
fades out gradually after lifting your finger from the key, that tail will be
cut off by the next note that starts, if no unused voice is available within
the first 4, <strong>not</strong> 4<em>n</em>, voices. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ejpw7GsyAGg">Here&rsquo;s</a> a demonstration.</p>

<p>Since the JP-08 is a (really good) digital simulation of the original analog
electronics, giving it eight voices shouldn&rsquo;t be that hard. Maybe you&rsquo;d need
a better processor, but compared with the costs of development and production,
that cost should be minimal. And you&rsquo;d have happier users. Then perhaps,
instead of buying another JP-08 and feeling like an idiot, I might have bought
one of the other Boutiques.</p>

<a name="Patch.Selection"></a>
<h2>Patch Selection</h2>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/jp-08-16.jpg' width='' height='' alt='The patch selection button rows of the JU-06 and the JP-08'><span class='caption-text'>The patch selection button rows of the JU-06 and the JP-08</span></span></p>

<p>The four voices bring another annoyance, which we need to take a step back to
understand. The Juno-106, JU-06, Jupiter-8, and JP-08 all have 16 buttons used
for patch selection. The JU-06 has eight bank buttons and eight patch buttons,
leading to a total of 64 patches. (The Juno-106, which I own, additionally has
a group selector multiplying everything by two for 128 patches in total.) On
the Juno-106 and JU-06, a single button press can switch the bank number (the
first digit) and the patch number (the last digit) independently (as well as
the group, on the Juno-106), which is very nice. (The Juno-106 also has a patch
increment pedal input, but I digress).</p>

<p>The JP-08 has eight patch number buttons and eight patch preset buttons.
Choosing one of the 64 patches always requires two consecutive presses of the
patch number buttons. A patch preset on the JP-08 is a layering of two patches
sounding simultaneously, and there are only eight of these. This is also how it
was on the Jupiter-8, except that a Jupiter-8 patch preset could also be
a left/right split between two patches instead of a layering.</p>

<p>A patch preset cuts the polyphony in half, since each note you play uses two
voices. Thus, with the JP-08 having only four voices and no split option, patch
presets are much less useful. You can&rsquo;t even play real chords! You can still
play leads and power chords with your layered sound. However, this could be
accomplished with the &lsquo;dual&rsquo; and &lsquo;upper/lower&rsquo; buttons without reserving eight
buttons for patch presets. Instead, it could have used the faster bank+patch
system like the Juno. (Or better yet, it could just have had eight voices.)</p>

<p>There is one final snafu with the 16 buttons and the way they relate to the
delay effect parameters (level, time, and feedback). Because changing the
parameters is difficult while playing, you are not likely to notice it, but
changing the delay time also flushes the delay buffer. However, if you control
the delay parameters with a knob on a MIDI controller, this becomes
embarrassingly obvious.</p>

<a name="In.Conclusion"></a>
<h2>In Conclusion</h2>

<p>The JP-08 is fun and sounds really good. But there are so many things that feel
like they could have been much better with small changes.</p>

<p>Eight voices, obviously. Then the sliders could have been much better with
a small increase in the height of the box. A small increase in width could have
allowed space for direct control of many more parameters. And an arpeggiator!
Not to mention full width keys or more mini keys. A normal pitch bend and mod
stick would also be great, but this might make the unit deeper.</p>

<p>Dimensions multiply, and the unit would quickly become much bigger and less
cute. But it would also be much better and less toy-like. The tiny Boutique
format just seems to go better with machines with fewer controls the Juno-106
or the VP-330.</p>

<p>Seeing newer Boutique releases having features that the JP-08 should have had
also feels like betrayal, after throwing money at a first generation Boutique
model. We&rsquo;re talking tempo synced LFO, tempo synced delay, sequencer note
slides, sequencer song mode, and sequencer <em>parameter locks</em>! It hurts, Roland.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Work Helps Me Beat Procrastination]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/01/22/work-helps-me-beat-procrastination/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-22T17:23:59+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2017/01/22/work-helps-me-beat-procrastination</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in school, I put off essay writing until the night before the due date. In
gymnasium/high school, I put off assignments until the <em>morning</em> of the due
date. In my first years of university it went so far that a student counsellor
suggested that maybe university wasn&rsquo;t for me.</p>

<p>Despite&mdash;or perhaps because of&mdash;that, I pulled myself together. After passing
some courses that especially triggered my procrastination, I did much better,
and eventually emerged with a master&rsquo;s degree in software engineering and a PhD
in computer science.</p>

<p>But that does not mean I had completely overcome procrastination, especially
not during the PhD study. It was not until <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2016/05/09/leaving-academia/">leaving academia</a> for the
IT business that I experienced what it is like to get control of my
procrastination. (It&rsquo;s amazing, by the way.)</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="My.Job"></a>
<h2>My Job</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s ironic that procrastination means postponing work, but my job actually
helps me avoid procrastination. I&rsquo;ll try to figure out why that is. To that
end, I&rsquo;ll first describe my job. It includes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Designing software solutions meeting the clients&#8217; requirements.</li>
<li>Implementing (programming) software solutions according to designs approved
by the clients.</li>
<li>Registering the time spent on all tasks in our time tracking system.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Doing.It.for.Others"></a>
<h2>Doing It for Others</h2>

<p>There are many aspects of the above that contribute to procrastinating less.
One of them, I think, is that this is the first time in my education and work
life that people who ask me to do something want me to do it for <em>their</em> sake.</p>

<p>Beating procrastination often requires external deadlines and reasons. In
education of all levels, teachers ask us to do exercises, homework,
assignments, semester projects, theses. But while they ask you, and systems may
be in place to punish those who do not comply, the requests are not truly
external. The purpose is that <em>you</em> learn, not (necessarily) that <em>they want</em>
to read your work.</p>

<p>Compulsory education contains more external pressure to learn than higher
education (which is probably why procrastination gets worse the higher you get
in the education system). In a job, you get back some external pressure, and
this time they care more about what they get out of it than what you get out of
it.</p>

<p>Although external reasons (and payment!) are good reasons to work, they are
unfortunately not enough to fight procrastination.</p>

<a name="Implementation.Tasks.are.Well-Defined"></a>
<h2>Implementation Tasks are Well-Defined</h2>

<p>One of the causes for procrastination is perfectionism. Often the desire to
find the perfect solution to a problem puts so much pressure on you that you do
not even succeed in finding a good-enough solution. Simply taking a step
towards finding the perfect solution feels like a futile step towards
a possibly unachievable goal, so let&rsquo;s just look at cat videos on YouTube
instead.</p>

<p>Working to implement a preapproved design means that the biggest decisions have
already been made, whether by yourself or by others, and locked in by the
client. Now your task is not to solve the original business problem, but simply
to implement the designed solution in the allotted time.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Simply&rdquo; does not mean to imply that it&rsquo;s easy. A high level of expertise is
required to write correct, robust, efficient, and maintainable code. But with
well-defined goals for the programming, the task is constrained enough that
a skilled procrastinator (skilled at programming, that is) can attack the task
head-on rather than postpone it.</p>

<p>I do still get ideas to change the design while working to implement it, but
the bureaucracy involved in changing it is actually a good thing here because
it keeps me from trying, unless I&rsquo;m convinced it&rsquo;s necessary. It&rsquo;s better to
have a good solution done on time than a perfect solution that isn&rsquo;t.</p>

<a name="Implementation.Tasks.are.Divisible"></a>
<h2>Implementation Tasks are Divisible</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not just that implementation tasks are easier when the design is fixed.
It&rsquo;s also that the they can be broken into smaller parts that are even easier
to do.</p>

<p>The first subtask is to understand the design and hold a mental model of it.
Depending on the level of detail in the design description, this can itself
turn into clarifying discussions with the author, but that is also fairly
well-defined.</p>

<p>Many of the remaining subtasks are taken from a repertoire that includes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Adding required tables and fields to the database</li>
<li>Identifying required data and writing queries to retrieve it</li>
<li>Adding the business logic</li>
<li>Testing the solution, and adding error handling and logging</li>
</ul>


<a name="Time.Tracking"></a>
<h2>Time Tracking</h2>

<p>Next up is the time tracking we are required to do. While working a task, any
task, we register the time spent in an issue tracker. Our issue trackers are
then connected to the time tracking system, and in the time tracking system
each week has to sum up to the number of hours our contract states before we
can &ldquo;close&rdquo; that week. It&rsquo;s cold, mechanical, and unsympathetic, and it works
wonders in beating procrastination.</p>

<a name="Design.Tasks.Can.Make.You.Proud"></a>
<h2>Design Tasks Can Make You Proud</h2>

<p>Design is the process of turning the client&rsquo;s requirements into a consistent
and implementable description in terms of the business domain. Sometimes this
requires several iterations with client feedback and further changes before the
design is approved. A design can also be a change to a previously implemented
module or feature.</p>

<p>If it&rsquo;s a change request, it&rsquo;s fairly simple: read up on documentation and code
until you hold a good-enough mental model of the existing functionality. From
there, seeing where changes are required, is often obvious.</p>

<p>If it&rsquo;s a new module or feature, it may be harder to get started. That&rsquo;s where
one of the risks of procrastination hide. However, two things can mitigate
this. The first is <em>structured procrastination</em>: While putting off the daunting
design task, work on something else productive like a straightforward
implementation task (as opposed to watching cat videos on YouTube). At least
you&rsquo;re doing something productive.</p>

<p>The second thing is that once you do get it cracked and have your initial idea
for the general direction of the design, a feeling of ownership and pride
starts to grow. This will make it much easier to keep the focus.</p>

<p>All in all, my job helps me keep my procrastination in check, which I&rsquo;m very
happy about. I hope all you other procrastinators out there can see that your
circumstances can help you beat procrastination, if you haven&rsquo;t cracked the
code yet.</p>

<p><em>Update 2018-07-28: Fixed typos.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learn Vim the Harder Way, Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2016/08/28/learn-vim-the-harder-way-part-ii/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-28T13:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2016/08/28/learn-vim-the-harder-way-part-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2016/05/16/learn-vim-the-harder-way/">previous post</a> I introduced learning <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vim_%28text_editor%29">Vim</a> the harder way. To summarize:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>The easy way</strong>: Use the arrow keys for cursor movement</li>
<li><strong>The hard way</strong>: Don&rsquo;t use arrow keys; use <em>hjkl</em> in <em>normal mode</em></li>
<li><strong>The harder way</strong>: Don&rsquo;t use <em>hjkl</em>; learn Vim&rsquo;s multitude of other motion
commands</li>
</ul>


<p>Now, there&rsquo;s nothing wrong with using the arrow keys per se, but it very often
leads to staying in <em>insert mode</em> most of the time and thus missing out on all
the stuff you can do from <em>normal mode</em>. As someone <a href="http://www.viemu.com/a-why-vi-vim.html">wrote</a> about vi/Vim:</p>

<blockquote><p>your keyboard becomes a huge specialized text-editing gamepad with almost
a hundred buttons.</p></blockquote>

<p>There&rsquo;s nothing wrong with using <em>hjkl</em> either, in fact they&rsquo;re very good
because they force you to use <em>normal mode</em> as your, well, normal mode.
However, normal mode only really provides an advantage if you harness its power
and go beyond the basics. For motions, that involves reducing your use of
<em>hjkl</em>. In this part we see how to do that for inserting and deleting text.</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Insert.Without..em.i..em."></a>
<h2>Insert Without <em>i</em></h2>

<p>One of the first things Vim users learn is that you type <em>i</em> to go to insert
mode (where you can write text). Just like <em>hjkl</em>, <em>i</em> is a basic command. And
just like there are many other motions beyond <em>hjkl</em>, there are more commands
that bring you to insert mode:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>a</em> appends text after the current character (like <em>i</em> inserts before it).</li>
<li><em>I</em> and <em>A</em> insert text at the beginning and end of the line, respectively,
no matter where on the line your cursor is.</li>
<li><em>o</em> and <em>O</em> &ldquo;open&rdquo; a new blank line for writing immediately after and before
the current line, respectively (no matter where on the line your cursor is).
When used for programming (for example with <code>:set autoindent</code>), &ldquo;open&rdquo; also
does intelligent indentation.</li>
<li><em>gi</em> inserts text where you last stopped inserting text, no matter where in
the buffer the cursor now is.</li>
</ul>


<p>Try disabling <em>i</em> with <code>:nmap i &lt;nop&gt;</code>, or perhaps with a reminder of what to
do instead: <code>:nnoremap i :echoerr "Try a/I/A/o/O/gi instead!"&lt;cr&gt;</code>. It&rsquo;s really
annoying, but that&rsquo;s the point. Once you have a basic grasp of the other insert
mode commands, you can remove the mapping again with <code>:nunmap i</code>.</p>

<p>By the way, I lied a bit earlier. The command <em>I</em> doesn&rsquo;t insert at the
beginning of the line. It inserts immediately before the first non-whitespace
character of the line, which is often convenient, not least in programming. But
you can still tell Vim to <em>really</em> insert at the beginning of the line with the
command <em>gI</em>. Vim is thorough like that.</p>

<a name="Delete.Without.Backspace"></a>
<h2>Delete Without Backspace</h2>

<p>Now you know a flexible set of commands to go to insert mode. Once you&rsquo;re
there, there&rsquo;s one thing you should not to too much (beside use the arrow
keys), and that is: backspace. Like many other commands, it is a basic
operation good in some cases and inefficient in others. It&rsquo;s good for
correcting a typo, but deleting words and anything bigger is like digging with
a teaspoon. So I&rsquo;d recommend removing the temptation to use the teaspoon by
disallowing backspacing past the position where you started insert mode:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>set backspace-=start</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>You can still correct typos while you type. In normal mode you can also delete
a few chars with the <em>x</em> and <em>X</em> commands which work like delete and backspace
do in insert mode.</p>

<p>For anything bigger, use the delete command <em>d</em>. It takes a motion or text
object. For example, <code>dw</code> deletes from the cursor position until the start of
the next word, <code>dt'</code> deletes until the next apostrophe, and <code>dap</code> deletes
a paragraph (the one the cursor is currently in). All in one step.</p>

<p>Besides being more efficient, doing it as a single command has the advantage
that it can be undone as a single command (<em>u</em>), and, perhaps more importantly,
that you get the whole thing copied so you can insert it later (in Vim, delete
and cut are the same thing).</p>

<a name="Delete.and.Insert.at.the.Same.Time"></a>
<h2>Delete and Insert at the Same Time</h2>

<p>In the previous section I suggest staying in normal mode when removing text.
But what if you want to both delete <em>and</em> insert text? Just like Vim provides
many commands than combine moving the cursor and inserting text (<em>a</em>, <em>I</em>, <em>A</em>,
etc.), it also provides commands that combine deleting and inserting:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>r</em> replaces the character under the cursor with another character of your
choosing</li>
<li><em>R</em> drops you into replace mode where you overwrite/replace text until you
return to normal mode with Esc.</li>
<li><em>s</em>/<em>S</em> substitute the character/line under the cursor with any text (insert
mode)</li>
<li><em>c</em> changes text into other text: It first awaits your choice of motion or
text object to delete and then drops you into insert mode. For example, <code>c)</code>
changes from the cursor position until the end of the sentence and <code>ci"</code>
changes the whole content of the double quote delimited string the cursor is
in.</li>
<li><em>C</em> changes from the cursor position to the end of the line (similarly to how
<em>D</em> deletes from the cursor position to the EOL while <em>d</em> takes a motion or
text object)</li>
</ul>


<p>If you&rsquo;re comfortable with <em>x</em>/<em>X</em>/<em>d</em>, but not the replace/substitute/change
commands, I&rsquo;d recommend something crazy: Disable <em>x</em>, <em>X</em>, and <em>d</em>:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>nmap x &lt;nop&gt;
</span><span class='line'>nmap X &lt;nop&gt;
</span><span class='line'>nmap d &lt;nop&gt;</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Instead, the stuff you want to delete, you can substitute/change into nothing
until the substitute/change commands comes naturally to you.</p>

<a name="Learn"></a>
<h2>Learn</h2>

<p>The point of temporarily disabling commands is not to say they&rsquo;re bad, because
they&rsquo;re not. They are strictly necessary parts of Vim. The point is to <em>also</em>
learn the more powerful and flexible commands. I have only covered the basics
of normal mode, but read <code>:help</code>, <code>:help user-manual</code>, and <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1218390/what-is-your-most-productive-shortcut-with-vim/1220118#1220118">this</a> to
uncover all the cool stuff you can do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[INSIDE]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2016/07/31/inside/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-31T19:53:27+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2016/07/31/inside</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don&rsquo;t game a lot, but after seeing rave reviews, I knew I had to try
Playdead&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.playdead.com/games/inside/">INSIDE</a>.</p>

<div class="video-container">
<iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/op4G1--kb-g?rel=0&showinfo=0&feature=player_detailpage" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>And, like many others, I was blown away.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Above all stands the eerie, mesmerizing, spine-chilling atmosphere. It&rsquo;s
a combination of the visuals, the sounds, the story. All three are tightly
integrated as well as dark, minimalist, mysterious, foreboding and
awe-inspiring.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.playdead.com/css/img/inside/screenshots/INSIDE_05.jpg"></p>

<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2.5D">two-and-a-half dimensions</a> are amazing. The game uses 2D controls in
a 3D world. The third dimension is an integral part of the game even though the
protagonist cannot enter it. First of all, it tells the most of the story.
Second, while the boy is stuck in 2D, antagonists can move in 3D which is used
in puzzles or to introduce them before they interact with you. When a dog
chases you, you can hear it barking as it appears in the distance and races
towards you. If it catches you, it does not feel unfair &mdash; only terrifying.</p>

<p>The camera is also used to great effect. While the camera always follows the
protagonist, it subtly, gradually changes perspective to draw attention to
puzzle elements and places you are going. The camera also zooms in and out
depending on the scene. I vividly remember the zoomed-in view of trying to fend
off a pack of dogs with a torch, or the zoom-out of an underwater expanse
making me feel small and vulnerable while also coaxing me into exploring.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://www.playdead.com/css/img/inside/screenshots/INSIDE_06.jpg' width='' height='' alt='The camera perspective reveals a drainpipe that will become relevant in the near future.'><span class='caption-text'>The camera perspective reveals a drainpipe that will become relevant in the near future.</span></span></p>

<p>The realism of movements is also amazing. The physically unrealistic platformer
classic of changing direction in mid-air does not work here. But it&rsquo;s also in
details such as running in mud slowing the boy down. He can stumble and fall.
When climbing a ladder, his hands and feet will touch each individual rung.
Climbing and swinging a rope looks realistic. While underwater, it takes time
to change direction.</p>

<p>In general, I just loved the attention to detail. His breathing chest movements
match the sound of his breathing. And his breathing matches the tension of the
situation. In this regard, I think that coming up short of breath from a deep
dive should also affect his breathing, but it doesn&rsquo;t. This seems like a minor
oversight in what is otherwise a parade of perfection.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.playdead.com/css/img/inside/screenshots/INSIDE_04.jpg"></p>

<p>The details are not just about the boy&rsquo;s movements. There are many subtleties
that you only find by chance. For example, while swinging from a lamp cord,
sparks will fly from the lamp on the off chance that it hits the wall. A blast
of air will throw zombies off their feet in the rare case they are standing
nearby. Some details are even hidden on purpose. There is a cord you can climb,
but when you stand under it, it (and the boy) is obscured by a pillar in the
foreground.</p>

<p>Finally, I love the complete lack of words in the game, both spoken and
written. The gameplay needs no explanation because the whole thing is just
a beautifully crafted progression of elements. The story is very open to
interpretation. I think you should play the game and see for yourself!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learn Vim the Harder Way]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2016/05/16/learn-vim-the-harder-way/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-16T14:59:23+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2016/05/16/learn-vim-the-harder-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first lesson of the official <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vim_%28text_editor%29">Vim</a> tutorial (&ldquo;vimtutor&rdquo;) introduces
the navigation keys <em>h</em>, <em>j</em>, <em>k</em>, <em>l</em>. This is where the user might go
&ldquo;What?&rdquo;, followed perhaps by &ldquo;What&rsquo;s wrong with the arrow keys?&rdquo; The tutorial
has this answer: &ldquo;The cursor keys should also work. But using hjkl you will be
able to move around much faster, once you get used to it. Really!&rdquo;</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/vimtutor.png"></p>

<p>From here, I think most people continue using Vim with the arrow keys and
perhaps mouse because that&rsquo;s what they&rsquo;re used to, and why change something
that works? Users who actually use hjkl from this point onwards (either by
sheer willpower or by disabling the mouse and arrow keys) are learning Vim &ldquo;the
hard way&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Let me say from the beginning that I agree with the tutorial: Using hjkl <em>is</em>
better. But for most people the hard way is not the right way. Learning Vim
<a href="http://yannesposito.com/Scratch/en/blog/Learn-Vim-Progressively/">progressively</a> is more fun and will allow you to switch to Vim
while still <a href="http://yehudakatz.com/2010/07/29/everyone-who-tried-to-convince-me-to-use-vim-was-wrong/">getting work done</a>. In addition to the official
vimtutor, you can also try an <a href="http://www.openvim.com/tutorial.html">interactive tutorial</a>, or even an
<a href="http://vim-adventures.com/">adventure game</a>.</p>

<p>If, however, you are going for the hard way, let me propose learning Vim the
<em>harder</em> way!</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Learning.Vim.the.Harder.Way"></a>
<h2>Learning Vim the Harder Way</h2>

<p>The harder way is to use neither arrow keys <em>nor</em> hjkl.</p>

<p>So what do you do instead? Finding out is exactly the point of this exercise.
Vim has a very rich set of motion commands (see <code>:help motion.txt</code> in Vim or
<a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/vim/vim/master/runtime/doc/motion.txt">here</a>) that you might never come across if you can get by with hjkl
&mdash; just like you wouldn&rsquo;t learn hjkl if you kept using the arrow keys.</p>

<p>While writing this article, I experimented with various variations on this.
After disabling hjkl, it took some time before I noticed that the sideways
motions <em>h</em> and <em>l</em> were missing (i.e., I use other, more direct motions more).
On the other hand, the up-down motions <em>j</em> and <em>k</em> in many cases <em>are</em> the most
efficient motions when combined with counts (see <code>:help count</code>) and relative
line numbers. Therefore, I do not recommend disabling <em>j</em> and
<em>k</em> completely. But to nudge you into using them intelligently, I suggest
disabling the &ldquo;repeat keys&rdquo; feature in your OS keyboard settings:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/repeat_keys.png"></p>

<p>When this is done, disable the mouse and <em>h</em> and <em>l</em> as well as the arrow keys
in both normal mode and insert mode:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='html'><span class='line'>set nocompatible
</span><span class='line'>set mouse=
</span><span class='line'>map h <span class="nt">&lt;nop&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>map l <span class="nt">&lt;nop&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>map <span class="nt">&lt;left&gt;</span> <span class="nt">&lt;nop&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>map <span class="nt">&lt;down&gt;</span> <span class="nt">&lt;nop&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>map <span class="nt">&lt;up&gt;</span> <span class="nt">&lt;nop&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>map <span class="nt">&lt;right&gt;</span> <span class="nt">&lt;nop&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>imap <span class="nt">&lt;left&gt;</span> <span class="nt">&lt;nop&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>imap <span class="nt">&lt;down&gt;</span> <span class="nt">&lt;nop&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>imap <span class="nt">&lt;up&gt;</span> <span class="nt">&lt;nop&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>imap <span class="nt">&lt;right&gt;</span> <span class="nt">&lt;nop&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The first command, <code>set nocompatible</code>, changes many options from vi compatible
to sane.</p>

<p>You can try these commands in Vim by typing &lsquo;:&rsquo; to go command line mode, typing
the command, and then pressing Enter. For example: <code>:map h &lt;nop&gt;</code> followed by
Enter. This lasts until you close Vim or undo it with <code>:unmap h</code>. To make it
stick, put the commands in your vimrc configuration file (see <code>:help vimrc</code>),
and they will be loaded each time you start Vim, until you remove them from
your vimrc again.</p>

<a name="Start.Learning"></a>
<h2>Start Learning</h2>

<p>At first, the above settings are a pain in the gluteus maximus.</p>

<p>Fire up <a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/vim/vim/master/runtime/doc/motion.txt"><code>:help motion.txt</code></a> and look around. (If you&rsquo;re tired of
moving down one <em>j</em> at a time, use CTRL-f and CTRL-b to go forward and backward
one page at a time. Or put the cursor on a <code>|keyword|</code> and press CTRL-] to jump
to that subject.)</p>

<p>To use <em>j</em> and <em>k</em> efficiently for editing, enable relative line numbers:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='html'><span class='line'>set number
</span><span class='line'>set relativenumber
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>They look like this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/vim_relativenumber.png"></p>

<p>As shown in the margin, the cursor is on line 124. To go to the line &ldquo;To
use&hellip;&rdquo;, just look to the left, read the 9, and go nine lines up with <em>9k</em>.
Without relative line numbers (i.e. <code>:set norelativenumber</code>, or <code>:set nornu</code>
for short), you could also see that this line is line 115 and go to it with
<em>115G</em>, but that&rsquo;s twice the typing.</p>

<p>While getting by with <em>j</em> and <em>k</em>, missing <em>h</em> and <em>l</em> is probably really bad
at first. Take a look at <code>:help word-motions</code> and <code>:help left-right-motions</code>
(which are sections of motion.txt). The six motions <em>f</em>, <em>F</em>, <em>t</em>, <em>T</em>,
<em>(comma)</em>, and <em>;</em> (where <em>(comma)</em> is the comma key itself), will come in
especially handy. To give an example, with the cursor at X on this line and an
&lsquo;x&rsquo; somewhere later, typing <em>fx</em> will go to that x. (Go try it in Vim!) For
letters more common than x, these find commands are less useful. But uppercase
letters and punctuation are easy targets, and help you navigate very quickly.</p>

<p>Playing around with <em>f</em> and family, you will notice that while they are very
fast to type, they only move within the current line, and of course they only
find one symbol at a time. Read <code>:help search-commands</code> to get into the big
league search commands.</p>

<p>At this point I&rsquo;ll remark that the search default settings are a bit lame.
I prefer these settings regarding search:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='vim'><span class='line'><span class="k">set</span> <span class="nb">incsearch</span>   <span class="c">&quot; Search while you type</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">set</span> <span class="nb">hlsearch</span>    <span class="c">&quot; Highlight all matches</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">set</span> <span class="nb">ignorecase</span>  <span class="c">&quot; Ignore case while searching...</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">set</span> <span class="nb">smartcase</span>   <span class="c">&quot; ...unless you use uppercase letters in the search pattern.</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Especially search <span style="background-color: yellow;">highlight</span> can
be useful, but after finding what you were looking for, you might want to get
rid of the <span style="background-color: yellow;">highlight</span>ing. Rather
than disabling it completely (<code>:set nohlsearch</code>), just turn it off until your
next search with <code>:nohlsearch</code>, or <code>:noh</code> for short.</p>

<p>In addition, when there are many highlighted matches close to each other,
Damian Conway&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/thoughtstream/Damian-Conway-s-Vim-Setup/blob/master/plugin/hlnext.vim">hlnext</a> plugin helps you see where you&rsquo;re at by
blinking the next hit reached with <em>n</em> or <em>N</em>.</p>

<a name="Conclusion"></a>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>As I mentioned in the beginning, learning Vim incrementally is the most useful.
So the harder way is not the best for most beginners. But I think it is very
useful for people who use Vim frequently but would like to unlock more of its
potential.</p>

<p>Also, we have just scratched the surface of what you can do in Vim. For any
learner, new or experienced, I&rsquo;d recommend reading <code>:help user-manual</code> from
start to end. This is in fact how I learned Vim.</p>

<p>Update: See also <a href="http://blog.erw.dk/2016/08/28/learn-vim-the-harder-way-part-ii/">part II</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leaving Academia]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2016/05/09/leaving-academia/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-09T06:35:59+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2016/05/09/leaving-academia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last fall, I had been at Aalborg University for nine years: One year in
electronic engineering, five years studying software engineering, and three
years doing a PhD in computer science. The first six years as a bachelor and
master&rsquo;s student were relatively straightforward and satisfying. The last three
years formed my introduction to the academic world.</p>

<p>Being a PhD student in computer science does not mean you are a student of
computer science at a high level. Well, you are that, but first and foremost,
you are an apprentice of academia. The distinction is important because, while
I love computer science, academia is, it turned out for me, not great.</p>

<p>I left the university before having finished my PhD, to work at a private
company as an IT consultant. I managed to finish my thesis concurrently with my
new job, and I have now defended it successfully. But the last half year has
also helped me see more clearly my motivation for switching jobs. It can be
summed up like this: Now, I go home from work most days feeling a sense of
accomplishment. Before, I came home from work many days with the feeling of
having failed.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Research is hard. It&rsquo;s hard because you are trying to do something that has not
been done before. There is no recipe that guarantees success, because if
someone could tell you what to do, you wouldn&rsquo;t be doing research anymore.
Research is hard because a lot of the time you feel lost and stupid. This is
normal, I was told. But knowing that it is normal does not magically make it
feel good.</p>

<a name="Purpose"></a>
<h2>Purpose</h2>

<p>The question then is if there is something else in the job that makes it
worthwhile and keeps you motivated. According to behavioral economist Dan
Ariely, two of the key motivating factors at work are the feelings of
<a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/dan_ariely_what_makes_us_feel_good_about_our_work">progress and purpose</a>. Progress is generally slow in research due to
its nature. You will fail a lot before stumbling upon something important. So
what about purpose?</p>

<p>Ideally, research should be about the noble goal of adding to the pool of human
knowledge. Cure the proverbial cancer. But doing something significant in
research takes decades and even then is not guaranteed to happen. And that
leaves us back at the slow progress. So how about the feeling of purpose in the
shorter term?</p>

<p>This is where my new job really became a contrast to research. On the grand
scale of things, my work as an IT consultant is fairly insignificant. But on
a smaller scale, it <em>is</em> significant: Someone (the client) is actually going to
use what I am building for them. This is in contrast to academia, where I feel
that very few people read my work, let alone <em>use it</em> for anything. Making
something that others use, want, and care about feels great. Submitting
a research paper for publication and getting grumpy reviews back months later
does not.</p>

<p>Of course, the work I do as an IT consultant is not guaranteed to be used. The
client may change their mind and drop whatever project you are working on. But
since they ordered it and are paying good money for it, they are likely to want
it. In academia, conferences and journals are more important and prestigious,
the more submissions they reject.</p>

<a name="Feedback"></a>
<h2>Feedback</h2>

<p>So what if you instead look for purpose in the very short short term &ndash; hours
and days? In presenting a small new idea, or new section in a draft, and having
your collaborators see it and comment on it? Here, academia also disappointed
me. Getting feedback on my work was not always easy. Meetings could be fitted
into busy schedules a few times a month, and you would be lucky to get an email
reply without sending several reminders.</p>

<p>Unlike the inherent hardness of research, feedback in the short term is
somewhat within your own control because you can influence who you collaborate
with. But I still think my experience is fairly common.</p>

<p>In my new job, feedback is not something I get a few times per week &ndash; it is
something I get a few times per <em>hour</em>. Everybody&rsquo;s busy, but we take time to
help each other. In general I liked my colleagues at the university, but I feel
more like part of a team now than I have ever done as a PhD student.</p>

<p>To top it off, I also feel much more valued now because my time is treated with
respect. And of course it is: Every hour I am not doing billable work is missed
income for the company. And so, getting equipment, booking travels, getting
expenses refunded &mdash; everything is laughably easy compared to the university.</p>

<a name="Just.a.Job."></a>
<h2>Just a Job?</h2>

<p>One might object and say that travel booking and emails are irrelevant; that
work in academia is about grander things. Indeed, a faculty member who joined
the research group I was in complained that the PhD students were not dedicated
enough; that we just treated research as &ldquo;a job&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I think if you work on a topic that you care deeply about, then indeed you can
push on in spite of the slow progress. The feeling of ownership is a strong
motivator.</p>

<p>I was not strongly dedicated to my PhD research. When I couldn&rsquo;t get a PhD
position within my favored topic, I settled for what I could get right here,
right now, rather than looking for other options. In hindsight this was
a mistake. But I&rsquo;m not the only one who made the mistake. And perhaps academia
as an increasingly competitive institution could benefit from having work done
by &ldquo;research <a href="http://academia.stackexchange.com/a/35003">technicians</a>&rdquo; following the lead of a principal
investigator. At least, that could solve the current situation where far more
PhDs are produced than there are permanent positions available for.</p>

<p>But to keep us technicians happy doing what is partially someone elses
research, we need to be treated exactly as employees doing a regular &ldquo;job&rdquo;. And
to be motivated to do this job where real successes are occasional at best, the
working conditions should provide the day-to-day work satisfaction. And of
course no matter your motivation to tackle long-term research problems, dealing
with bureaucracy is no fun.</p>

<a name="How.to.Succeed"></a>
<h2>How to Succeed</h2>

<p>I do hope that the work I have done during my time working in research has made
a <a href="http://matt.might.net/articles/phd-school-in-pictures/">dent</a>, and I am thankful for the good experiences I have had. But
I would also like others considering doing a PhD to think about why they want
to do it. I thought that because I was a good bachelor and master&rsquo;s student,
I would be a good PhD student. And perhaps I was good for my co-authors, at
least I have been told that. But being a PhD student wasn&rsquo;t good for <em>me</em>.</p>

<p>I think, for academia to be good for you, three things are crucial:</p>

<ul>
<li>You should have a clear goal that is enough yours that you feel ownership of
it and therefore motivation. If your research project is too much somebody
else&rsquo;s idea, you may lose this important source of motivation.</li>
<li>When that is said, you should also work with people who agree with your goal,
and who you enjoy working with. If you collaborate with people you do not
strongly enjoy working with, you will miss regular morale boosts that help keep
you going in spite of the many failures you encounter.</li>
<li>You need to be either highly confident or <a href="http://jcs.biologists.org/content/121/11/1771">productively stupid</a>.</li>
</ul>


<p>Perhaps someday I will get an idea for a research project of my own and find
the right place to pursue it, but for now I&rsquo;ll happily develop &ldquo;mundane&rdquo;
business software that people use in the &ldquo;real world&rdquo;, as we used to say at the
university.</p>

<p><em>Update 2018-07-28: Fixed a typo.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Entering Dates and Times in Vim]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2016/04/19/entering-dates-and-times-in-vim/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-19T07:55:20+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2016/04/19/entering-dates-and-times-in-vim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a young Windows user, I learned that if you write <code>.LOG</code> as the first line
of a text file, then each time you open it in Notepad, it appends the current
time and date to the file. That was pretty cool. And useful for logging things,
as <code>.LOG</code> implies. Later I became a <a href="http://www.vim.org/about.php">Vim</a> user and started enjoying all
the customization I can do to my editor. Or perhaps I became a Vim user because
I enjoy customizing! Either way, I like my date and time shortcuts in Vim. For
example:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='C'><span class='line'><span class="n">noremap</span><span class="o">!</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">expr</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="p">,</span><span class="n">t</span> <span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;%H:%M&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This means: Map the key sequence <code>,t</code> (comma followed by &rsquo;t&#8217;) to the result of
the expression <code>strftime("%H:%M")</code> in the insert and command line modes. So if
I write &ldquo;The package arrived ,t&rdquo;, what I will see is &ldquo;The package arrived
13:43&rdquo;, or whatever the time was. I use capital T for further precision
(seconds), <code>,d</code> to insert the date (of course in ISO 8601 format), and <code>,l</code> to
insert date and time together (&lsquo;l&rsquo; for log, as with <code>.LOG</code>):</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='C'><span class='line'><span class="n">noremap</span><span class="o">!</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">expr</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="p">,</span><span class="n">T</span> <span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;%H:%M:%S&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">noremap</span><span class="o">!</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">expr</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="p">,</span><span class="n">d</span> <span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;%Y-%m-%d&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">noremap</span><span class="o">!</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">expr</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="p">,</span><span class="n">l</span> <span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;%Y-%m-%d %H:%M&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<!-- more -->


<p>There are only so many shortcuts you can make with the Control and Alt keys,
but if you use key sequences, you have many more. I have chosen comma as
a &ldquo;leader&rdquo; key because I rarely write it without following it by a space. In
case I do want to write literally &ldquo;,t&rdquo; without a space, I have to type &ldquo;,,t&rdquo;,
where the double comma is a command to insert a single comma:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='C'><span class='line'><span class="n">noremap</span><span class="o">!</span> <span class="p">,,</span> <span class="p">,</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The &ldquo;nore&rdquo; part of &ldquo;noremap&rdquo; means &ldquo;no remapping&rdquo;, i.e., don&rsquo;t use the output
of this mapping as input to another mapping. If it <em>did</em> remap, the one comma
produced here would be interpreted as the start of one of the mappings starting
with comma, including itself.</p>

<p>I use these functions daily, for example at work, where I keep a log of which
tasks I start when. I also use it a lot with <a href="http://todotxt.com/">todotxt</a> when writing
due dates or threshold dates. Finally, I added a mapping to insert the first of
the next month.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='C'><span class='line'><span class="n">noremap</span><span class="o">!</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">expr</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="p">,</span><span class="n">D</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="err">\</span> <span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;%Y&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;%m&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="mi">12</span> <span class="p">.</span> <span class="s">&quot;-&quot;</span> <span class="p">.</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="err">\</span> <span class="n">repeat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sc">&#39;0&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">len</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;%m&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">%</span> <span class="mi">12</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="p">.</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="err">\</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;%m&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">%</span> <span class="mi">12</span> <span class="p">.</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="err">\</span> <span class="s">&quot;-01&quot;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Typing &ldquo;,D&rdquo; today would yield 2016-05-01, for example.</p>

<p>Entered times and dates can also be manipulated with Vim&rsquo;s Ctrl-A and Ctrl-X
increment and decrement commands. Want to add two weeks? Type 14 followed by
Ctrl-X to add 14 days.</p>

<p>My duplicate increment line mappings also come in handy:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='C'><span class='line'><span class="n">nnoremap</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">silent</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>       <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">F2</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>  <span class="err">@</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="err">&#39;</span><span class="n">yyp</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">c</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">v</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="n">c</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="err">&#39;</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">cr</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">nnoremap</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">silent</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>       <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">F3</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>  <span class="err">@</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="err">&#39;</span><span class="n">yypE</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">c</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">v</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="n">c</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="err">&#39;</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">cr</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If I write &ldquo;2016-04-20 Plan:&rdquo; followed by 10 and then the F3 key, I immediately
have:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='C'><span class='line'><span class="mi">2016</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mo">04</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">20</span> <span class="nl">Plan</span><span class="p">:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">2016</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mo">04</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">21</span> <span class="nl">Plan</span><span class="p">:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">2016</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mo">04</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">22</span> <span class="nl">Plan</span><span class="p">:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">2016</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mo">04</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">23</span> <span class="nl">Plan</span><span class="p">:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">2016</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mo">04</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">24</span> <span class="nl">Plan</span><span class="p">:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">2016</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mo">04</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">25</span> <span class="nl">Plan</span><span class="p">:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">2016</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mo">04</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">26</span> <span class="nl">Plan</span><span class="p">:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">2016</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mo">04</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">27</span> <span class="nl">Plan</span><span class="p">:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">2016</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mo">04</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">28</span> <span class="nl">Plan</span><span class="p">:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">2016</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mo">04</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">29</span> <span class="nl">Plan</span><span class="p">:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">2016</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mo">04</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">30</span> <span class="nl">Plan</span><span class="p">:</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Actually, Vim just thinks it&rsquo;s decrementing the integer -19 to -20 and so on,
but Tim Pope&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/tpope/vim-speeddating">speeddating.vim</a> plugin adds date and time
awareness, so typing Ctrl-A on 2016-04-30 would result in 2016-05-01 and not
2016-04-31. Happy Vimming!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Remote Desktop White Screen - Solved]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2016/03/12/remote-desktop-white-screen-solved/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-12T13:54:10+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2016/03/12/remote-desktop-white-screen-solved</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/rdp.png" width="450"></p>

<p>At work, I often connect to Windows servers over Remote Desktop Protocol (RDP).
A few times, I have been met with a blank white screen, typically after
changing screen resolution in the Remote Desktop Connection options.</p>

<p>The first time this happened I spent a lot of time googling to no avail, so now
I will put the solution I found by chance here in case it might help someone
else. And note that encountering a blank <em>black</em> screen is a different and more
frequent problem, the solutions to which didn&rsquo;t help me with my white screen in
the time that I spent on it.</p>

<a name="Solution:.Alt-F4"></a>
<h3>Solution: Alt-F4</h3>

<p>An <strong>Alt-F4</strong> was all it took to get rid of the white screen. However, if that
does not work, you can also try a <strong>Ctrl-Alt-End</strong> (the remote desktop
equivalent of Ctrl-Alt-Del), and see if you can work anything out from there.
Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Keep Track With a Year at a Glance]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2016/01/10/keep-track-with-a-year-at-a-glance/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-10T19:32:58+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2016/01/10/keep-track-with-a-year-at-a-glance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://blog.erw.dk/images/posts/floss.jpg' width='' height='' alt='The calendar helped me floss (more or less) daily.'><span class='caption-text'>The calendar helped me floss (more or less) daily.</span></span></p>

<p>If you are already starting to forget about your New Year&rsquo;s resolutions, here&rsquo;s
a tip to keep going: Visualize your progress: Put X&rsquo;s on a calendar on every
day you do what whatever you want to do more of. Stick the calendar on the wall
or wherever it would remind you of your goal.</p>

<p>Some years back, each time I visited my dentist, she recommended that I floss.
And I would decide that <em>this time</em> I would start doing it. But some days
later, I started slipping and forgetting about it. It wasn&rsquo;t until I put
a year-at-a-glance calendar on the bathroom cabinet door that the habit stuck.</p>

<p>Putting a mark on a calendar is not rocket science, but the satisfaction of
marking a completed task and of seeing your progress is a mental reward that
can make a big difference. If you want to try, I made a one page 2016 calendar
you can print (<a href="http://blog.erw.dk/files/cal2016.odt">LibreOffice/odt</a>,
<a href="http://blog.erw.dk/files/cal2016.docx">Word/docx</a>). (It was easily made with the open source
ncal utility, invoked as <code>ncal -bh 2016</code>.)</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Don.t.Break.the.Chain"></a>
<h2>Don&rsquo;t Break the Chain</h2>

<p>For goals that can practically be done every day, it&rsquo;s not just having many
marks on the calendar that is important. A further motivation is to keep the
chain of successful days unbroken. (This method is widely known as the
<a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=seinfeld+strategy">Seinfeld Strategy</a>, even though Jerry Seinfeld says
<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/1ujvrg/jerry_seinfeld_here_i_will_give_you_an_answer/ceitfxh">it wasn&rsquo;t his idea</a>.)
For workouts or other things that you might not have time to do every day, you
could still use the chain method by using a list of weeks of the year, and
checking off each week that met your goal, say, doing at least two workouts. Or
maybe drinking at most three bottles of soda that week.</p>

<p>The chain method is also used in games and apps. For example, the app
<a href="http://www.memrise.com/">Memrise</a> shows me my learning streak, or unbroken chain of days that
I learn/memorize words or images in my chosen topic. Showing the streak has
helped me to learn <a href="http://www.memrise.com/course/42769/country-mapping/">the world map</a> for five minutes a day, 234
days in a row today. (The streak trick worked better than even the designers
anticipated &ndash; the app crashed when trying to award me a 200-day badge.)</p>

<a name="Not.Just.for.Resolutions"></a>
<h2>Not Just for Resolutions</h2>

<p>The fine art of putting marks on a calendar is not just for New Year&rsquo;s
resolutions. I find it useful for anything I want to track. For example, I use
one to remember when I last watered my chili plant. Or put a mark when you
vacuum clean. Then you can see both when it would be a good idea to do it
again, and in the long run, how often you do it &ndash; if you&rsquo;re interested in that
sort of thing. Happy tracking!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
