<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: work life | Erik Ramsgaard Wognsen]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/blog/categories/work-life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/"/>
  <updated>2021-11-11T22:13:21+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.erw.dk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Ramsgaard Wognsen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Work Helps Me Beat Procrastination]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/01/22/work-helps-me-beat-procrastination/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-22T17:23:59+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2017/01/22/work-helps-me-beat-procrastination</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p></p>

<p>Back in school, I put off essay writing until the night before the due date. In
gymnasium/high school, I put off assignments until the <em>morning</em> of the due
date. In my first years of university it went so far that a student counsellor
suggested that maybe university wasn&rsquo;t for me.</p>

<p>Despite&mdash;or perhaps because of&mdash;that, I pulled myself together. After passing
some courses that especially triggered my procrastination, I did much better,
and eventually emerged with a master&rsquo;s degree in software engineering and a PhD
in computer science.</p>

<p>But that does not mean I had completely overcome procrastination, especially
not during the PhD study. It was not until <a href="/2016/05/09/leaving-academia/">leaving academia</a> for the
IT business that I experienced what it is like to get control of my
procrastination. (It&rsquo;s amazing, by the way.)</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></li>
</ul>


<a name="My.Job"></a>
<h2>My Job</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s ironic that procrastination means postponing work, but my job actually
helps me avoid procrastination. I&rsquo;ll try to figure out why that is. To that
end, I&rsquo;ll first describe my job. It includes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Designing software solutions meeting the clients&#8217; requirements.</li>
<li>Implementing (programming) software solutions according to designs approved
by the clients.</li>
<li>Registering the time spent on all tasks in our time tracking system.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Doing.It.for.Others"></a>
<h2>Doing It for Others</h2>

<p>There are many aspects of the above that contribute to procrastinating less.
One of them, I think, is that this is the first time in my education and work
life that people who ask me to do something want me to do it for <em>their</em> sake.</p>

<p>Beating procrastination often requires external deadlines and reasons. In
education of all levels, teachers ask us to do exercises, homework,
assignments, semester projects, theses. But while they ask you, and systems may
be in place to punish those who do not comply, the requests are not truly
external. The purpose is that <em>you</em> learn, not (necessarily) that <em>they want</em>
to read your work.</p>

<p>Compulsory education contains more external pressure to learn than higher
education (which is probably why procrastination gets worse the higher you get
in the education system). In a job, you get back some external pressure, and
this time they care more about what they get out of it than what you get out of
it.</p>

<p></p>

<p>Although external reasons (and payment!) are good reasons to work, they are
unfortunately not enough to fight procrastination.</p>

<a name="Implementation.Tasks.are.Well-Defined"></a>
<h2>Implementation Tasks are Well-Defined</h2>

<p>One of the causes for procrastination is perfectionism. Often the desire to
find the perfect solution to a problem puts so much pressure on you that you do
not even succeed in finding a good-enough solution. Simply taking a step
towards finding the perfect solution feels like a futile step towards
a possibly unachievable goal, so let&rsquo;s just look at cat videos on YouTube
instead.</p>

<p>Working to implement a preapproved design means that the biggest decisions have
already been made, whether by yourself or by others, and locked in by the
client. Now your task is not to solve the original business problem, but simply
to implement the designed solution in the allotted time.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Simply&rdquo; does not mean to imply that it&rsquo;s easy. A high level of expertise is
required to write correct, robust, efficient, and maintainable code. But with
well-defined goals for the programming, the task is constrained enough that
a skilled procrastinator (skilled at programming, that is) can attack the task
head-on rather than postpone it.</p>

<p>I do still get ideas to change the design while working to implement it, but
the bureaucracy involved in changing it is actually a good thing here because
it keeps me from trying, unless I&rsquo;m convinced it&rsquo;s necessary. It&rsquo;s better to
have a good solution done on time than a perfect solution that isn&rsquo;t.</p>

<p></p>

<a name="Implementation.Tasks.are.Divisible"></a>
<h2>Implementation Tasks are Divisible</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not just that implementation tasks are easier when the design is fixed.
It&rsquo;s also that the they can be broken into smaller parts that are even easier
to do.</p>

<p>The first subtask is to understand the design and hold a mental model of it.
Depending on the level of detail in the design description, this can itself
turn into clarifying discussions with the author, but that is also fairly
well-defined.</p>

<p>Many of the remaining subtasks are taken from a repertoire that includes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Adding required tables and fields to the database</li>
<li>Identifying required data and writing queries to retrieve it</li>
<li>Adding the business logic</li>
<li>Testing the solution, and adding error handling and logging</li>
</ul>


<p></p>

<a name="Time.Tracking"></a>
<h2>Time Tracking</h2>

<p>Next up is the time tracking we are required to do. While working a task, any
task, we register the time spent in an issue tracker. Our issue trackers are
then connected to the time tracking system, and in the time tracking system
each week has to sum up to the number of hours our contract states before we
can &ldquo;close&rdquo; that week. It&rsquo;s cold, mechanical, and unsympathetic, and it works
wonders in beating procrastination.</p>

<a name="Design.Tasks.Can.Make.You.Proud"></a>
<h2>Design Tasks Can Make You Proud</h2>

<p></p>

<p>Design is the process of turning the client&rsquo;s requirements into a consistent
and implementable description in terms of the business domain. Sometimes this
requires several iterations with client feedback and further changes before the
design is approved. A design can also be a change to a previously implemented
module or feature.</p>

<p>If it&rsquo;s a change request, it&rsquo;s fairly simple: read up on documentation and code
until you hold a good-enough mental model of the existing functionality. From
there, seeing where changes are required, is often obvious.</p>

<p>If it&rsquo;s a new module or feature, it may be harder to get started. That&rsquo;s where
one of the risks of procrastination hide. However, two things can mitigate
this. The first is <em>structured procrastination</em>: While putting off the daunting
design task, work on something else productive like a straightforward
implementation task (as opposed to watching cat videos on YouTube). At least
you&rsquo;re doing something productive.</p>

<p>The second thing is that once you do get it cracked and have your initial idea
for the general direction of the design, a feeling of ownership and pride
starts to grow. This will make it much easier to keep the focus.</p>

<p></p>

<p>All in all, my job helps me keep my procrastination in check, which I&rsquo;m very
happy about. I hope all you other procrastinators out there can see that your
circumstances can help you beat procrastination, if you haven&rsquo;t cracked the
code yet.</p>

<p><em>Update 2018-07-28: Fixed typos.</em></p>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leaving Academia]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2016/05/09/leaving-academia/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-09T06:35:59+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2016/05/09/leaving-academia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last fall, I had been at Aalborg University for nine years: One year in
electronic engineering, five years studying software engineering, and three
years doing a PhD in computer science. The first six years as a bachelor and
master&rsquo;s student were relatively straightforward and satisfying. The last three
years formed my introduction to the academic world.</p>

<p>Being a PhD student in computer science does not mean you are a student of
computer science at a high level. Well, you are that, but first and foremost,
you are an apprentice of academia. The distinction is important because, while
I love computer science, academia is, it turned out for me, not great.</p>

<p>I left the university before having finished my PhD, to work at a private
company as an IT consultant. I managed to finish my thesis concurrently with my
new job, and I have now defended it successfully. But the last half year has
also helped me see more clearly my motivation for switching jobs. It can be
summed up like this: Now, I go home from work most days feeling a sense of
accomplishment. Before, I came home from work many days with the feeling of
having failed.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Research is hard. It&rsquo;s hard because you are trying to do something that has not
been done before. There is no recipe that guarantees success, because if
someone could tell you what to do, you wouldn&rsquo;t be doing research anymore.
Research is hard because a lot of the time you feel lost and stupid. This is
normal, I was told. But knowing that it is normal does not magically make it
feel good.</p>

<a name="Purpose"></a>
<h2>Purpose</h2>

<p>The question then is if there is something else in the job that makes it
worthwhile and keeps you motivated. According to behavioral economist Dan
Ariely, two of the key motivating factors at work are the feelings of
<a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/dan_ariely_what_makes_us_feel_good_about_our_work">progress and purpose</a>. Progress is generally slow in research due to
its nature. You will fail a lot before stumbling upon something important. So
what about purpose?</p>

<p>Ideally, research should be about the noble goal of adding to the pool of human
knowledge. Cure the proverbial cancer. But doing something significant in
research takes decades and even then is not guaranteed to happen. And that
leaves us back at the slow progress. So how about the feeling of purpose in the
shorter term?</p>

<p>This is where my new job really became a contrast to research. On the grand
scale of things, my work as an IT consultant is fairly insignificant. But on
a smaller scale, it <em>is</em> significant: Someone (the client) is actually going to
use what I am building for them. This is in contrast to academia, where I feel
that very few people read my work, let alone <em>use it</em> for anything. Making
something that others use, want, and care about feels great. Submitting
a research paper for publication and getting grumpy reviews back months later
does not.</p>

<p>Of course, the work I do as an IT consultant is not guaranteed to be used. The
client may change their mind and drop whatever project you are working on. But
since they ordered it and are paying good money for it, they are likely to want
it. In academia, conferences and journals are more important and prestigious,
the more submissions they reject.</p>

<a name="Feedback"></a>
<h2>Feedback</h2>

<p>So what if you instead look for purpose in the very short short term &ndash; hours
and days? In presenting a small new idea, or new section in a draft, and having
your collaborators see it and comment on it? Here, academia also disappointed
me. Getting feedback on my work was not always easy. Meetings could be fitted
into busy schedules a few times a month, and you would be lucky to get an email
reply without sending several reminders.</p>

<p>Unlike the inherent hardness of research, feedback in the short term is
somewhat within your own control because you can influence who you collaborate
with. But I still think my experience is fairly common.</p>

<p>In my new job, feedback is not something I get a few times per week &ndash; it is
something I get a few times per <em>hour</em>. Everybody&rsquo;s busy, but we take time to
help each other. In general I liked my colleagues at the university, but I feel
more like part of a team now than I have ever done as a PhD student.</p>

<p></p>

<p>To top it off, I also feel much more valued now because my time is treated with
respect. And of course it is: Every hour I am not doing billable work is missed
income for the company. And so, getting equipment, booking travels, getting
expenses refunded &mdash; everything is laughably easy compared to the university.</p>

<a name="Just.a.Job."></a>
<h2>Just a Job?</h2>

<p>One might object and say that travel booking and emails are irrelevant; that
work in academia is about grander things. Indeed, a faculty member who joined
the research group I was in complained that the PhD students were not dedicated
enough; that we just treated research as &ldquo;a job&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I think if you work on a topic that you care deeply about, then indeed you can
push on in spite of the slow progress. The feeling of ownership is a strong
motivator.</p>

<p>I was not strongly dedicated to my PhD research. When I couldn&rsquo;t get a PhD
position within my favored topic, I settled for what I could get right here,
right now, rather than looking for other options. In hindsight this was
a mistake. But I&rsquo;m not the only one who made the mistake. And perhaps academia
as an increasingly competitive institution could benefit from having work done
by &ldquo;research <a href="http://academia.stackexchange.com/a/35003">technicians</a>&rdquo; following the lead of a principal
investigator. At least, that could solve the current situation where far more
PhDs are produced than there are permanent positions available for.</p>

<p>But to keep us technicians happy doing what is partially someone elses
research, we need to be treated exactly as employees doing a regular &ldquo;job&rdquo;. And
to be motivated to do this job where real successes are occasional at best, the
working conditions should provide the day-to-day work satisfaction. And of
course no matter your motivation to tackle long-term research problems, dealing
with bureaucracy is no fun.</p>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<a name="How.to.Succeed"></a>
<h2>How to Succeed</h2>

<p>I do hope that the work I have done during my time working in research has made
a <a href="http://matt.might.net/articles/phd-school-in-pictures/">dent</a>, and I am thankful for the good experiences I have had. But
I would also like others considering doing a PhD to think about why they want
to do it. I thought that because I was a good bachelor and master&rsquo;s student,
I would be a good PhD student. And perhaps I was good for my co-authors, at
least I have been told that. But being a PhD student wasn&rsquo;t good for <em>me</em>.</p>

<p>I think, for academia to be good for you, three things are crucial:</p>

<ul>
<li>You should have a clear goal that is enough yours that you feel ownership of
it and therefore motivation. If your research project is too much somebody
else&rsquo;s idea, you may lose this important source of motivation.</li>
<li>When that is said, you should also work with people who agree with your goal,
and who you enjoy working with. If you collaborate with people you do not
strongly enjoy working with, you will miss regular morale boosts that help keep
you going in spite of the many failures you encounter.</li>
<li>You need to be either highly confident or <a href="http://jcs.biologists.org/content/121/11/1771">productively stupid</a>.</li>
</ul>


<p>Perhaps someday I will get an idea for a research project of my own and find
the right place to pursue it, but for now I&rsquo;ll happily develop &ldquo;mundane&rdquo;
business software that people use in the &ldquo;real world&rdquo;, as we used to say at the
university.</p>

<p><em>Update 2018-07-28: Fixed a typo.</em></p>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<p></li>
</ul>


<p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
