<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: music | Erik Ramsgaard Wognsen]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/blog/categories/music/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/"/>
  <updated>2021-06-26T14:29:40+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.erw.dk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Ramsgaard Wognsen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yousician "No tempo definitions found"]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/07/28/yousician-no-tempo-definitions-found/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-28T12:23:29+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/07/28/yousician-no-tempo-definitions-found</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p></p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/posts/yousician_no_tempo_definitions.png"></p>

<p>This summer my girlfriend and I started practicing piano with <a href="https://yousician.com">Yousician</a>,
which is a kind of gamified music tutor, that listens to your playing and gives
instant feedback. It contains songs of gradually increasing difficulty, plus
you can upload your own songs in the <a href="https://www.musicxml.com/">MusicXML</a> format.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Adding songs is very easy&rdquo;, claims <a href="https://yousician.zendesk.com/hc/en-us/articles/207247365-What-is-MusicXML-file-and-how-to-upload-it">the documentation</a>, but at our
first attempt we were met with this error message: <strong>&ldquo;No tempo definitions
found. Please specify tempo in the file.&rdquo;</strong> Googling the error message gave no
results at all, so hopefully this post will change that.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="left" src="/images/posts/musicxml_hello_world.gif"></p>

<p>MusicXML is an interchange format with files typically generated or exported
from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scorewriter">scorewriter programs</a>. But us being programmers, we looked
to the XML itself to fix the problem. To find a
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimal_Working_Example">minimal working example</a>, we tried the
<a href="https://www.musicxml.com/tutorial/hello-world/">MusicXML &ldquo;Hello World&rdquo;</a> example. Uploaded to Yousician, it gave the
same error message about the tempo missing.</p>

<a name="Solution"></a>
<h2>Solution</h2>

<p>If you control the scorewriter generating the MusicXML file and it allows
including tempo when you export, that should be the simple solution. Otherwise,
in the first <code>&lt;measure&gt;</code> element, add <code>&lt;sound tempo="120"/&gt;</code> with your desired
tempo in BPM:</p>

<pre><code class="xml">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?&gt;
&lt;!DOCTYPE score-partwise PUBLIC
    "-//Recordare//DTD MusicXML 3.1 Partwise//EN"
    "http://www.musicxml.org/dtds/partwise.dtd"&gt;
&lt;score-partwise version="3.1"&gt;
  &lt;part-list&gt; ... &lt;/part-list&gt;
  &lt;part id="P1"&gt;
    &lt;measure number="1"&gt;
      &lt;sound tempo="120"/&gt;  &lt;!-- ADD THIS ELEMENT --&gt;
      &lt;attributes&gt; ... &lt;/attributes&gt;
      &lt;note&gt; ... &lt;/note&gt;
      ...
</code></pre>

<a name="Details"></a>
<h2>Details</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think Yousician complies completely with the MusicXML standard.
Two things from the documentation of the <a href="https://usermanuals.musicxml.com/MusicXML/Content/CT-MusicXML-sound.htm">sound element</a>:</p>

<ul>
<li>The sound element [&hellip;] can stand alone within a part/measure [&hellip;]</li>
<li>If [the tempo is] 0, the sound-generating program should prompt the user at
the time of compiling a sound (MIDI) file.</li>
</ul>


<p>Yousician doesn&rsquo;t recognize a sound element in a part, only in a measure.
Second, if we see Yousician as a &ldquo;sound-generating program&rdquo; (it can play the
uploaded piece as a practice help, as well as play accompaniments), then it
doesn&rsquo;t satisfy the second part either. Tempo 0 will result in the message
&ldquo;Unfortunately something went wrong with file import.&rdquo; It would be better if it
prompted the user for a tempo, in case of both 0 and missing tempo.</p>

<p>However, tempo 1 was blindly accepted, resulting in a song slower than molasses
in January!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Roland Boutique Needs]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/02/25/what-roland-boutique-needs/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-25T16:46:09+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/02/25/what-roland-boutique-needs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p></p>

<p></p>

<p>Roland Boutique is a series of small form factor electronic music instruments.
The line debuted in 2015 with recreations of three iconic Roland 1980s synths.
I got the JP-08 which I wrote about <a href="/2017/06/25/roland-jp-08-review/">here</a>. Since then I&rsquo;ve been
watching the series grow with interest.</p>

<p>By now, the <a href="https://www.roland.com/us/promos/roland_boutique/">Boutique line</a> includes nine products recreating
Roland&rsquo;s back catalog: Five subtractive synths (JP-08, JU-06, JX-03, TB-03,
SH-01A), the VP-03 vocoder, the TR-08 and TR-09 drum machines, and finally the
D-05 &ldquo;linear synthesizer&rdquo; mixing sampling and synthesis.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/boutique_hero.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In 2017, Roland ventured outside their own history. Teaming up with Studio
Electronics, they released the Minimoog-inspired analog monosynth SE-02. Having
started down this path, they might make an FM (frequency modulation) synth.
Missing from the lineup is also perhaps a sampler/sample player/sample mangler?</p>

<p></p>

<p>That would at least match miniatures produced by other manufacturers in the
last few years. The very small and affordable Korg Volca series has the
straightforwardly named Beats, Bass, Keys, Sample, and FM. The first four
predated the original Boutique trio by 1-2 years, while the FM was released in
2016.</p>

<p>Swedish manufacturer Elektron also recently went small with the less toylike
&mdash; and less affordable &mdash; Digitakt sampler and Digitone FM-synth, with the
latter being announced just one month ago.</p>

<p>The 2015 Yamaha Reface series also has CS, DX, YC, and CP, doing synth, FM,
electric organ, and electric piano, respectively. And this leads me toward what
I would most like to see in the Roland Boutique series.</p>

<a name="Give.Me.a.Piano."></a>
<h2>Give Me a Piano!</h2>

<p></p>

<p>When you think of a digital piano, you are more likely to think of 88 weighted
keys than 25 non-weighted &ldquo;synth action&rdquo; minikeys. But one of the advantages of
the Boutiques is that they can both slot into the K-25m keyboard module and
perform as a sound module/desktop synth.</p>

<p>I would love to have a Roland Boutique piano with high-quality, natural,
acoustic piano sounds as well as high-quality electric pianos, organs, strings,
etc. I guess the model number would be in the form of FP-0x or RD-0x. I would
use such a Boutique piano module both as a sound module plugged into a MIDI
keyboard, and in the sofa as a plaything and/or compositional tool with the
K-25m keyboard attached.</p>

<p>The D-05 unfortunately does not fill this role. When the D-50 was launched in
1987 it certainly came closer than any analog synth to sounding like acoustic
instruments, but that doesn&rsquo;t mean it could actually pass for one. I went to my
local music store to try out the D-05, and while it does have a dozen patches
with &ldquo;piano&rdquo; in their name, none of them sound like an acoustic piano. It can
do electric pianos and organs, but overall I think the D-50/D-05 has a certain
80s/90s &ldquo;lo-fi&rdquo; sound. It excels at some things, but not acoustic piano.</p>

<p></p>

<a name="The.Panel"></a>
<h2>The Panel</h2>

<p>Some of the Boutiques have too many buttons crammed into the limited space on
the panel. This includes the <a href="/2017/06/25/roland-jp-08-review/">JP-08</a>, and judging from pictures, also
the TR-08, TR-09 and SE-02. Some have a more reasonable amount, such as the
JU-06, SH-01A, and VP-03. The D-05 doesn&rsquo;t have too many buttons per se, but it
faithfully recreates the dreary menu diving experience of the &ldquo;digital age&rdquo; (to
achieve more hands-on programming of the D-50/D-550/D-05, you need the enormous
PG-1000 programmer). But, digital pianos typically do not have a lot of
buttons. So what do I want on the Boutique piano panel?</p>

<p>I can think of a lot!</p>

<p></p>

<ul>
<li>Better speaker(s), perhaps even front facing</li>
<li>Dedicated octave up/down buttons</li>
<li>A good pitch/modulation stick (yes, electric organs can <a href="http://www.organforum.com/forums/showthread.php?22171-Pitch-bending-on-a-Hammond-A-mystery">pitch bend</a>)</li>
<li>Effects! Reverb, Leslie, Overdrive, Chorus, you name it.</li>
<li>Loop machine</li>
<li>Tape recorder</li>
<li>Sequencer</li>
<li>Arpeggiator</li>
<li>Chord memory</li>
<li>Scale/chord library (like a <a href="https://www.islainstruments.com/product/kordbot/">KordBot</a>?)</li>
</ul>


<p>Finally, such a module shouldn&rsquo;t be expensive. Unless it would have several of
the above features, it should be closer to 150 €/$ than to 400 €/$. It&rsquo;s
a ripoff that the K-25m keyboard is already 100 €/$.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Roland JP-08 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/06/25/roland-jp-08-review/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-25T17:06:23+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2017/06/25/roland-jp-08-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the early 1980s Roland produced a number of synthesizers that aged into
classics. The flagship Jupiter-8 is perhaps the most famous, used by electronic
artists such as Jean Michel Jarre, Depeche Mode, and Moby, as well as pop
artists like Michael Jackson, Madonna, and Abba.</p>

<p>Today, a used Jupiter-8 in good condition can cost more than a new top end
modern synthesizer, which is to say a lot. Luckily, in late 2015 Roland
released miniature versions of these classics, at relatively affordable prices.
Jupiter-8 became JP-08, and I got to own a little piece of music history.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/posts/boutiques.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Three originals (Juno-106, Jupiter-8, JX-3P) above the three new &lsquo;Boutique&rsquo; versions (JU-06, JP-08, JX-03)'><span class='caption-text'>Three originals (Juno-106, Jupiter-8, JX-3P) above the three new &lsquo;Boutique&rsquo; versions (JU-06, JP-08, JX-03)</span></span></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a bit late for a review, one and a half year after the release, but on the
other hand, the Jupiter-8 came out before I was born, so in comparison, the new
version is still very recent!</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Sound.in.a.Box"></a>
<h2>Sound in a Box</h2>

<p>One might ask why you need a box like this when you can generate the same
sounds in your computer. But the new Roland releases are in fact just software
in boxes &mdash; digital emulations of the original electronics. The point is that
a box with the right buttons, knobs, and sliders makes the experience of sound
exploration tactile and immediate.</p>

<p>Plus, in this age of multi purpose devices, there is just something fascinating
about a device that does just one thing, does it well, and doesn&rsquo;t let you
connect to Facebook.</p>

<div class="video-container">
<iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/C1zdcqoe8qg?feature=player_detailpage" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<a name="A.Small.Box"></a>
<h2>A Small Box</h2>

<p>Compared with the Jupiter-8, the JP-08 is tiny. It has the footprint of an A4
sheet of paper (somewhere between letter and legal for you North Americans),
and that&rsquo;s <em>with</em> the optional mini-keyboard attached. Since it can also be
powered from batteries, that means it&rsquo;s <em>portable</em>. You can bring it on trips,
to the park, or just the sofa. (Or bring it to bed, according to
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/junkiexlofficial">JunkieXL</a>!)</p>

<p>As part of the portability, the unit even has a built-in speaker so you can
play it without attaching a sound system or headphones. As practical as this
is, the speaker has no bass and a tendency to make the chassis rattle and
resonate. So I recommend skipping it altogether because that will sound much
better and make you appreciate the unit more.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/jp-08.jpg"></p>

<a name="Too.Small.a.Box"></a>
<h2>Too Small a Box</h2>

<p>The portable coolness however comes at a cost. To fit all of the controls of
the Jupiter-8 into such a small areal, they have been arranged in two rows.
Thus the sliders only have a throw of 1 cm, which means they require delicate
hand movements. This detracts from the overall hand-on experience, even though
they are usable with patience. The worst part is that it&rsquo;s very hard to sweep
the filter or pulse width smoothly.</p>

<p>However diminutive they are, controls dedicated to exactly one sound parameter
provide much of the immediacy of the overall experience. Unfortunately, the
auxiliary controls are tucked away under button combinations &mdash; a few
labelled, most not.</p>

<ul>
<li>The solo/unison/poly mode buttons have moved from dedicated buttons to
(labelled) combinations. This is acceptable because this is not something
you&rsquo;re likely to need to switch quickly.</li>
<li>The portamento settings also glided (pun intended) into a combination, with
the glide time set by sliding the modulation ribbon with the &lsquo;dual&rsquo; button
held down. This is a bit sad, since I could imaging tweaking the glide time
while playing.</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s worse for features native to the JP-08 such as delay effect parameters,
transpose, pitch bend range, MIDI channel, and especially keyboard octave
selection which is not easily done while playing the mini keyboard.</li>
<li>Also, the pitch bend and modulation features have devolved: The VCO/VCF
destination sliders and selectors have disappeared, and the crude ribbon
makes it difficult to do smooth or precise pitch bends.</li>
</ul>


<p></p>

<a name="Better.With.a.MIDI.Controller"></a>
<h2>Better With a MIDI Controller</h2>

<p>Many of the above problems can be solved by a separate MIDI controller:</p>

<ul>
<li>More octaves can be played directly, or at least octaves can be selected more
easily</li>
<li>Bigger knobs and sliders can be used to obtain smoother sweeps and precise
parameter input</li>
<li>The portamento glide time can be adjusted with a single knob or slider</li>
<li>The Jupiter-8 hold (sustain) feature, missing from the JP-08, can be mapped
to a button</li>
<li>The Jupiter-8 arpeggiator, also sadly missing from the JP-08, can be restored
with an arpeggiating controller such as the Arturia KeyStep</li>
</ul>


<p>Using a separate controller defeats the portability, but seen from the bright
side it just means you can switch between portability and better control.</p>

<a name="Signal.Routing"></a>
<h2>Signal Routing</h2>

<p>Also lost in the miniaturization were the little orange signal routing hints
scattered around the original Jupiter-8 panel:</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/posts/jupiter-8-panel.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Image used with permission from Nikolaus Riehm / Studio Repair'><span class='caption-text'>Image used with permission from Nikolaus Riehm / Studio Repair</span></span></p>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t know of these when I got my JP-08, so it was somewhat confusing. The
source mix knob was the first one I figured out: It mixes between the two only
sound sources &mdash; the two oscillators.</p>

<p>Then there&rsquo;s also routing between the two oscillators. VCO-1 has a &lsquo;cross mod&rsquo;
slider and VCO-2 has a &lsquo;sync&rsquo; switch. What&rsquo;s missing from the panel is the
direction of the routing (and even that routing is going on, if you don&rsquo;t know
what &lsquo;cross mod&rsquo; or &lsquo;sync&rsquo; means).</p>

<p>Cross modulation allows the pitch of VCO-1 to be affected by the pitch of
VCO-2, creating crazy bends or new timbres, depending on the frequency of
VCO-2. Sync allows VCO-2 to return to the start of its cycle at the frequency
of VCO-1, creating new timbres out of existing wave forms. After figuring out
the routing, the JP-08 made a lot more sense.</p>

<p>Perhaps most difficult is keeping track of what the two envelopes control.
ENV-1 can affect the pulse width of both oscillators, the frequency of either
or both oscillators, and the filter cutoff frequency. ENV-2 controls the VCA
and the filter frequency. The filter has a switch choosing which envelope
currently controls the filter.</p>

<p></p>

<a name="Docking.Looks.Better"></a>
<h2>Docking Looks Better</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/jp-08_k-25m.jpg"></p>

<p>The JP-08 itself is a sturdy metal panel on top of a plastic box. In its
unmounted form it appears somewhat naked. Adding the optional K-25m keyboard
module really helps completing the look of the device.</p>

<p>Before I got the keyboard module, the device looked somehow messy and
unfinished on my desk. Now, it makes me smile when I look at it. So I&rsquo;m happy
I got the keyboard module even though it is both expensive and only mediocre as
a keyboard. For use mainly with an external keyboard, the synth can also dock
in the keyboard-less, cheaper DK-01 dock.</p>

<p>Also, the metal surfaces have a satisfying ability to not pick up fingerprints.</p>

<a name="More.Like.JP-04"></a>
<h2>More Like JP-04</h2>

<p>The &lsquo;8&rsquo; in Jupiter-8 meant eight voices. The JP-08 only has four voices,
meaning only 4 notes can sound at the same time. This has irritated a lot of
people, including me. I mean, it&rsquo;s not that I play 9th chords all the time, but
Roland, did you really need to go for the minimum effort here, to try to sell
more boxes?</p>

<p>Roland happily claims that you can connect more units to increase the polyphony
by four each time. This is better than nothing, but it&rsquo;s also only partially
true. Because while you can play 4<em>n</em> notes <em>simultaneously</em>, there&rsquo;s still
voice stealing when you play notes sequentially (which is called&hellip; music&hellip;
you might have heard of it, Roland). That means that if you play a sound that
fades out gradually after lifting your finger from the key, that tail will be
cut off by the next note that starts, if no unused voice is available within
the first 4, <strong>not</strong> 4<em>n</em>, voices. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ejpw7GsyAGg">Here&rsquo;s</a> a demonstration.</p>

<p>Since the JP-08 is a (really good) digital simulation of the original analog
electronics, giving it eight voices shouldn&rsquo;t be that hard. Maybe you&rsquo;d need
a better processor, but compared with the costs of development and production,
that cost should be minimal. And you&rsquo;d have happier users. Then perhaps,
instead of buying another JP-08 and feeling like an idiot (which I chose not
to), I might have bought one of the other Boutiques.</p>

<p></p>

<a name="Patch.Selection"></a>
<h2>Patch Selection</h2>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/posts/jp-08-16.jpg' width='' height='' alt='The patch selection button rows of the JU-06 and the JP-08'><span class='caption-text'>The patch selection button rows of the JU-06 and the JP-08</span></span></p>

<p>The four voices bring another annoyance, which we need to take a step back to
understand. The Juno-106, JU-06, Jupiter-8, and JP-08 all have 16 buttons used
for patch selection. The JU-06 has eight bank buttons and eight patch buttons,
leading to a total of 64 patches. (The Juno-106, which I own, additionally has
a group selector multiplying everything by two for 128 patches in total.) On
the Juno-106 and JU-06, a single button press can switch the bank number (the
first digit) and the patch number (the last digit) independently (as well as
the group, on the Juno-106), which is very nice. (The Juno-106 also has a patch
increment pedal input, but I digress).</p>

<p>The JP-08 has eight patch number buttons and eight patch preset buttons.
Choosing one of the 64 patches always requires two consecutive presses of the
patch number buttons. A patch preset on the JP-08 is a layering of two patches
sounding simultaneously, and there are only eight of these. This is also how it
was on the Jupiter-8, except that a Jupiter-8 patch preset could also be
a left/right split between two patches instead of a layering.</p>

<p>A patch preset cuts the polyphony in half, since each note you play uses two
voices. Thus, with the JP-08 having only four voices and no split option, patch
presets are much less useful. You can&rsquo;t even play real chords! You can still
play leads and power chords with your layered sound. However, this could be
accomplished with the &lsquo;dual&rsquo; and &lsquo;upper/lower&rsquo; buttons without reserving eight
buttons for patch presets. Instead, it could have used the faster bank+patch
system like the Juno. (Or better yet, it could just have had eight voices.)</p>

<p>There is one final snafu with the 16 buttons and the way they relate to the
delay effect parameters (level, time, and feedback). Because changing the
parameters is difficult while playing, you are not likely to notice it, but
changing the delay time also flushes the delay buffer. However, if you control
the delay parameters with a knob on a MIDI controller, this becomes
embarrassingly obvious.</p>

<a name="In.Conclusion"></a>
<h2>In Conclusion</h2>

<p>The JP-08 is fun and sounds really good. But there are so many things that feel
like they could have been much better with small changes.</p>

<p>Eight voices, obviously. Then the sliders could have been much better with
a small increase in the height of the box. A small increase in width could have
allowed space for direct control of many more parameters. And an arpeggiator!
Not to mention full width keys or more mini keys. A normal pitch bend and mod
stick would also be great, but this might make the unit deeper.</p>

<p>Dimensions multiply, and the unit would quickly become much bigger and less
cute. But it would also be much better and less toy-like. The tiny Boutique
format just seems to go better with machines with fewer controls the Juno-106
or the VP-330.</p>

<p>Seeing newer Boutique releases having features that the JP-08 should have had
also feels like betrayal, after throwing money at a first generation Boutique
model. We&rsquo;re talking tempo synced LFO, tempo synced delay, sequencer note
slides, sequencer song mode, and sequencer <em>parameter locks</em>! It hurts, Roland.</p>

<p><em>Update 2019-08-28: Minor clarification.</em></p>

<p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Samba!]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2015/01/29/samba/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-29T10:42:32+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2015/01/29/samba</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p></p>

<p>After spending the fall of 2014 doing research in the Netherlands, I have moved
home to Aalborg, Denmark and returned to the samba group <a href="https://www.facebook.com/SambaskolenPocoLoco">Poco Loco</a>.
The group has dancers and percussionists; I&rsquo;m one of the latter. Starting again
after my half-year break reminded me of how it was when I first started playing
samba. While you enjoy the video of the group here, I&rsquo;ll geek out on the
drumming below.</p>

<div class="video-container">
<iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/ogQt9G1zEN8?feature=player_detailpage" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>




<!-- more -->


<p>In my gymnasium (high school) years, I played the drum kit, mostly rock music.
On the drum kit, you play with both hands and both feet simultaneously, so
coming from this background, I thought playing a single drum at a time should
be fairly easy. It turns out it&rsquo;s not!</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/35/Tamborim.JPG">https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/35/Tamborim.JPG</a>&#8217; width=&#8217;320&#8217; height=&#8217;240&#8217; alt=&#8217;<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Tamborim.JPG#mediaviewer/File:Tamborim.JPG">Tamborim</a> by <a href="//commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Alno">Alno</a> / <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">CC BY-SA 3.0</a>&#8217;><span class='caption-text'><a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Tamborim.JPG#mediaviewer/File:Tamborim.JPG">Tamborim</a> by <a href="//commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Alno">Alno</a> / <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">CC BY-SA 3.0</a></span></span>
</p>

<p>For example, there&rsquo;s the tiny <em>tamborim</em> which, despite its modest size (6&#8221;
&approx; 15 cm), contributes a lot to the character of the sound of a samba
<em>bateria</em>. Its basic pattern plays every 16th note, indefinitely, with one
hand. That requires good technique, first to be able to play at high speed at
all, then to keep going. (I hope I&rsquo;ll be able to do it some day!)</p>

<p>The <em>caixa</em> (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snare_drum">snare drum</a>) also plays every 16th note in the basic
pattern. Unlike with the tamborim, you can alternate the hands. But like the
tamborim, the rhythm is played with &ldquo;samba swing&rdquo; which gives an eager,
energetic feeling. It takes a lot of time readjust when your musical background
is rock-based. (You can hear the difference <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FhiID-40EkY">in this video</a>, where
he switches between exaggerated, medium, and no swing.)</p>

<p></p>

<p>The <em>repinique</em> is a drum that can make different sounds depending on how it&rsquo;s
struck. Below is a video of a guy showing how it&rsquo;s played. The drum is used
by the leader to cue the breaks and perform calls that the rest of the bateria
answers. So it has a very important role. But playing it involves slapping your
hand into its metal rim 100-150 times per minute. And it sports tuning rods
that are always available for said hand to impale itself on. As one of my
bandmates said: You are not initiated until you have bled on your drum!</p>

<div class="video-container">
<iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/xwxyskWxoWU?feature=player_detailpage" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>




<!--
I usually play the *surdo*

The rhythms must be played with "swing" to get the right, energetic feeling. 

surdos, chocalho
This is the reason I joined the group in the first place
-->


<p>Samba is hard, but it&rsquo;s great. Both when we practice and when we perform on the
street or on a stage. The driving, unending rhythm and the feeling of unity in
a group of people or a whole carnival are just awe-inspiring.</p>

<p>The atmosphere is also happy and relaxed. Mistakes are made, but you just play
on. It&rsquo;s more important to keep going than to play perfectly (there&rsquo;s an
important life lesson in that!)</p>

<p>I was also surprised when I returned from my half year break. I could no longer
consciously remember the many breaks and call/response sequences. But when the
leader played the calls, my hands automatically responded. It&rsquo;s like riding
a bike &ndash; you can do it, but you can&rsquo;t explain how.</p>

<p>Fun facts:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Samba swing is in a way the opposite of jazz swing. Jazz swing/shuffle is
&ldquo;lazy&rdquo; and delays off-beat notes. Samba swing is &ldquo;eager&rdquo; and plays some of
the notes between the main beats too early.</p></li>
<li><p>You cannot keep time with your feet because you will be walking in a parade
at speeds that are likely independent of the music.</p></li>
<li><p>I still geek out and write down <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drum_tablature">drum tabs</a> to learn and understand
new sequences, but after that the automated learning quickly takes over. Most
people in our group just learn by repetition, without writing it down.</p></li>
<li><p>Earlier in my life, the primary meaning of &ldquo;samba&rdquo; was a piece of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samba_%28software%29">networking software</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>I have no idea why our group is called Poco Loco (a bit crazy) in Spanish,
when samba is Brazilian. I guess even the name is a bit crazy!</p></li>
</ul>


<p>If you live near Aalborg, and find this all interesting, we could sure use
a few more drummers (also dancers!). All you need is the interest (and at least
a hint of a sense of rhythm). See the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/SambaskolenPocoLoco">facebook page</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
