<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: android | Erik Ramsgaard Wognsen]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/blog/categories/android/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/"/>
  <updated>2022-12-15T21:30:13+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.erw.dk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Ramsgaard Wognsen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AAWireless First Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2022/06/04/aawireless-first-impressions/"/>
    <updated>2022-06-04T21:20:37+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2022/06/04/aawireless-first-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/posts/aawireless.jpg" width="375" title="Picture shows a car infotainment screen with Google Maps as well as the small AAWireless device plugged in to the car&rsquo;s USB port" ></p>

<p>My <a href="/2021/05/02/hyundai-ioniq-electric/">car</a> supports Android Auto which lets me connect my smartphone and
use the phone&rsquo;s apps on the car&rsquo;s infotainment system including touchscreen,
speakers and microphone. Examples include Google Maps for navigation and
Spotify for music, as well as Google Assistant voice commands.</p>

<p>It normally requires a wired USB connection between phone and car, but
<a href="https://www.aawireless.io/">AAWireless</a> is a device that acts as a wireless bridge between
phone and car while the device stays plugged in to the car, so your phone can
stay in your pocket or bag. I&rsquo;m happy so say it works well so far.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>With the product being crowdfunded, and just being a consumer electronic
product in general, I was prepared for some problems. To my pleasant surprise,
the product Just Works for me. After the initial Bluetooth pairing, the device
connects quickly when I turn the car on, and the car&rsquo;s touchscreen is
responsive. I did not use the accompanying <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=app.aawireless">app</a> to configure or update
the device, as it was not necessary for me, and because I didn&rsquo;t want the app
to update the device&rsquo;s firmware, as some reviews complained about problems with
a recent version of the firmware.</p>

<p>The AAWireless device uses less than 1&nbsp;W of power from the wired USB
connection which is nice. I don&rsquo;t know how the phone&rsquo;s power consumption is
affected and I have not yet tried longer trips with the AAWireless. But based
on my limited experience with it, I&rsquo;m happy with the purchase.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Assistant Currently Unavailable for This Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2019/05/31/google-assistant-currently-unavailable-for-this-language/"/>
    <updated>2019-05-31T11:28:46+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2019/05/31/google-assistant-currently-unavailable-for-this-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One day I said &ldquo;Hey Google&rdquo; and my <a href="/2017/11/19/google-pixel-2-first-impressions/">Pixel</a> didn&rsquo;t respond. After a few
more unsuccessful tries I went into the settings and saw that Voice Match &mdash;
the feature that lets you activate Google Assistant by voice &mdash; &ldquo;is currently
unavailable for this language&rdquo;. I found this strange since the language was set
to <strong>English</strong>, and it used to work. Now, neither US nor UK English, nor
Danish, could make it work.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/google_assistant_voice_match_unavailable.png"></p>

<p>I googled the problem and found lots of tips, but none of them worked. Later
I found a solution, that I&rsquo;ll post here in the hopes of helping someone else.</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Toward.The.Solution"></a>
<h2>Toward The Solution</h2>

<p>Before I found the solution I checked several things after googling the
problem. I confirmed that the microphone did work in other apps. In fact, it
even worked in the Google app itself when activated by touch instead of voice.
I didn&rsquo;t have other voice assistants installed that could somehow conflict with
Google Assistant. I couldn&rsquo;t retrain the voice model as some recommended since
the whole Voice Match feature was unavailable. I tried rebooting, uninstalling
Google app updates, clearing its cache, reinstalling the updates, rebooting
some more, all to no avail.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/posts/google_assistant_android_language_preferences.png"></p>

<p>Besides the system Voice settings&#8217; language preferences, the Google app&rsquo;s
Assistant settings also have language preferences. Here, I also had English
(tried both US and UK), so that couldn&rsquo;t be the unsupported language either.
Finally I went to the system settings&#8217; main language preferences, which are
a <em>third</em> language setting in the same Google/Android ecosystem. My main
language was set to &ldquo;English (Denmark)&rdquo;.</p>

<a name="Solution"></a>
<h2>Solution</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not enough to use a supported language, the regional variant also has to
be supported and set in the correct one out of three sets of language
preferences. &ldquo;English (Denmark)&rdquo; doesn&rsquo;t work, but setting the main system
language preferences&#8217; top or only language to &ldquo;English (United States)&rdquo; does.
Presumably English from other primarily English-speaking regions works as well.</p>

<p><strong>After changing my <em>main</em> system language to &ldquo;English (United States)&rdquo;
I could now activate Voice Match a.k.a. &ldquo;OK Google&rdquo;/&ldquo;Hey Google&rdquo;.</strong></p>

<a name="Problems"></a>
<h2>Problems</h2>

<p>The above is more of a hack than an actual solution, because it prevents me
from using Danish regional (time, date, number, etc.) formats on Android while
using Voice Match.</p>

<p>When I got my Pixel 2 I had set it myself to &ldquo;English (United States)&rdquo;. This
worked fine until I later installed Google Fit and wanted its calendar view to
use Monday as the first day of the week, rather than Sunday. The app didn&rsquo;t
have it&rsquo;s own setting for this, but it worked after I changed the main system
language to &ldquo;English (Denmark)&rdquo;. I don&rsquo;t use Google Assistant every day, so
when &ldquo;Hey Google&rdquo; later didn&rsquo;t work, I didn&rsquo;t immediately make the connection
to the region change.</p>

<p>If the original error message had been &ldquo;This feature is currently unavailable
for <em>English (Denmark)</em>&rdquo;, rather than the generic &ldquo;this language&rdquo;, it would
have been much easier to fix. Even better, Android should use the Voice
settings&#8217; language as the voice language. Or the Assistant settings&#8217; language
as the assistant language. Or stop having so many language settings! Or let
Voice Match fall back to a supported language variant if the chosen one is
unsupported.</p>

<a name="More.Problems"></a>
<h2>More Problems</h2>

<p>Speaking of Google Assistant problems, I just <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2019/may/28/a-white-collar-sweatshop-google-assistant-contractors-allege-wage-theft">read</a> that many of the
linguists that helped create Google Assistant were treated with mistrust and
being paid less than 20% of what permanent staff makes, while also expected to
do unlogged overtime. I appreciate that not all skills are in equal demand, and
therefore pay, but that&rsquo;s no excuse to treat people with a lack of respect <em>on
top of</em> low pay and inferior health insurance. I think Google should choose to
treat <em>all</em> its workers with dignity. #DontBeEvil</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Android 9 Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/11/06/android-9-impressions/"/>
    <updated>2018-11-06T08:43:18+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/11/06/android-9-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/posts/android9_homescreen.png"></p>

<p>Last year I got the <a href="/2017/11/19/google-pixel-2-first-impressions/">Google Pixel 2</a> smartphone to try the pure Android
experience. It took a bit of time to get used to but I have come to appreciate
its simplicity and cleanness. But the main purpose was getting OS updates
directly from Google, without waiting for the OEMs. Besides monthly security
updates, the new Android 9 came in August. Here are my impressions after two
months, including Gesture Navigation, the Overview, Adaptive Battery, and
Digital Wellbeing, as well as my thoughts on the Pixel 2 after a year.</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Pixel.2.a.Year.Later"></a>
<h2>Pixel 2 a Year Later</h2>

<p>The two things I initially liked best about the Pixel 2 are still the best: The
speed and the screen. The speed and responsiveness of the device is still
amazing one year and OS update later. This is what using a computer &mdash; because
a smartphone is a computer &mdash; in 2018 should feel like. (Running Windows 10 on
a laptop does, incidentally, not feel like 2018.)</p>

<p>The brightness range of the screen is also still great. Not perfect, but
I certainly find myself needing <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.haxor">Screen Filter</a> less often than
before I got an OLED screen. The always-on screen feature that shows the time
and notifications when the screen is &ldquo;off&rdquo; was also neat at first, but I&rsquo;ve
since grown so accustomed to it that a device that doesn&rsquo;t have it now feels
antiquated. Similarly, the fingerprint sensor on the back was ok at first but
now makes the phone feel like a natural extension of my hand
(<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/shortcuts/2018/oct/30/get-a-grip-are-smartphones-ruining-our-manual-dexterity">for better or worse</a>).
And unlike the <a href="https://youtu.be/hrHf6XQpmk0?t=94">in-screen fingerprint sensor</a> of the new OnePlus 6T, the
traditional sensor does not blind you with its bright light at night.</p>

<p>The camera and speakers are still great, and I can still get through the day
with battery left to spare. To mention a few negatives, the volume rocker is
still too stiff, and I&rsquo;ve disabled the Active Edge squeeze feature completely
as it was more likely to be activated accidentally than when I actually needed
it.</p>

<a name="Android.9"></a>
<h2>Android 9</h2>

<p>Android 9 was released in August. Installing the update was extremely fast,
just like booting up the Pixel 2 was when I first turned it on a year ago.
Again, this feels like 2018. Other improvements made me wonder why they weren&rsquo;t
made sooner. The sound volume control now defaults to controlling media volume
instead of ringer volume, also when no media is playing. Now you can lower the
volume <em>before</em> your embarrassing video starts playing. Simple yet great.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='/images/posts/android9_rotate_button.png' width='497' height='138' alt='The rotate button works with and without gesture navigation enabled.'><span class='caption-text'>The rotate button works with and without gesture navigation enabled.</span></span></p>

<p>Another such feature is the screen rotation button. I prefer having screen
auto-rotate disabled so I can keep reading while lying on my side in bed or in
the sofa. But for the few times I did want the screen to rotate, it was
annoying to have to enable the auto-rotate feature and then disable it later
after use. Now in Android 9, if auto-rotate is disabled but the phone senses
it&rsquo;s been rotated, a little rotate button appears that let&rsquo;s you rotate the
screen, once, without messing with the general auto-rotate setting. If you
ignore it, the button goes away after some seconds. Made me wonder why this
wasn&rsquo;t built in many years ago.</p>

<a name="App.Switching.and.Overview"></a>
<h2>App Switching and Overview</h2>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/posts/android9_overview.png' width='' height='' alt='The Overview/app switching screen of Android 9'><span class='caption-text'>The Overview/app switching screen of Android 9</span></span></p>

<p>As seen in the picture with the rotate button above, there are now two
different ways to navigate around Android 9. The new gesture navigation with
the &ldquo;pill&rdquo; button, as well as the traditional navigation bar.</p>

<p>In the traditional mode, the &ldquo;Overview button&rdquo; (the square) opens the Overview
where you can see recently used apps and switch to them. A second press of the
Overview button switches to the next most recently used app. This can be done
quickly, i.e., double tapping the Overview button to switch to the next most
recently used app.</p>

<p>Using gesture navigation, swiping up from the pill (or in fact anywhere on the
bottom of the screen) opens the Overview, while instead dragging the pill to
the right scrolls through recently used apps until you release it.</p>

<p>The Overview mode, besides app switching, lets you select and copy text, even
from apps that don&rsquo;t allow this during normal usage, which is a great feature.
It&rsquo;s also from the Overview that apps can be sent to split screen mode.</p>

<a name="To.Gesture.or.Not.to.Gesture"></a>
<h2>To Gesture or Not to Gesture</h2>

<p>Since I got the Pixel 2 last year, I have loved double tapping the Overview
button, so it was not like I desperately wanted a different way of navigating.
Happily, upgrading to Android 9 didn&rsquo;t force the switch to the new gesture
navigation. In fact, I had to enable it myself, by activating the &ldquo;Swipe up on
Home button&rdquo; gesture.</p>

<p>Swiping up is very smooth, and while you do it, the active app shrinks down to
the rectangle/preview shown in the Overview. If you continue swiping up, the
app drawer opens. In the Overview you can scroll sideways between the previews,
and to select one, you can tap it, or swipe it back down and out to full
screen. This part works well.</p>

<p>The sideways drag feature is a mixed bag. It&rsquo;s good for switching to the
previous app with a short, quick sideways swipe &mdash; even simpler than the old
double tap. If you hold and drag further, the sideways scroll snaps to each app
with satisfying haptic feedback, which is even better than the regular
Overview. But. The problem with the sideways drag is that in one-handed
operation, it invariably leads your thumb into an uncomfortable position.</p>

<p>This is why I prefer the short sideways swipe for the previous app and swiping
up to the Overview if I want to go further back. But this leads to a mental
overhead: Now I stop and think before gesturing. The old Overview button didn&rsquo;t
have this problem: Every switch starts with a press of the button. Gesture
navigation <em>looks</em> fancy, but I have to say my thumb prefers the old way.</p>

<p></li>
</ul>


<a name="Adaptive.Battery"></a>
<h2>Adaptive Battery</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/posts/android9_adaptive_battery.png"></p>

<p>According to android.com, &ldquo;Adaptive Battery learns how you like to use your
phone, so the apps and services you don&rsquo;t use as much aren&rsquo;t a battery drain&rdquo;.
Unlike gesture navigation, this feature was enabled automatically when
I upgraded.</p>

<p>When I travel for work, I book a taxi to the airport ahead of time, and in the
early morning on my travel day, the app notifies me when the taxi is ready to
pick me up. Except this didn&rsquo;t happen after I had upgraded to Android 9. In the
same vein, the airline app notifies me when the online check-in opens. Didn&rsquo;t
happen either. So mine and Android&rsquo;s ideas of &ldquo;using an app&rdquo; are not the same.
I also use the Dropbox app to upload my photos in the background &mdash; also
delayed from the &ldquo;optimization&rdquo;. Luckily, you can stop individual apps from
being optimized. On the other hand, I guess this feature also optimizes tons of
apps that I don&rsquo;t need to run in the background. So it&rsquo;s probably fine after
you have set up your exclusions.</p>

<a name="Digital.Wellbeing"></a>
<h2>Digital Wellbeing</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/posts/android9_digital_wellbeing.png"></p>

<p>Finally, Android 9 brings the <a href="https://wellbeing.google/">Digital Wellbeing</a> feature which shows you
how much you use your smartphone, and offers you ways to reduce interruptions
and screen time.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s interesting to see how much I use my smartphone. The picture to the right
is from one of the aforementioned travel days, which brings my usage a bit
higher than usual. But besides the statistics I don&rsquo;t feel that the feature
brings me much. It helps reduce the number of notifications, but I have already
disabled the most nagging notifications myself, including all email
notifications (try it, it&rsquo;s great for your sanity).</p>

<p>It allows you to set time limits for app use, but I have already uninstalled my
time wasters such as the Facebook app. The &ldquo;Wind Down&rdquo; feature helps you go to
bed by enabling Do Not Disturb mode and turning the screen grayscale. I already
have DND and Night Light on a schedule. The grayscale mode is kinda cool, but
I often end up disabling it to see what I&rsquo;m doing.</p>

<p>I think Digital Wellbeing is a good idea, but I already knew that, it seems.
But I could see how many people could benefit from easy access to all these
settings to nudge them into reclaiming a bit of non-phone time.</p>

<p>All in all, Android 9 feels like evolution rather than revolution, but that&rsquo;s
fair. Smartphones themselves were a revolution that started only around ten
years ago, even though they have now invaded our lives. But we might start
seeing some bigger changes to the smartphone market already when next years
<a href="https://www.phonearena.com/news/LG-foldable-phone-announcement-date_id110590">folds around</a>.</p>

<p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Pixel 2 - First Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/11/19/google-pixel-2-first-impressions/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-19T15:58:03+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2017/11/19/google-pixel-2-first-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just bought a new smartphone. After three HTC models (Desire Z, One X, One
M8) I decided to go for the pure Android experience with a Google Pixel 2 (I
went with the Clearly White, non-XL version). Here are my thoughts after two
weeks.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/pixel2.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The first thing I noticed was the <strong>speed</strong>. Booting it up for the first time
took what I remember as mere seconds. Coming from a 3.5 year old smartphone,
this was a big improvement. Not so relevant on a daily basis, but a good first
impression. But the Pixel 2 also feels very snappy in use, especially compared
with my old smartphone burdened by the newest, hungriest apps.</p>

<p>The second great thing I noticed is the <strong>screen</strong>. It looks fine, but what I&rsquo;m
really happy about is its ability to reduce the brightness to a fairly low
level so I don&rsquo;t get blinded in low light conditions. I guess older OLED
smartphones might have been able to do the same, but it&rsquo;s certainly the first
smartphone I have owned where I have been satisfied with the low brightness
level. The automatic brightness adjustment is also excellent. On top of that,
the Night Light feature is great. As a <a href="http://jonls.dk/redshift/">Redshift</a> (similar to
<a href="https://justgetflux.com/">f.lux</a>) user I was happy to see it built in to the OS.</p>

<p>Third, the <strong>battery</strong> life is good. As a test, I skipped charging one night,
and just used it regularly two days in a row. When I went to bed the second
night, it still had 19% left. And that&rsquo;s even with two battery-eating always-on
features enabled: Ambient display (showing date, time, and notification icons)
and Now Playing (which does <em>offline</em> analysis of ambient sound to identify
playing songs).</p>

<a name="The.Stuff.People.Talk.About"></a>
<h2>The Stuff People Talk About</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/posts/pixel2front.jpg" width="370"></p>

<p>On-device song identification is pretty cool. Another hypey feature is the
&ldquo;Active Edge&rdquo; which let&rsquo;s you <strong>squeeze</strong> the sides of the phone to activate
Google Assistant. It&rsquo;s fun to play with, but not very useful in my opinion.
I have to shift the phone in my hand to squeeze the right area, and half of the
time, the &ldquo;meat&rdquo; of the base of my thumb folds up and taps something unwanted
on the screen. So it&rsquo;s better to just launch Assistant the regular way: by long
pressing the home button.</p>

<p>In other news, the <strong>bezels</strong> have taken flak for being too large for 2017. And
I guess they are. On the plus side, I can comfortably reach both top and bottom
of the screen with my thumb, and they have room for front-facing stereo
speakers.</p>

<p>They didn&rsquo;t leave room for a <strong>headphone jack</strong>, though. The phone&rsquo;s packaging
included a (somewhat bulky) converter but no wired USB C headphones &mdash; to get
more people to look at the <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=Pixel+Buds">Pixel Buds</a>, I guess.</p>

<p>Finally, the Pixel 2&rsquo;s <strong>camera</strong> is supposedly really, really good. I don&rsquo;t
disagree so far, but I&rsquo;ll know more when I get around to trying it somewhere
more picturesque than my desk.</p>

<a name="Small.Annoyances"></a>
<h2>Small Annoyances</h2>

<p>Overall, I&rsquo;m fairly satisfied with the Pixel 2. But there are a few small
annoyances:</p>

<ul>
<li>No support for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miracast">Miracast</a> - only Chromecast</li>
<li>The Pixel 2 is not officially for sale in Denmark, which means that the
<a href="https://store.google.com/product/pixel_2">Google Store</a> webpage will not even acknowledge that the Pixel 2 or
its accessories exist, if you access it from Denmark without tricks</li>
<li>The ambient display, which is white text on a black background, <em>strobes</em>,
which you can see when you move the phone around</li>
<li>Dust and debris gets stuck in the speaker grills
<span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/posts/android8_notification_collapse.png' width='' height='' alt='Areas for expanding/collapsing notifications'><span class='caption-text'>Areas for expanding/collapsing notifications</span></span></li>
<li>The device/screen vibrates when the speakers are playing, which can be felt
in the 120&ndash;700 Hz range</li>
<li>The power button and volume rocker require too much pressure to press</li>
<li>Most Android 8 notifications can be expanded/collapsed, to which a large
part of their surface is reserved. This means that unlike older Android
notifications, I kinda have to aim when I tap them.</li>
<li>Going for pure Android is not as cool as I had imagined, and the default
launcher and dialler are disappointing</li>
<li>Since the bezels are there anyway, a fingerprint reader on the front would be
nice, for those times I want to use the phone flat on the table</li>
</ul>


<p>Come to think of it, many of these feel like a step down from my HTC One M8.
But they&rsquo;re not a big problem compared to the improvements in speed, screen
blackness, camera, and battery, all in a thinner, lighter body.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll get to see over the coming months and years if the &ldquo;full Google
experience&rdquo; is worth the price. At least I should be getting updates quickly
for <a href="https://www.androidauthority.com/google-pixel-2-xl-update-804779/">three years</a>, which is better than many OEMs. I just hope the
Pixel 2 will stay snappy as the updates come.</p>

<p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
