<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: keyboards | Erik Ramsgaard Wognsen]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/blog/categories/keyboards/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/"/>
  <updated>2021-10-02T22:55:02+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.erw.dk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Ramsgaard Wognsen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Weird Keyboard]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2018/04/14/my-weird-keyboard/"/>
    <updated>2018-04-14T16:57:10+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2018/04/14/my-weird-keyboard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I use a weird computer keyboard: The <a href="https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/shop/advantage2/">Kinesis Advantage</a>.
It&rsquo;s a concave, columnar, split, tented, mechanical keyboard with thumb keys.
It&rsquo;s very comfortable and much better than anything Logitech or Microsoft have
ever labeled ergonomic.</p>

<p></p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/kinesis_advantage2.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Ergonomic.Features"></a>
<h2>Ergonomic Features</h2>

<p><strong>Columnar</strong> means that the keys are laid out in straight columns, so you don&rsquo;t
have to bend your fingers sideways as you curl and extend them &mdash; unlike on
a standard, staggered keyboard, where especially the left hand fingers need to
move unnaturally. The <strong>split</strong> also helps avoiding sideways bends for the
wrists. For more details, see the illustration of the <a href="https://www.trulyergonomic.com/store/unique-symmetric-columnar-key-arrangement--truly-ergonomic-mechanical-keyboard--orthogonal-matrix-non-staggered">Truly Ergonomic
keyboard</a> (which I haven&rsquo;t tried (yet)).</p>

<p><strong>Tented</strong> means that the thumb side of each hand sits higher than the pinky
side. This gives the wrists a more natural rotation. The Advantage only tilts
20 degrees &mdash; other keyboards such as the
<a href="https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/shop/freestyle2-for-pc-us/">Kinesis Freestyle</a> and the <a href="http://safetype.com">SafeType</a> can tent
(up to) 90 degrees (while <a href="https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/frreestyle2-ascent-90-1.jpg">looking</a> even less
conventional than the Advantage).</p>

<p>The <strong>thumb key</strong> clusters make more keys reachable without moving the hand
away from its home position, and it offloads Backspace and Enter from the
overworked right pinky and onto the stronger thumbs.</p>

<p>The <strong>mechanical</strong> keyswitches (Cherry MX brown or red) register the keypress
when the key is halfway depressed (2 out of 4 millimeters). This is opposed to
standard rubber dome keyboards that require you to bottom out &mdash; fully depress
the key until the finger is jolted to a stop.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/kinesis_advantage2_side.jpg"></p>

<p>The best feature of the Advantage is the <strong>concave</strong> keywells: The scooped-out
parts of the keyboard where the alphanumeric keys reside. They serve several
purposes:</p>

<ul>
<li>As you curl and extend your fingers, the keys remain at the same distance
from your fingertips, so you don&rsquo;t need to stretch your fingers much to
reach. This also makes it easy to access all five (!) rows of keys.</li>
<li>The same happens when you move your index finger to the side (like T, G, B),
reducing sideways-twisting finger motions.</li>
<li>The depths of the columns are matched with the corresponding fingers, so they
all rest naturally in the home position.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Switching"></a>
<h2>Switching</h2>

<p>I got my first Kinesis Advantage in 2011. As I recall, it only took a few days
to adapt to this weird keyboard. The best part is that I can still switch
effortlessly between the Advantage and standard, flat, staggered keyboards. Not
that I particularly enjoy it, but I can do it, which is very practical for
traveling. The Advantage is actually narrower than a standard 104/105-key
keyboard, but it&rsquo;s bigger in the two other dimensions and therefore not easy to
transport.</p>

<p>However, the physical shape of my keyboard is not the only weird thing about my
typing. The <em>logical</em> layout I use &mdash; <a href="/2015/02/27/4-years-with-colemak/">Colemak</a> &mdash; is weird too.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/kinesis_advantage_custom_keycaps_right.jpg"></p>

<p>Switching logical layout is much harder for me than switching physical layout.
Even though the Advantage is firmware remappable, I set my logical layout in
the computer OS, so I will keep the logical layout for all keyboards, including
the laptop keyboard.</p>

<p>Some people retain their QWERTY touch typing skills while learning an
alternative layout by associating logical layout with physical keyboard, e.g.,
typing Colemak on the Advantage and QWERTY on standard keyboards. And I did
actually get the Advantage the same year I switched to Colemak, but I much
prefer typing Colemak on my laptop while traveling over maintaining my QWERTY
skills.</p>

<a name="Legends"></a>
<h2>Legends</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not really necessary have Colemak legends on the keys, but I did get a set
of custom keycaps made by <a href="http://www.wasdkeyboards.com/">WASD keyboards</a> for one of my two Advantages
&mdash; complete with my Danish variation of Colemak &mdash; as shown in the images
above and below. It&rsquo;s mostly for show, because the legends are not necessary
for touch typing, and the Advantage is not so good anyway for one-handed use
where the legends might be relevant.</p>

<p>In fact, hunt-and-peck typing is for some reason easier for me with QWERTY
legends, even while I type Colemak. My eyes are more used to the common QWERTY
layout, I guess. I just know that pressing the QWERTY &rsquo;T&#8217; key produces a &lsquo;G&rsquo; in
Colemak. If I look down and the key shows a &lsquo;G&rsquo;, my eyes get confused, even
though my fingers knows exactly where to press to get the &lsquo;G&rsquo; while touch
typing.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/kinesis_advantage_custom_keycaps_left.jpg"></p>

<a name="Downsides"></a>
<h2>Downsides</h2>

<p>The Advantage is not great for everything. Split keyboards are not good for the
occasional one-handed use (e.g., while holding a drink, phone, piece of paper).</p>

<p>The Advantage is not the best for gaming either. The arrow keys are spread on
both sides of the split which is fine for two-handed office and programming
use, but not ideal for gaming. The key positions are matched to finger lengths,
so the WASD keys will not work well with the normal WASD-fingers. ESDF should
be perfect, though.</p>

<p>For a long time, the typical complaint of the Advantage was the low quality of
the rubber F-keys. In 2016, the Advantage2 was launched, with Cherry ML
switches instead of rubber dome F-keys, and more programming options. This is
the product I link to in the top of the post because the product page for the
old version seems to be gone. I haven&rsquo;t tried it, but I can only imagine it&rsquo;s
an improvement.</p>

<p>Another problem partially solved by time is the built-in combined USB hub and
PS/2-to-USB converter. It &mdash; and the whole keyboard with it &mdash; didn&rsquo;t work
with Windows 7. Kinesis did sell a cable conversion kit to work around this,
but I went DIY and installed a PS/2-to-USB adapter myself, bypassing the
problematic USB hub, on my &ldquo;work&rdquo; board.</p>

<p>My &ldquo;home&rdquo; board always worked fine with Linux (and Windows 10), but it&rsquo;s also
not recognized by the BIOS of my desktop computer&rsquo;s motherboard. A smaller
problem but I&rsquo;m considering giving this board a USB hubectomy as well. The
Advantage2 has supposedly also solved this problem.</p>

<p>There are a few problems with the Advantage, but they are minor compared to the
Advantage (heh) of using an extremely comfortable keyboard for my 10+ daily
hours of computer usage.</p>

<a name="Key.Remapping"></a>
<h2>Key Remapping</h2>

<p>My remaining complaints were solved with easy firmware remapping, which is in
fact just a testament to the Advantage&rsquo;s flexibility:</p>

<ul>
<li>I swapped Space and Backspace because I have for some reason always used my
left hand&rsquo;s thumb for Space.</li>
<li>I use the Alt+Tab shortcut all the time, so I moved the Alt key closer to my
thumb in the left thumb cluster.</li>
<li>I made the key above Tab work as an Escape key.</li>
<li>I made the key below Tab work as a Control key because that&rsquo;s how control
freaks control.</li>
<li>I put Down to the left of Up because that&rsquo;s how Vim users roll.</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Update 2018-11-06: Minor clarifications.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[4 Years with Colemak]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2015/02/27/4-years-with-colemak/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-27T13:38:30+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2015/02/27/4-years-with-colemak</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p></p></blockquote>

<p>As a young computer user I felt that something was wrong with the keyboard.
Like Morpheus says to Neo when they first meet:</p>

<blockquote><p>What you know you can&rsquo;t explain. But you feel it. You&rsquo;ve felt it your entire
life. That there&rsquo;s something wrong with the world. You don&rsquo;t know what it is
but it&rsquo;s there, like a splinter in your mind driving you mad. It is this
feeling that has brought you to me. Do you know what I&rsquo;m talking about?</p></blockquote>

<p>QWERTY.</p>

<p>Touch typing on the QWERTY keyboard layout is wrong. You can do it every day,
all day, but there&rsquo;s something wrong with it. Today, four years ago, I took the
red pill: I started using the <a href="http://colemak.com/">Colemak</a> keyboard layout.</p>

<p></p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/posts/colemak_qwerty_3d.png' width='' height='' alt='Comparison of QWERTY and Colemak keyboard layouts with letter frequencies. Graphics by Pavel Pavlov.'><span class='caption-text'>Comparison of QWERTY and Colemak keyboard layouts with letter frequencies. Graphics by Pavel Pavlov.</span></span></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In the image above, the QWERTY and Colemak keyboard layouts are shown with the
height of each key set to the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Letter_frequency#Relative_frequencies_of_letters_in_the_English_language">frequency</a> with which it is
used. With this view, a pattern becomes obvious: The most often used keys are
scattered in QWERTY and collected on the home row in Colemak (pronounced
Coal-Mac). This means that you have to move your fingers much less in Colemak.
In fact, the home row has only around ⅓ of keystrokes in QWERTY while in
Colemak it has ¾ in English. The backspace key that is also used fairly often
is also changed from an awkward pinky stretch to a prime location on the home
row: where the caps lock key used to be.</p>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/posts/CmkNew_IBM-DIY_90d-erw.png' width='' height='' alt='Colemak Keyboard Figure (IBM style) by <a href="https://github.com/DreymaR">Øystein Bech Gadmar</a>, <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a>, caps lock key retouched, colors adjusted.&#8217;><span class='caption-text'>Colemak Keyboard Figure (IBM style) by <a href="https://github.com/DreymaR">Øystein Bech Gadmar</a>, <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a>, caps lock key retouched, colors adjusted.</span></span></p>

<p>Typing on Colemak is very smooth. Besides reducing the distance your fingers
have to travel, it also makes transitions from one letter to the next pleasant.
This is for example done by reducing repeated use of the same finger. QWERTY
repeats the same finger in some frequent <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bigram">bigrams</a> (sequences of two
letters) such as <em>ed</em>, <em>de</em>, <em>ce</em>, <em>my</em>, and <em>un</em>. They might seem
inconspicuous, but they disrupt the flow of typing, and the latter two also
jump two rows. To type out
<em><a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/1661">The Adventures of Sherlock Holmes</a></em> you would type 21782
same-finger bigrams on QWERTY and 5503 on Colemak. (On both layouts you would
in addition type 10095 same <em>letter</em> bigrams (<em>ll</em>, <em>ee</em>, etc.), but those are
not easily avoided.)</p>

<p>Longer sequences also flow smoothly. This is partly because they consist of the
shorter sequences mentioned above, which are themselves pleasant, and partly
because of <em>rolls</em>. These are sequences that just &ldquo;roll&rdquo; off your fingers. For
example, the common <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trigram">trigrams</a> <em>ing</em>, <em>the</em>, <em>ent</em>, and <em>tio</em> flow
in one direction over the keyboard, left-to-right or right-to-left, making them
easy to type. Rolls on the same hand are even better: T<strong>hey</strong>, c<strong>oul</strong>d,
sh<strong>oul</strong>d, l<strong>ast</strong>, fi<strong>rst</strong>, med<strong>ium</strong>, cl<strong>ien</strong>t, ar<strong>oun</strong>d, sh<strong>arp</strong>,
<strong>arg</strong>ument. These (common) sequences almost makes typing fun!</p>

<p>But in the end, Colemak is a good balance of many desirable properties: Minimal
finger movement, smooth transitions, less work for the weaker fingers, a good
balance between hand alternation and rolls, and a good balance between right
and left hand.</p>

<p>As someone who works with computers all day, these past four years have been
much more comfortable due to Colemak. Therefore I would like to say thank you
to Shai Coleman for creating Colemak, and the Colemak <a href="http://forum.colemak.com/">community</a>
for encouragement and many discussions!</p>

<p></p>

<p>Below, some frequently asked questions, and my answers to them.</p>

<a name="Frequently.Asked.Questions"></a>
<h2>Frequently Asked Questions</h2>

<a name="Does.it.work.on.my.computer."></a>
<h3>Does it work on my computer?</h3>

<p>Yes. It&rsquo;s built into Mac OS X, Linux (X.org), *BSD, ChromeOS, Android, iOS
(for external keyboards), etc. Basically all the cool kids. You can also get
and customize it on Windows (even without admin privileges) with <a href="http://www.autohotkey.com/">AutoHotKey</a>
or <a href="http://pkl.sourceforge.net/">Portable Keyboard Layout</a>, OS X with <a href="http://scripts.sil.org/cms/scripts/page.php?site_id=nrsi&amp;id=ukelele">Ukelele</a>, and Linux
with X.org xkb (built in). See <a href="http://colemak.com/Download">Colemak downloads</a>.</p>

<a name="Do.I.need.a.new..physical..keyboard."></a>
<h3>Do I need a new (physical) keyboard?</h3>

<p>No. Key labels are not good for touch typing on any layout. And only frequently
used keys change in Colemak compared to QWERTY, so the rare ones even keep
their correct labels if you need a peek for those.</p>

<a name="But.wait..why.touch.type.at.all."></a>
<h3>But wait, why touch type at all?</h3>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Touch_typing">Touch typing</a> means that you type without looking at the
keyboard or your hands. This means you can keep your focus on your work, which
avoids the overhead of switching your attention.</p>

<p>If you do not currently touch type, you can
kill two stones with one bird
by
learning touch typing on Colemak. It&rsquo;s also more fun because you start typing
real words instead of permutations of <em>fjdksl</em>!</p>

<p></p>

<a name="How.much.time.does.it.take.to.learn."></a>
<h3>How much time does it take to learn?</h3>

<p>Check out <a href="http://forum.colemak.com/viewforum.php?id=6">users&#8217; experiences</a> on the forum! For me
it took a couple of weeks to reach a workable level, and a couple of months to
become proficient.</p>

<p>Since then, a new and probably more comfortable method has paved the way for
learning Colemak: the <a href="http://forum.colemak.com/viewtopic.php?id=1858">Tarmak transitional layouts</a>.
Instead of switching all keys at once and being generally confused, you change
a few keys, adapt, change a few more, adapt again. This way, you can stay
fairly productive during the whole transition period. It&rsquo;s really quite clever.</p>

<p></p>

<a name="What.about.other.people.using.your.computer."></a>
<h3>What about other people using your computer?</h3>

<p>If you want to share the computer with others, all major OSes allow some quick
keyboard shortcut to switch layouts. If not, consider your alternative layout
a deterrent ;-)</p>

<a name="What.about.using.other.people.s.computers."></a>
<h3>What about using other people&rsquo;s computers?</h3>

<p>While primarily using an alternative layout, some people retain their ability
to type QWERTY, and others do not. <a href="http://www.ryanheise.com/colemak/">Here</a> are some tips on
retaining proficiency in both layouts.</p>

<p>Personally I lost interest in QWERTY after a few weeks of using Colemak. Now
I hunt and peck when I use other people&rsquo;s computers and enjoy the comfortable
99% of the time on my own computers.</p>

<p></p>

<a name="What.about.other.alternative.layouts."></a>
<h3>What about other alternative layouts?</h3>

<p>Colemak is neither the first nor the last attempt at a better keyboard layout.
It is however one of the better ones so far. You can see a comparison of
keyboard layouts at <a href="http://mkweb.bcgsc.ca/carpalx/?popular_alternatives">carpalx</a>.</p>

<a name="Does.it.work.for.my.language."></a>
<h3>Does it work for my language?</h3>

<p>Yes, probably. Colemak is made for English, but it supports <a href="http://colemak.com/Multilingual">many languages</a>
in the sense that you can type the necessary special characters and accents. It
is also likely that the letters that are most common in English (and therefore
easy to type on Colemak), are also frequent in your own language. It might not
be a perfect match, but it&rsquo;s probably a lot better than QWERTY and its cousins
(QWERTZ, AZERTY).</p>

<p>The special characters are inserted using the AltGr key. If you type 90%
English and 10% something else, AltGr will probably do fine. If your balance is
closer to 50/50, you could make a localized version of Colemak, or find an
existing one. There are no official Colemak versions available for languages
other than English (but there are some unofficial ones by the community).</p>

<p>The official approach is to use the standard Colemak including US style
punctuation symbol locations and use some punctuation keys for the most common
extra characters in your language (the less-than/greater-than key found between
Shift and Z on most non-US keyboards is a good first choice). For example, in
<a href="http://practicalcryptography.com/cryptanalysis/letter-frequencies-various-languages/french-letter-frequencies/">French</a>, &lsquo;é&rsquo; is frequent (2.4%) and a good
candidate for a dedicated key, while &lsquo;ê&rsquo; (0.1%) is not and can be typed using
the standard Colemak AltGr layer.</p>

<p>Another approach is to start with your native keyboard layout and drop in the
Colemak letter block. I will show that below because that is my own approach.
The reason to do this is the same reasoning that is behind Colemak proper:
Avoid moving low frequency keys (such as punctuation and rare letters). They
take longer to relearn because you practice them less often.</p>

<p>As a side note, if you don&rsquo;t type so much English but still want a better
layout, you could look for something made for your own language, for example
German (de-ergo, NEO, ADNW), French (Bépo, Dvorak-fr, bvofrak), Dutch (De
Correspondent), or Portuguese (pt-Nativo).</p>

<a name="Does.it.work.for.Danish."></a>
<h3>Does it work for Danish?</h3>

<p>Yes, see the section above. The main difference between Danish and English is
the addition of Æ, Ø, and Å. At 0.87%, 0.94%, and 1.19% respectively, they are
not extremely <a href="http://practicalcryptography.com/cryptanalysis/letter-frequencies-various-languages/danish-letter-frequencies/">frequent</a>. But on the other hand,
their sum is 3.0%, and having to reach for AltGr 2-3 times per sentence is more
than I want. (However, this can be made much easier by putting AltGr on the
Caps Lock location.)</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/posts/colemak_dk.png' width='' height='' alt='Danish Colemak. The shaded keys have moved compared to Danish QWERTY.'><span class='caption-text'>Danish Colemak. The shaded keys have moved compared to Danish QWERTY.</span></span></p>

<p>My solution keeps Ø and Å in their regular locations, while Æ only moves one
position up &mdash; like the semicolon key in English.</p>

<p>On top of that I have made some <a href="https://bitbucket.org/erw/colemak/src/default/dk">changes</a> to facilitate programming,
such as putting the brackets {[]} on AltGr-neio, putting backslash on the
½ key. These types of modifications are personal and you will probably want
something else. If you are a programmer, you can also use the &ldquo;standard&rdquo;
solution which is to use the US English layout (whether QWERTY or Colemak).</p>

<p></p>

<a name="What.about..Vim...vim_category.."></a>
<h3>What about <a href="/blog/categories/vim/">Vim</a>?</h3>

<p>The first difference you notice is that <em>j</em> and <em>k</em> have moved away from the
home row &mdash; and rightly so, because in typing, they are very rare: 0.22% and
0.81%. There are many options. Some people use vim as-is. Either because they
don&rsquo;t feel the need for any changes, or because they use the arrow keys anyway
(in which case I would recommend learning <em>hjkl</em>).</p>

<p></p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/posts/colemak_vim_erw.png' width='' height='' alt='Vim remapping for Colemak'><span class='caption-text'>Vim remapping for Colemak</span></span></p>

<p>Some people make only minimal changes to Vim (see for example the end of
<a href="http://www.ryanheise.com/colemak/">this page</a>) while others use the opportunity to do a
<a href="http://forum.colemak.com/viewtopic.php?id=50">major refurnishing</a>.
My own approach is in between but conceptually simple. Keys are shifted around
two loops: <em>k</em>-<em>n</em>-<em>j</em>-<em>e</em> and <em>i</em>-<em>l</em>. This restores the normal <em>hjkl</em>
navigation cluster and puts next match <em>n</em> back on its previous location.
Insert <em>i</em> and end <em>e</em> are now on L and J. (You can memorize it as &lsquo;linsert&rsquo;
and &lsquo;jend&rsquo; until muscle memory takes over.) You can source <a href="https://bitbucket.org/erw/colemak/src/default/colemak.vim">my mappings</a>
from your .vimrc to try it out.</p>

<p></p>

<a name="What.about.using.an.Ergonomic.keyboard.instead."></a>
<h3>What about using an Ergonomic keyboard instead?</h3>

<p>That is a good idea.
Especially if it has a <a href="http://deskthority.net/wiki/Staggering#Matrix_layout">columnar or matrix</a> key layout.
Then it might even be better for comfort than switching layout.
The two approaches can also be combined.
That&rsquo;s what I do, but more on that later. (<a href="/2018/04/14/my-weird-keyboard/">Link!</a>)</p>

<p>Thanks for reading!</p>

<p><em>Update 2018-04-14: Added link to my Kinesis Advantage post.</em></p>

<p></p>

<p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
