<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: productivity | Erik Ramsgaard Wognsen]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/blog/categories/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/"/>
  <updated>2017-11-19T16:01:54+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.erw.dk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Ramsgaard Wognsen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Work Helps Me Beat Procrastination]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2017/01/22/work-helps-me-beat-procrastination/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-22T17:23:59+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2017/01/22/work-helps-me-beat-procrastination</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p></p>

<p>Back in school, I put off essay writing until the night before the due date. In
gymnasium/high school, I put off assignments until the <em>morning</em> of the due
date. In my first years of university it went so far that a student counsellor
suggested that maybe university wasn&rsquo;t for me.</p>

<p>Despite&mdash;or perhaps because of&mdash;that, I pulled myself together. After passing
some courses that especially triggered my procrastination, I did much better,
and eventually emerged with a master&rsquo;s degree in software engineering and a PhD
in computer science.</p>

<p>But that does not mean I had completely overcome procrastination, especially
not during the PhD study. It was not until <a href="/2016/05/09/leaving-academia/">leaving academia</a> for the
IT business that I experienced what it is like to get control of my
procrastination. (It&rsquo;s amazing, by the way.)</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></li>
</ul>


<a name="My.Job"></a>
<h2>My Job</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s ironic that procrastination means postponing work, but my job actually
helps me avoid procrastination. I&rsquo;ll try to figure out why that is. To that
end, I&rsquo;ll first describe my job. It includes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Designing software solutions meeting the clients&#8217; requirements.</li>
<li>Implementing (programming) software solutions according to designs approved
by the clients.</li>
<li>Registering the time spent on all tasks in our time tracking system.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Doing.It.for.Others"></a>
<h2>Doing It for Others</h2>

<p>There are many aspects of the above that contribute to procrastinating less.
One of them, I think, is that this is the first time in my education and work
life that people who ask me to do something want me to do it for <em>their</em> sake.</p>

<p>Beating procrastination often requires external deadlines and reasons. In
education of all levels, teachers ask us to do exercises, homework,
assignments, semester projects, theses. But while they ask you, and systems may
be in place to punish those who do not comply, the requests are not truly
external. The purpose is that <em>you</em> learn, not (necessarily) that <em>they want</em>
to read your work.</p>

<p>Compulsory education contains more external pressure to learn than higher
education (which is probably why procrastination gets worse the higher you get
in the education system). In a job, you get back some external pressure, and
this time they care more about what they get out of it than what you get out of
it.</p>

<p></p>

<p>Although external reasons (and payment!) are good reasons to work, they are
unfortunately not enough to fight procrastination.</p>

<a name="Implementation.Tasks.are.Well-Defined"></a>
<h2>Implementation Tasks are Well-Defined</h2>

<p>One of the causes for procrastination is perfectionism. Often the desire to
find the perfect solution to a problem puts so much pressure on you that you do
not even succeed in finding a good-enough solution. Simply taking a step
towards finding the perfect solution feels like a futile step towards
a possibly unachievable goal, so let&rsquo;s just look a cat videos on YouTube
instead.</p>

<p>Working to implement a preapproved design means that the biggest decisions have
already been made, whether by yourself or by others, and locked in by the
client. Now your task is not to solve the original business problem, but simply
to implement the designed solution in the alotted time.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Simply&rdquo; does not mean to imply that it&rsquo;s easy. A high level of expertise is
required to write correct, robust, efficient, and maintainable code. But with
well-defined goals for the programming, the task is constrained enough that
a skilled procrastinator (skilled at programming, that is) can attack the task
head-on rather than postpone it.</p>

<p>I do still get ideas to change the design while working to implement it, but
the bureaucracy involved in changing it is actually a good thing here because
it keeps me from trying, unless I&rsquo;m convinced it&rsquo;s necessary. It&rsquo;s better to
have a good solution done on time than a perfect solution that isn&rsquo;t.</p>

<p></p>

<a name="Implementation.Tasks.are.Divisible"></a>
<h2>Implementation Tasks are Divisible</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not just that implementation tasks are easier when the design is fixed.
It&rsquo;s also that the they can be broken into smaller parts that are even easier
to do.</p>

<p>The first subtask is to understand the design and hold a mental model of it.
Depending on the level of detail in the design description, this can itself
turn into clarifying discussions with the author, but that is also fairly
well-defined.</p>

<p>Many of the remaining subtasks are taken from a repertoire that includes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Adding required tables and fields to the database</li>
<li>Identifying required data and writing queries to retrieve it</li>
<li>Adding the business logic</li>
<li>Testing the solution, and adding error handling and logging</li>
</ul>


<p></p>

<a name="Time.Tracking"></a>
<h2>Time Tracking</h2>

<p>Next up is the time tracking we are required to do. While working a task, any
task, we register the time spent in an issue tracker. Our issue trackers are
then connected to the time tracking system, and in the time tracking system
each week has to sum up to the number of hours our contract states before we
can &ldquo;close&rdquo; that week. It&rsquo;s cold, mechanical, and unsympathetic, and it works
wonders in beating procrastination.</p>

<a name="Design.Tasks.Can.Make.You.Proud"></a>
<h2>Design Tasks Can Make You Proud</h2>

<p></p>

<p>Design is the process of turning the client&rsquo;s requirements into a consistent
and implementable description in terms of the business domain. Sometimes this
requires several iterations with client feedback and further changes before the
design is approved. A design can also be a change to a previously implemented
module or feature.</p>

<p>If it&rsquo;s a change request, it&rsquo;s fairly simple: read up on documentation and code
until you hold a good-enough mental model of the existing functionality. From
there, seeing where changes are required, is often obvious.</p>

<p>If it&rsquo;s a new module or feature, it may be harder to get started. That&rsquo;s where
one of the risks of procrastination hide. However, two things can mitigate
this. The first is <em>structured procrastination</em>: While putting off the daunting
design task, work on something else productive like a straightforward
implementation task (as opposed to watching cat videos on YouTube). At least
you&rsquo;re doing something productive.</p>

<p>The second thing is that once you do get it cracked and have your initial idea
for the general direction of the design, a feeling of ownership and pride
starts to grow. This will make it much easier to keep the focus.</p>

<p></p>

<p>All in all, my job helps me keep my procrastination in check, which I&rsquo;m very
happy about. I hope all you other procrastinators out there can see that your
circumstances can help you beat procrastination, if you haven&rsquo;t cracked the
code yet.</p>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Keep Track With a Year at a Glance]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.erw.dk/2016/01/10/keep-track-with-a-year-at-a-glance/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-10T19:32:58+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.erw.dk/2016/01/10/keep-track-with-a-year-at-a-glance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/posts/floss.jpg' width='' height='' alt='The calendar helped me floss (more or less) daily.'><span class='caption-text'>The calendar helped me floss (more or less) daily.</span></span></p>

<p>If you are already starting to forget about your New Year&rsquo;s resolutions, here&rsquo;s
a tip to keep going: Visualize your progress: Put X&rsquo;s on a calendar on every
day you do what whatever you want to do more of. Stick the calendar on the wall
or wherever it would remind you of your goal.</p>

<p></p>

<p>Some years back, each time I visited my dentist, she recommended that I floss.
And I would decide that <em>this time</em> I would start doing it. But some days
later, I started slipping and forgetting about it. It wasn&rsquo;t until I put
a year-at-a-glance calendar on the bathroom cabinet door that the habit stuck.</p>

<p>Putting a mark on a calendar is not rocket science, but the satisfaction of
marking a completed task and of seeing your progress is a mental reward that
can make a big difference. If you want to try, I made a one page 2016 calendar
you can print (<a href="/files/cal2016.odt">LibreOffice/odt</a>,
<a href="/files/cal2016.docx">Word/docx</a>). (It was easily made with the open source
ncal utility, invoked as <code>ncal -bh 2016</code>.)</p>

<!-- more -->


<a name="Don.t.Break.the.Chain"></a>
<h2>Don&rsquo;t Break the Chain</h2>

<p>For goals that can practically be done every day, it&rsquo;s not just having many
marks on the calendar that is important. A further motivation is to keep the
chain of successful days unbroken. (This method is widely known as the
<a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=seinfeld+strategy">Seinfeld Strategy</a>, even though Jerry Seinfeld says
<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/1ujvrg/jerry_seinfeld_here_i_will_give_you_an_answer/ceitfxh">it wasn&rsquo;t his idea</a>.)
For workouts or other things that you might not have time to do every day, you
could still use the chain method by using a list of weeks of the year, and
checking off each week that met your goal, say, doing at least two workouts. Or
maybe drinking at most three bottles of soda that week.</p>

<p>The chain method is also used in games and apps. For example, the app
<a href="http://www.memrise.com/">Memrise</a> shows me my learning streak, or unbroken chain of days that
I learn/memorize words or images in my chosen topic. Showing the streak has
helped me to learn <a href="http://www.memrise.com/course/42769/country-mapping/">the world map</a> for five minutes a day, 234
days in a row today. (The streak trick worked better than even the designers
anticipated &ndash; the app crashed when trying to award me a 200-day badge.)</p>

<p></p>

<a name="Not.Just.for.Resolutions"></a>
<h2>Not Just for Resolutions</h2>

<p>The fine art of putting marks on a calendar is not just for New Year&rsquo;s
resolutions. I find it useful for anything I want to track. For example, I use
one to remember when I last watered my chili plant. Or put a mark when you
vacuum clean. Then you can see both when it would be a good idea to do it
again, and in the long run, how often you do it &ndash; if you&rsquo;re interested in that
sort of thing. Happy tracking!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
